[
  {
    "question": "1. How does the height of the tropopause normally vary with latitude in the northern hemisphere ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It remains constant throughout the year.",
      "b. It remains constant from north to south.",
      "c. It increases from south to north.",
      "d. It decreases from south to north."
    ],
    "answer": "d. It decreases from south to north."
  },
  {
    "question": "2. What, approximately, is the average height of the tropopause over the equator ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 40 km",
      "b. 8 km",
      "c. 11 km",
      "d. 16 km"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 16 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "3. In which layer is most of the atmospheric humidity concentrated ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Troposphere.",
      "b. Tropopause.",
      "c. Stratosphere.",
      "d. Stratopause."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Troposphere."
  },
  {
    "question": "4. What is the boundary layer between troposphere and stratosphere called?",
    "options": [
      "a. Tropopause.",
      "b. Ionosphere.",
      "c. Stratosphere.",
      "d. Atmosphere."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Tropopause."
  },
  {
    "question": "5. Which of the following cloud types can project up into the stratosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulonimbus",
      "b. Cirrostratus",
      "c. Altocumulus",
      "d. Altostratus"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "6. Which one of the following statements applies to the tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is, by definition, a temperature inversion",
      "b. It is, by definition, an isothermal layer",
      "c. It indicates a strong temperature lapse rate",
      "d. It separates the troposphere from the stratosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It separates the troposphere from the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "7. The thickness of the troposphere varies with",
    "options": [
      "a. latitude",
      "b. longitude",
      "c. rotation of the earth",
      "d. the wind"
    ],
    "answer": "a. latitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "8. What is the approximate composition of the dry air by volume in the troposphere ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 21 % oxygen, 78 % nitrogen, and the rest other gasses",
      "b. 10 % oxygen, 89 % nitrogen, and the rest other gasses",
      "c. 88 % oxygen, 9 % nitrogen, and the rest other gasses",
      "d. 50 % oxygen, 40 % nitrogen, and the rest other gasses"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 21 % oxygen, 78 % nitrogen, and the rest other gasses"
  },
  {
    "question": "9. Which layer of the atmosphere contains more than 90 per cent of all water vapour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Troposphere",
      "b. Lower stratosphere",
      "c. Upper stratosphere",
      "d. Ionosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "10. Going from the equator to the north pole, the altitude of the tropopause",
    "options": [
      "a. increases and its temperature increases",
      "b. decreases and its temperature increases",
      "c. increases and its temperature decreases",
      "d. decreases and its temperature decreases"
    ],
    "answer": "b. decreases and its temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "11. The troposphere is the",
    "options": [
      "a. part of the atmosphere above the stratosphere",
      "b. part of the atmosphere below the tropopause",
      "c. boundary between the mesosphere and thermosphere",
      "d. boundary between the stratosphere and the mesosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "b. part of the atmosphere below the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "12. The tropopause is a level at which",
    "options": [
      "a. vertical currents are strongest",
      "b. water vapour content is greatest",
      "c. pressure remains constant",
      "d. temperature ceases to fall with increasing height"
    ],
    "answer": "d. temperature ceases to fall with increasing height"
  },
  {
    "question": "13. The tropopause is lower",
    "options": [
      "a. south of the equator than north of it",
      "b. in summer than winter in moderate latitudes",
      "c. over the North Pole than over the equator",
      "d. over the equator than over the South Pole"
    ],
    "answer": "c. over the North Pole than over the equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "14. The average height of the tropopause at 50\u00b0N is about",
    "options": [
      "a. 14 km",
      "b. 8 km",
      "c. 11 km",
      "d. 16 km"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 11 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "15. The height and the temperature of the tropopause are respectively in the order of",
    "options": [
      "a. 8 km and -40\u00b0C over the equator",
      "b. 16 km and -75\u00b0C over the equator",
      "c. 8 km and - 75\u00b0C over the poles",
      "d. 16 km and -40\u00b0C over the poles"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 16 km and -75\u00b0C over the equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "16. The troposphere",
    "options": [
      "a. has a greater vertical extent above the equator than above the poles",
      "b. contains all oxygen of the stratosphere",
      "c. is the separation layer between the stratosphere and atmosphere",
      "d. reaches the same height at all latitudes"
    ],
    "answer": "a. has a greater vertical extent above the equator than above the poles"
  },
  {
    "question": "17. In the mid-latitudes the stratosphere extends on an average from",
    "options": [
      "a. 85 to more than 200 km",
      "b. 0 to 11 km",
      "c. 50 to 85 km",
      "d. 11 to 50 km"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 11 to 50 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "18. A temperature increase with altitude through a layer is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Heating aloft.",
      "b. An inversion.",
      "c. An extension.",
      "d. Unstable air."
    ],
    "answer": "b. An inversion."
  },
  {
    "question": "19. The layer of the Earth\u00b4s atmosphere which most concerns aviators is called the:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratosphere.",
      "b. Tropopause.",
      "c. Troposphere.",
      "d. Equatorial zone."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Troposphere."
  },
  {
    "question": "20. The percentage concentration of gases in the atmosphere is constant from the surface of the earth to a certain altitude with the exception of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Oxygen",
      "b. Nitrogen",
      "c. Hydrogen",
      "d. Water vapour"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Water vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "21. Define the tropopause:",
    "options": [
      "a. A relatively thin layer, or boundary zone, which separates the lower atmosphere from the tropopause",
      "b. That area where the temperature change does not exceed two-thirds of one degree Celsius per thousand foot increase in altitude over a range of 6000 feet.",
      "c. That area where the temperature change does not exceed two-thirds of one degree Celsius per thousand foot increase in altitude independent of latitude.",
      "d. A relatively thick layer or boundary zone below the troposphere."
    ],
    "answer": "b. That area where the temperature change does not exceed two-thirds of one degree Celsius per thousand foot increase in altitude over a range of 6000 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "22. The region of the atmosphere which is normally stable and has few clouds is known as the:",
    "options": [
      "a. Tropopause",
      "b. Troposphere",
      "c. Stratosphere",
      "d. Jetstream"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "23. The lowest layer in the atmosphere is:",
    "options": [
      "a. The Stratosphere",
      "b. The Troposphere",
      "c. The Mesosphere",
      "d. The Heavi Side Layer"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The Troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "24. The layer of the atmosphere above the tropopause is known as the:",
    "options": [
      "a. Troposphere",
      "b. Stratosphere",
      "c. Mesosphere",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "25. What is the primary cause of all changes in the Earth's weather?",
    "options": [
      "a. Variation of solar energy at the Earth's surface",
      "b. Changes in air pressure over the Earth's surface",
      "c. Movement of air masses from moist areas to dry areas",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Variation of solar energy at the Earth's surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "26. What is a characteristic of the troposphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. It contains all the moisture of the atmosphere",
      "b. There is an overall decrease of temperature with an increase of altitude",
      "c. The average altitude of the top of the troposphere is about 8 kilometres",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "b. There is an overall decrease of temperature with an increase of altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "27. What weather feature occurs at altitude levels near the tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. Maximum winds and narrow wind shear zones",
      "b. Abrupt temperature increase above the tropopause",
      "c. Thin layers of cirrus clouds at the tropopause level",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Maximum winds and narrow wind shear zones"
  },
  {
    "question": "28. Which feature is associated with the tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. Absence of wind and turbulence",
      "b. Absolute upper limit of cloud formation",
      "c. Abrupt change of temperature lapse rate",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Abrupt change of temperature lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "29. The boundary layer between troposphere and stratosphere is called",
    "options": [
      "a. Ionosphere",
      "b. Tropopause",
      "c. Stratopause",
      "d. Atmosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "30. What is the average temperature of the tropical tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. -75\u00b0C",
      "b. -65\u00b0C",
      "c. -56,5\u00b0C",
      "d. -40\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -75\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "31. Which statement is true concerning the tropopause from the equator to the poles?",
    "options": [
      "a. The tropopause decreases, the tropopause temperature increases",
      "b. The tropopause decreases, the tropopause temperature decreases",
      "c. The tropopause increases, the tropopause temperature increases",
      "d. The tropopause increases, the tropopause temperature decreases"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The tropopause decreases, the tropopause temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "32. Which layer of the atmosphere contains more than 90 % of the total amount of water vapour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Troposphere",
      "b. Lower stratosphere",
      "c. Higher stratosphere",
      "d. Ionosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "33. What can be said about the temperature in the lower stratosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature is constant",
      "b. The temperature is increasing",
      "c. The temperature is decreasing",
      "d. The temperature is first increasing and then decreasing"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The temperature is constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "34. At a certain position, the temperature on the 300 hPa chart is -48\u00b0C; according to the tropopause chart, the tropopause is at FL 330. What is the most likely temperature at FL 350 ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -56,5\u00b0C.",
      "b. -50\u00b0C.",
      "c. -54\u00b0C.",
      "d. -58\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "c. -54\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "35. What is the most likely temperature at the tropical tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. -55\u00b0C.",
      "b. -75\u00b0C.",
      "c. -35\u00b0C.",
      "d. -25\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "b. -75\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "36. The 0\u00b0 isotherm is forecast to be at FL 50. At what FL would you expect a temperature of -6\u00b0 C?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 110",
      "b. FL 20",
      "c. FL 100",
      "d. FL 80"
    ],
    "answer": "d. FL 80"
  },
  {
    "question": "37. In the lower part of the stratosphere the temperature",
    "options": [
      "a. decreases with altitude",
      "b. is almost constant",
      "c. increases with altitude",
      "d. increases at first and decreases afterward"
    ],
    "answer": "b. is almost constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "38. Which is true of the temperature at the tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is higher in polar regions than in equatorial regions",
      "b. It is higher in equatorial regions than in polar regions",
      "c. It is highest in middle latitudes",
      "d. There is no significant difference with change of latitude"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It is higher in polar regions than in equatorial regions"
  },
  {
    "question": "39. As altitude increases, the weight of the atmosphere above you will:",
    "options": [
      "a. decrease",
      "b. remain the same",
      "c. increase",
      "d. increase with 1,5 kg/m2 pr 1000 ft."
    ],
    "answer": "a. decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "40. An inversion is characterized by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Constant temperature with increasing altitude",
      "b. Parts of the air mass at each level is warmer than surrounding air.",
      "c. The tendency to increase relative humidity with increasing altitude.",
      "d. Increasing temperature with increasing altitude."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Increasing temperature with increasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "41. While flying at FL 120, you notice an OAT of -2\u00b0C. At which altitude do you expect the freezing level to be?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 110",
      "b. FL 130",
      "c. FL 150",
      "d. FL 90"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 110"
  },
  {
    "question": "42. Several physical processes contribute to atmospheric warming. Which of the following contribute the most ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Absorption and evaporation.",
      "b. Solar radiation and conduction.",
      "c. Absorption and vaporization.",
      "d. Convection and condensation."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Convection and condensation."
  },
  {
    "question": "43. Convective activity over land in mid-latitudes is greatest in",
    "options": [
      "a. winter in the afternoon.",
      "b. winter during the night and early morning.",
      "c. summer during the night and early morning.",
      "d. summer in the afternoon."
    ],
    "answer": "d. summer in the afternoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "44. Advection is :",
    "options": [
      "a. the same as convection",
      "b. vertical motion of air",
      "c. the same as subsidence",
      "d. horizontal motion of air"
    ],
    "answer": "d. horizontal motion of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "45. The radiation of the sun heats",
    "options": [
      "a. the air in the troposphere only directly if no clouds are present",
      "b. the air in the troposphere directly",
      "c. the water vapour in the air of the troposphere",
      "d. the surface of the earth, which heats the air in the troposphere"
    ],
    "answer": "d. the surface of the earth, which heats the air in the troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "46. The majority of troposphere heating is the result of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation of the sun",
      "b. Heating from the ground below",
      "c. Re-radiation of the sun's rays from the surface of the earth",
      "d. Re-radiation from the clouds."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Heating from the ground below"
  },
  {
    "question": "47. Why is a calm and clear-sky night cooler than a cloudy night?",
    "options": [
      "a. The clouds prevent radiation from the atmosphere",
      "b. There is radiation from the clouds",
      "c. The radiation from the earth's surface slips into space.",
      "d. Due to contents of carbon dioxide."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The radiation from the earth's surface slips into space."
  },
  {
    "question": "48. A layer is conditionally unstable if the air",
    "options": [
      "a. is unstable for saturated air as well as for dry air.",
      "b. is stable for saturated air and unstable for dry air.",
      "c. becomes stable by lifting it.",
      "d. is unstable for saturated air and stable for dry air."
    ],
    "answer": "d. is unstable for saturated air and stable for dry air."
  },
  {
    "question": "49. Absolute instability exists whenever the environmental lapse rate",
    "options": [
      "a. exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate.",
      "b. exceeds the dry adiabatic lapse rate.",
      "c. is less than the saturated adiabatic lapse rate.",
      "d. is between the dry and saturated adiabatic lapse rate."
    ],
    "answer": "b. exceeds the dry adiabatic lapse rate."
  },
  {
    "question": "50. In an air mass with no clouds the surface temperature is 15\u00b0C and 13\u00b0C at 1000m. This layer of air is:",
    "options": [
      "a. unstable",
      "b. stable",
      "c. a layer of heavy turbulence",
      "d. conditionally unstable"
    ],
    "answer": "b. stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "51. An inversion is a layer of air which is",
    "options": [
      "a. absolutely unstable",
      "b. absolutely stable",
      "c. conditionally unstable",
      "d. conditionally stable"
    ],
    "answer": "b. absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "52. The environmental lapse rate in an actual atmosphere",
    "options": [
      "a. has a fixed value of 2\u00b0C/1000 FT",
      "b. has a fixed value of 1\u00b0C/100m",
      "c. has a fixed value of 0.65\u00b0C/100m",
      "d. varies with time"
    ],
    "answer": "d. varies with time"
  },
  {
    "question": "53. The dry adiabatic lapse rate has a value of",
    "options": [
      "a. 0.5\u00b0C/100m",
      "b. 2\u00b0C/1000FT",
      "c. 0.65\u00b0C/100m",
      "d. 1\u00b0C/100m"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1\u00b0C/100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "54. The dry adiabatic lapse rate",
    "options": [
      "a. has a constant fixed value",
      "b. is greater in summer than in winter",
      "c. is greater during the night than during the day",
      "d. has a variable value"
    ],
    "answer": "a. has a constant fixed value"
  },
  {
    "question": "55. An air mass is called stable when",
    "options": [
      "a. the vertical motion of rising air tends to become weaker and disappears",
      "b. the temperature in a given air mass decreases rapidly with height",
      "c. the pressure in a given area is constant",
      "d. the environmental lapse rate is high, with little vertical motion of air currents"
    ],
    "answer": "a. the vertical motion of rising air tends to become weaker and disappears"
  },
  {
    "question": "56. In still air the temperature decreases at an average of 1.2\u00b0C per 100 m increase in altitude. This temperature change is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. saturated adiabatic lapse rate",
      "b. environmental lapse rate",
      "c. dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "d. normal lapse rate"
    ],
    "answer": "b. environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "57. A layer can be",
    "options": [
      "a. unstable for unsaturated air and conditionally unstable",
      "b. stable for saturated air and unstable for unsaturated air",
      "c. unstable for unsaturated air and neutral for saturated air",
      "d. stable for unsaturated air and unstable for saturated air"
    ],
    "answer": "d. stable for unsaturated air and unstable for saturated air"
  },
  {
    "question": "58. When in the upper part of a layer warm air is advected the",
    "options": [
      "a. stability increases in the layer",
      "b. stability decreases in the layer",
      "c. wind will back with increasing height in the northern hemisphere",
      "d. wind speed will always decrease with increasing height in the northern hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. stability increases in the layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "59. From which of the following pieces of information can the stability of the atmosphere be derived?",
    "options": [
      "a. Surface temperature",
      "b. Environmental lapse rate",
      "c. Dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "d. Pressure at the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "60. The value of the saturated adiabatic lapse rate is closest to that of the dry adiabatic lapse rate in",
    "options": [
      "a. cumulus",
      "b. freezing fog",
      "c. stratus",
      "d. cirrus"
    ],
    "answer": "d. cirrus"
  },
  {
    "question": "61. The weather is clear and the temperature decreases uniformly and rapidly as you climb (approaching 3\u00b0C per 1000 ft), you have an indication of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stable air.",
      "b. Unstable air.",
      "c. Saturation.",
      "d. Sublimation."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Unstable air."
  },
  {
    "question": "62. Absolute instability in a layer of air is characterized by the vertical temperature gradient in the layer being:",
    "options": [
      "a. Greater than 1\u00b0/100 m.",
      "b. Greater than 0.5\u00b0/100 m.",
      "c. Less than 0.65\u00b0/100 m.",
      "d. Less than 0.6\u00b0/100 m."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Greater than 1\u00b0/100 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "63. What is meant by \"standard lapse rate\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature increases as height increases",
      "b. Temperature decreases as height increases",
      "c. Temperature remains constant as height increases",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Temperature decreases as height increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "64. The lapse rate for a dry parcel of air is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 3\u00b0C/1000ft",
      "b. 1.5\u00b0C/1000ft",
      "c. 1.98\u00b0C/1000ft",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 3\u00b0C/1000ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "65. An environmental lapse rate is observed to be 2.5C/1000ft. Which of the following is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. A dry parcel of air would be stable if it was forced to rise",
      "b. A saturated parcel of air would be stable if it was forced to rise",
      "c. A dry parcel of air would be unstable if it was forced to rise",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A dry parcel of air would be stable if it was forced to rise"
  },
  {
    "question": "66. What feature is associated with a temperature inversion?",
    "options": [
      "a. A stable layer of air",
      "b. An unstable layer of air",
      "c. Air mass thunderstorms",
      "d. Cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A stable layer of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "67. What is indicated about an air mass if the temperature remains unchanged or decreases slightly as altitude is increased?",
    "options": [
      "a. The air is usntable",
      "b. A temperature inversion exists",
      "c. The air is stable",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The air is stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "68. Which condition is present when a local parcel of air is stable?",
    "options": [
      "a. The parcel of air resists convection",
      "b. The parcel of air cannot be forced uphill",
      "c. As the parcel of air moves upward, its temperature becomes warmer than the surrounding air",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The parcel of air resists convection"
  },
  {
    "question": "69. How can the stability of the atmosphere be determined?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ambient temperature lapse rate",
      "b. Atmospheric pressure at various levels",
      "c. Surface temperature/dewpoint spread.",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ambient temperature lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "70. From which of the following pieces of information can stability of the atmosphere be derived?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "b. Pressure at the surface",
      "c. Surface temperature",
      "d. Environmental lapse rate"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "71. State the preference of a layer of air with no clouds, surface temperature 15\u00b0C, and 13\u00b0C at 1000 metres:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stable layer",
      "b. Unstable layer",
      "c. The preference cannot be determined",
      "d. None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Stable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "72. What is the preference of a layer with constant temperature?",
    "options": [
      "a. Absolutely stable",
      "b. Unstable",
      "c. Relatively stable",
      "d. An example of an inversion"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "73. Which of the following is a common cause of ground or surface temperature inversion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Heating of the air by subsidence",
      "b. Warm air being lifted rapidly aloft, in the vicinity of mountainous terrain.",
      "c. The movement of colder air under warm air, or the movement of warm air over cold air.",
      "d. Terrestrial radiation on a clear night with no or very light winds."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Terrestrial radiation on a clear night with no or very light winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "74. Which of the following is a common result of subsidence ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Clear air turbulence at higher altitudes .",
      "b. CB-clouds and thunderstorms over a large area.",
      "c. Wide spread NS and AS clouds and intense precipitation.",
      "d. An inversion over a large area with haze, mist."
    ],
    "answer": "d. An inversion over a large area with haze, mist."
  },
  {
    "question": "75. What characteristic is associated with a temperature inversion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stability",
      "b. Instability",
      "c. Clear ice",
      "d. Area of active storms"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "76. What is the technical term for an increase in temperature with altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. Subsidence",
      "b. Inversion",
      "c. Adiabatic",
      "d. Advection"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "77. An inversion is a layer of air in which the temperature",
    "options": [
      "a. increases with height more than 1\u00b0C/100m",
      "b. remains constant with height",
      "c. increases with height",
      "d. decreases with height more than 1\u00b0C/100m"
    ],
    "answer": "c. increases with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "78. An isothermal layer is a layer of air in which the temperature",
    "options": [
      "a. increases with height at a constant rate",
      "b. increases with height",
      "c. decreases with height at a constant rate",
      "d. remains constant with height"
    ],
    "answer": "d. remains constant with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "79. An inversion is",
    "options": [
      "a. an increase of temperature with height",
      "b. an increase of pressure with height",
      "c. a decrease of pressure with height",
      "d. a decrease of temperature with height"
    ],
    "answer": "a. an increase of temperature with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "80. A significant inversion at low height is a characteristic of",
    "options": [
      "a. the passage of cold front",
      "b. nocturnal radiation",
      "c. advection fog",
      "d. cumulus clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "b. nocturnal radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "81. What is meant by \"inversion\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature increases as height increases",
      "b. Temperature decreases as height increases",
      "c. Temperature remains constant as height increases",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Temperature increases as height increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "82. What is meant by \"isothermal layer\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature increases as height increases",
      "b. Temperature decreases as height increases",
      "c. Temperature remains constant as height increases",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Temperature remains constant as height increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "83. Where is a common location for an inversion?",
    "options": [
      "a. At the tropopause",
      "b. In the stratosphere",
      "c. At the base of cumulus clouds",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "b. In the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "84. A temperature increase with increasing altitude is called",
    "options": [
      "a. Subsidence",
      "b. Inversion",
      "c. Adiabate",
      "d. Advection"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Inversion"
  },
    {
    "question": "85. Continuous freezing rain is observed at an airport. Which would be the most probable vertical temperature lapse rate?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "d. D"
  },
  {
    "question": "86. What is the cause for a surface temperature inversion?",
    "options": [
      "a. The presence of a high pressure area",
      "b. The presence of a polar front depression",
      "c. Moist, unstable air, and a lifting action",
      "d. By heavy radiational cooling at night of the lowest layer of air, or if warm air moves in over a colder surface"
    ],
    "answer": "d. By heavy radiational cooling at night of the lowest layer of air, or if warm air moves in over a colder surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "87. The diurnal variation in temperature is largest when the sky is",
    "options": [
      "a. clear and winds are strong",
      "b. clear and winds are weak",
      "c. overcast and winds are weak",
      "d. overcast and winds are strong"
    ],
    "answer": "b. clear and winds are weak"
  },
  {
    "question": "88. Around Paris on January 3rd at 1800 UTC, the surface temperature, under shelter, is 3\u00b0C. The sky is covered by 8 oktas of stratus. QNH is 1033 hPa. If the sky is covered all night, the minimum temperature of the night of January 3rd to January 4th should be",
    "options": [
      "a. slightly above +3\u00b0C.",
      "b. significantly below 0\u00b0C.",
      "c. slightly below +3\u00b0C.",
      "d. significantly above +3\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "c. slightly below +3\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "89. On a clear sky, continental ground surface, wind calm, the minimum temperature is reached approximately",
    "options": [
      "a. at the moment the sun rises",
      "b. half an hour before sunrise",
      "c. half an hour after sunrise",
      "d. one hour before sunrise"
    ],
    "answer": "c. half an hour after sunrise"
  },
  {
    "question": "90. Temperature variation during 24 hours is least over:",
    "options": [
      "a. Sea.",
      "b. Grass.",
      "c. Mountain.",
      "d. Forest."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Sea."
  },
  {
    "question": "91. Over which of the following surface types would you expect the greatest diurnal range of temperature to occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. An extensive forest area",
      "b. A desert area",
      "c. An ocean",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A desert area"
  },
  {
    "question": "92. What positions are connected by isobars on the surface weather chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. Positions with the same air pressure at a given level",
      "b. Positions with the same temperature at a given level",
      "c. Positions with the same wind velocity at a given level",
      "d. Positions with the same relative pressure heights"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Positions with the same air pressure at a given level"
  },
  {
    "question": "93. The isobars drawn on a surface weather chart represent lines of equal pressure",
    "options": [
      "a. at a determined density altitude",
      "b. at flight level",
      "c. at height of observatory",
      "d. reduced to sea level"
    ],
    "answer": "d. reduced to sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "94. The station pressure used in surface weather charts is",
    "options": [
      "a. QNE",
      "b. QFE",
      "c. QNH",
      "d. QFF"
    ],
    "answer": "d. QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "95. Isobars on a surface chart are lines of equal",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE",
      "b. QFF",
      "c. QNE",
      "d. QNH"
    ],
    "answer": "b. QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "96. The pressure system at position 'b' is a",
    "options": [
      "a. ridge of high pressure",
      "b. secondary low",
      "c. trough of low pressure",
      "d. col"
    ],
    "answer": "d. col"
  },
  {
    "question": "97. The pressure distribution located mainly at point B is a",
    "options": [
      "a. depression",
      "b. col",
      "c. trough of low pressure",
      "d. ridge of high pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "d. ridge of high pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "98. At sea level, the pressure of the atmosphere on a standard day will cause the mercury in the column to rise to:",
    "options": [
      "a. 92.29 inches",
      "b. 19.19 inches",
      "c. 29.29 inches",
      "d. 29.92 inches"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 29.92 inches"
  },
  {
    "question": "99. What is dynamic pressure?",
    "options": [
      "a. Turbulence.",
      "b. Pressure caused by movement.",
      "c. Acceleration force.",
      "d. Centrifugal force."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Pressure caused by movement."
  },
  {
    "question": "100. The unit of pressure most commonly used in meteorology is:",
    "options": [
      "a. kg /cm2.",
      "b. lbs/inch2.",
      "c. hPa",
      "d. tons/m2."
    ],
    "answer": "c. hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "101. Lines connecting points of equal pressure are called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Isogonic lines.",
      "b. Isobars.",
      "c. Agonic.",
      "d. Barometric."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "102. A line on a chart joining places of equal sea level pressure is called an:",
    "options": [
      "a. Isogonal",
      "b. Agonic line",
      "c. Isobar",
      "d. Isotherm"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Isobar"
  },
  {
    "question": "103. What is the pressure in surface weather charts called?",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE",
      "b. QFF",
      "c. QNH",
      "d. QNE"
    ],
    "answer": "b. QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "104. What can be said about isobars?",
    "options": [
      "a. Isobars appear on meteorological surface charts",
      "b. Isobars are lines of equal temperature",
      "c. Certain information can be depicted with the isobars on upper level charts",
      "d. Isobars show wind speeds around a jet stream area"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Isobars appear on meteorological surface charts"
  },
  {
    "question": "105. In the troposphere the decrease of pressure per 100 m increase in height",
    "options": [
      "a. is greater at higher levels than at lower levels.",
      "b. remains constant at all levels.",
      "c. is smaller at higher levels than at lower levels.",
      "d. is in the order of 27 hPa near MSL."
    ],
    "answer": "c. is smaller at higher levels than at lower levels."
  },
  {
    "question": "106. What is the approximate vertical interval which is equal to a pressure change of 1 hPa at an altitude of 5500 m ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15 m (50 FT).",
      "b. 8 m (27 FT).",
      "c. 32 m (105 FT).",
      "d. 64 m (210 FT)."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 15 m (50 FT)."
  },
  {
    "question": "107. Which of the following is true concerning atmospheric pressure ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is higher in winter than in summer",
      "b. It decreases with height",
      "c. It is higher at night than during the day",
      "d. It always decreases with height at a rate of 1 hPa per 8m"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It decreases with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "108. An isohypse (contour)",
    "options": [
      "a. indicates the altitude of the zero degree isotherm",
      "b. is the longest slope line of a frontal surface",
      "c. is the limit between two air masses of different temperature",
      "d. indicates the true altitude of a pressure level"
    ],
    "answer": "d. indicates the true altitude of a pressure level"
  },
  {
    "question": "109. The rate of fall of pressure with height is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Greater in cold air than in warm air",
      "b. Greater in warm air than in cold air",
      "c. Inversely proportional to temperature",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Greater in cold air than in warm air"
  },
  {
    "question": "110. The average change of pressure with height in the lower atmosphere is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1 hPa/27ft",
      "b. 1 hPa/20ft",
      "c. 1 hPa/50ft",
      "d. 1 hPa/56 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1 hPa/27ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "111. The isohypse 2960 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. 850 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "112. The isohypse 1620 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. 850 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 850 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "113. The isohypse 11880 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. 850 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 200 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "114. The isohypse 5700 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 200 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "115. The isohypse 8760 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 200 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "116. At which average height can the 700 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 3,0 km AMSL",
      "b. 5,5 km AMSL",
      "c. 9,0 km AMSL",
      "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 3,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "117. At which average height can the 500 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 3,0 km AMSL",
      "b. 5,5 km AMSL",
      "c. 9,0 km AMSL",
      "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 5,5 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "118. At which average height can the 200 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 3,0 km AMSL",
      "b. 5,5 km AMSL",
      "c. 9,0 km AMSL",
      "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "119. At which average height can the 300 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1,5 km AMSL",
      "b. 3,0 km AMSL",
      "c. 9,0 km AMSL",
      "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 9,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "120. At which average height can the 850 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1,5 km AMSL",
      "b. 3,0 km AMSL",
      "c. 9,0 km AMSL",
      "d. 12,0 km AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1,5 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "121. What is the value for a pressure change of 1 hPa at an altitude of 5500 m?",
    "options": [
      "a. approx. 8 m (27ft)",
      "b. approx. 16 m (54 ft)",
      "c. approx. 32 m (105 ft)",
      "d. approx. 64 m (210 ft)"
    ],
    "answer": "b. approx. 16 m (54 ft)"
  },
  {
    "question": "122. In order to calculate QFE from QNH, which of the following must be known ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Elevation and the temperature at the airfield.",
      "b. Temperature at the airfield.",
      "c. Elevation of the airfield and the temperature at MSL.",
      "d. Elevation of the airfield."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Elevation of the airfield."
  },
  {
    "question": "123. The QFF at an airfield located 400 metres above sea level is 1016 hPa. The air temperature is 10\u00b0C higher than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "options": [
      "a. Less than 1016 hPa",
      "b. 1016 hPa",
      "c. More than 1016 hPa",
      "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
    ],
    "answer": "c. More than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "124. The QFF at an airfield located 400 metres above sea level is 1016 hPa. The air temperature is 10\u00b0C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is not possible to give a definitive answer",
      "b. More than 1016 hPa",
      "c. 1016 hPa",
      "d. Less than 1016 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Less than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "125. The QNH at an airfield located 200 metres above sea level is 1009 hPa. The air temperature is 10\u00b0C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QFF?",
    "options": [
      "a. Less than 1009 hPa",
      "b. 1009 hPa",
      "c. More than 1009 hPa",
      "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
    ],
    "answer": "c. More than 1009 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "126. The QNH at an airfield located 200 metres above sea level is 1022 hPa. The air temperature is not available. What is the QFF?",
    "options": [
      "a. Less than 1022 hPa",
      "b. More than 1022 hPa",
      "c. 1022 hPa",
      "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
  },
  {
    "question": "127. The QNH at an airfield located 0 metres above sea level is 1022 hPa. The air temperature is not available. What is the QFF?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is not possible to give a definitive answer",
      "b. Less than 1022 hPa",
      "c. More than 1022 hPa",
      "d. 1022 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1022 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "128. The QNH at an airfield in California located 69 metres below sea level is 1018 hPa. The air temperature is 10\u00b0C higher than a standard atmosphere. What is the QFF?",
    "options": [
      "a. More than 1018 hPa",
      "b. Less than 1018 hPa",
      "c. 1018 hPa",
      "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
    ],
    "answer": "a. More than 1018 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "129. The QFF at an airfield in California located 69 metres below sea level is 1030 hPa. The air temperature is 10\u00b0C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is not possible to give a definitive answer",
      "b. Less than 1030 hPa",
      "c. 1030 hPa",
      "d. More than 1030 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. More than 1030 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "130. If the QFE at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 980 hPa, what is the approximate QNH ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1015 hPa",
      "b. 1000 hPa",
      "c. 1005 hPa",
      "d. 1010 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1005 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "131. If the QFE at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1000 hPa, what is the approximate QNH?",
    "options": [
      "a. 985 hPa",
      "b. 1025 hPa",
      "c. 990 hPa",
      "d. 1035 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1025 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "132. If the QNH at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1015 hPa, what is the approximate QFE? (Assume 1hPa = 8m)",
    "options": [
      "a. 1005 hPa",
      "b. 995 hPa",
      "c. 1000 hPa",
      "d. 990 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 990 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "133. If the QNH at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1025 hPa, what is the approximate QFE?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1005 hPa",
      "b. 995 hPa",
      "c. 1000 hPa",
      "d. 1025 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1000 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "134. QNH is defined as",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE reduced to MSL using the values of the standard atmosphere",
      "b. pressure at MSL in the standard atmosphere",
      "c. pressure at MSL in the actual atmosphere",
      "d. QFE reduced to MSL using the values of the actual atmosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. QFE reduced to MSL using the values of the standard atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "135. In order to reduce QFE to QNH, which of the following item(s) must be known ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Elevation of the airfield and the temperature at the airfield",
      "b. Temperature at the airfield",
      "c. Elevation of the airfield and the temperature at MSL",
      "d. Elevation of the airfield"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Elevation of the airfield"
  },
  {
    "question": "136. At an airport (400 m AMSL), a QFF of 1016 hPa and a temperature 10\u00b0C higher than ISA is observed:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QNH is higher than 1016 hPa",
      "b. The QNH is lower than 1016 hPa",
      "c. The QNH equals 1016 hPa",
      "d. The QNH cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The QNH is higher than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "137. At an airport (400 m AMSL), a QFF of 1016 hPa and a temperature 10\u00b0C lower than ISA is observed:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QNH is higher than 1016 hPa",
      "b. The QNH is lower than 1016 hPa",
      "c. The QNH equals 1016 hPa",
      "d. The QNH cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The QNH is lower than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "138. At an airport (200 m AMSL), a QNH of 1009 hPa and a temperature 10\u00b0C lower than ISA is observed:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QFF is higher than 1016 hPa",
      "b. The QFF is lower than 1016 hPa",
      "c. The QFF equals 1009 hPa",
      "d. The QFF cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The QFF is higher than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "139. At an airport (200 m AMSL), a QNH of 1022 hPa is observed and the temperature is unknown:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QFF is higher than 1022 hPa",
      "b. The QFF is lower than 1022 hPa",
      "c. The QFF equals 1022 hPa",
      "d. The QFF cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The QFF cannot be determined"
  },
  {
    "question": "140. At an airport (0 m AMSL), a QNH of 1022 hPa is observed and the temperature is unknown:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QFF is higher than 1022 hPa",
      "b. The QFF is lower than 1022 hPa",
      "c. The QFF equals 1022 hPa",
      "d. The QFF cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The QFF equals 1022 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "141. At an airport in California (69 m below MSL), a QNH of 1018 hPa and a temperature 10\u00b0C higher than standard is observed:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QFF is higher than 1018 hPa",
      "b. The QFF is lower than 1018 hPa",
      "c. The QFF equals 1018 hPa",
      "d. The QFF cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The QFF is higher than 1018 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "142. At an airport in California (69 m below MSL), a QFF of 1030 hPa and a temperature 10\u00b0C lower than standard is observed:",
    "options": [
      "a. The QNH is higher than 1030 hPa",
      "b. The QNH is lower than 1030 hPa",
      "c. The QNH equals 1030 hPa",
      "d. The QNH cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The QNH is higher than 1030 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "143. QFE 980 hPa at an altitude of 200 m AMSL: What will the approximate QNH be?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1000 hPa",
      "b. 1005 hPa",
      "c. 1010 hPa",
      "d. 1015 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1005 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "144. QFE 1000 hPa at an altitude of 200 m AMSL: What will the approximate QNH be?",
    "options": [
      "a. 985 hPa",
      "b. 990 hPa",
      "c. 1025 hPa",
      "d. 1035 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1025 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "145. QNH 1015 hPa at an altitude of 200 m AMSL: What will the approximate QFE be?",
    "options": [
      "a. 990 hPa",
      "b. 995 hPa",
      "c. 1000 hPa",
      "d. 1005 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 990 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "146. QNH 1025 hPa at an altitude of 200 m AMSL: What will the approximate QFE be?",
    "options": [
      "a. 995 hPa",
      "b. 1000 hPa",
      "c. 1005 hPa",
      "d. 1025 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1000 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "147. State the definition for QNH:",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient",
      "b. QFF reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient",
      "c. QFE reduced to MSL, using actual temperature gradient",
      "d. QNE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient"
    ],
    "answer": "a. QFE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "148. State the definition for QFF:",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient",
      "b. QNH reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient",
      "c. QFE reduced to MSL, using actual temperature gradient",
      "d. QNE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient"
    ],
    "answer": "c. QFE reduced to MSL, using actual temperature gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "149. Which value has to be known to calculate the QNH out of the QFE?",
    "options": [
      "a. Field elevation",
      "b. Actual temperature",
      "c. The relative humidity of the air",
      "d. The density altitude of the field"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Field elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "150. Which statement is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. QNH can be equal to QFE",
      "b. QNH is always lower than QFE",
      "c. QFE is always lower than QNH",
      "d. QFE can be equal to QFF only"
    ],
    "answer": "c. QFE is always lower than QNH"
  },
  {
    "question": "151. State the definition for QNH:",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure reduced to sea level, using the standard temperature gradient",
      "b. QFF reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient",
      "c. QFE reduced to MSL, using actual temperature gradient",
      "d. QNE reduced to MSL, using standard temperature gradient"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Pressure reduced to sea level, using the standard temperature gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "152. At FL 180, the air temperature is -35\u00b0C.The air density at this level is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Greater than the density of the ISA atmosphere at FL 180.",
      "b. Less than the density of the ISA atmosphere at FL 180.",
      "c. Equal to the density of the ISA atmosphere at FL 180.",
      "d. Unable to be determined without knowing the QNH."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Greater than the density of the ISA atmosphere at FL 180."
  },
  {
    "question": "153. Under what condition does pressure altitude have the same value as density altitude ?",
    "options": [
      "a. When the altimeter has no position error.",
      "b. At sea level when the temperature is 0\u00b0C.",
      "c. At standard temperature.",
      "d. When the altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa."
    ],
    "answer": "c. At standard temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "154. Half the mass of the atmosphere is found in the first",
    "options": [
      "a. 11 km",
      "b. 3 km",
      "c. 8 km",
      "d. 5 km"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 5 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "155. Stratiform clouds indicate stable air. Flight generally will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. Rough with good visibility.",
      "b. Smooth with low ceiling and visibility.",
      "c. Smooth with good visibility.",
      "d. Smooth with moderate turbulence and good visibility."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Smooth with low ceiling and visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "156. In relation to 'air density' which of the following responses are correct:",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold air is less dense than warm air.",
      "b. Dry warm air is less dense than cold air.",
      "c. If the temperature is decreasing the air density will decrease",
      "d. Air density is not influenced of air humidity."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Dry warm air is less dense than cold air."
  },
  {
    "question": "157. Which of the following combinations contain the greatest air density?",
    "options": [
      "a. High pressure and high temperature.",
      "b. High pressure and low temperature.",
      "c. Low pressure and high temperature.",
      "d. Low pressure and low temperature."
    ],
    "answer": "b. High pressure and low temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "158. Air density is mass of air per unity of volume, and is influenced by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure, latitude and season.",
      "b. Pressure, temperature and the amount of water vapour.",
      "c. Altitude",
      "d. both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. both b) and c) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "159. Which statement is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. Air density generally increases as altitude increases",
      "b. Air density generally stays the same as altitude increases",
      "c. Air density generally decreases as altitude increases",
      "d"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Air density generally decreases as altitude increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "160. The lowest assumed temperature in the International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is :",
    "options": [
      "a. -44.7\u00b0C",
      "b. -273\u00b0C",
      "c. -56.5\u00b0C",
      "d. -100\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -56.5\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "161. A 200 hPa pressure altitude level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 50.",
      "b. FL 300.",
      "c. FL 100.",
      "d. FL 390."
    ],
    "answer": "d. FL 390."
  },
  {
    "question": "162. The temperature at FL 140 is -12\u00b0C. What will the temperature be at FL 110 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -9\u00b0C.",
      "b. -18\u00b0C.",
      "c. -6\u00b0C.",
      "d. -15\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "c. -6\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "163. An outside air temperature of -35\u00b0C is measured while cruising at FL 200. What is the temperature deviation from the ISA at this level?",
    "options": [
      "a. 5\u00b0C colder than ISA.",
      "b. 10\u00b0C warmer than ISA.",
      "c. 5\u00b0C warmer than ISA.",
      "d. 10\u00b0C colder than ISA."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 10\u00b0C colder than ISA."
  },
  {
    "question": "164. How does temperature vary with increasing altitude in the ICAO standard atmosphere below the tropopause?",
    "options": [
      "a. At first it increases and higher up it decreases",
      "b. Increases",
      "c. Decreases",
      "d. Remains constant"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "165. What is the vertical temperature lapse rate, up to 11 km, in the standard ICAO atmosphere ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 2\u00b0C per 1000 m",
      "b. 4.5\u00b0C per 1000 m",
      "c. 3\u00b0C per 1000 m",
      "d. 6.5\u00b0C per 1000 m"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 6.5\u00b0C per 1000 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "166. The temperature at FL 80 is +6\u00b0C. What will the temperature be at FL 130 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "options": [
      "a. +2\u00b0C",
      "b. -6\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. -4\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. -4\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "167. The temperature at FL 110 is -5\u00b0C. What will the temperature be at FL 50 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -3\u00b0C",
      "b. +3\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. +7\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. +7\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "168. The temperature at FL 160 is -22\u00b0C. What will the temperature be at FL 90 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -4\u00b0C",
      "b. -8\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. +4\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -8\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "169. A temperature of +15\u00b0C is recorded at an altitude of 500 metres above sea level. If the vertical temperature gradient is that of a standard atmosphere, what will the temperature be at the summit of a mountain, 2500 metres above sea level?",
    "options": [
      "a. +4\u00b0C",
      "b. +2\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. -2\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. +2\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "170. How would you characterise an air temperature of -15\u00b0C at the 700 hPa level over western Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Within +/-5\u00b0C of ISA",
      "b. High",
      "c. Low",
      "d. 20\u00b0C below standard"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Within +/-5\u00b0C of ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "171. How would you characterise an air temperature of -30\u00b0C at the 300 hPa level over western Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Very low",
      "b. Within +/-5\u00b0C of ISA",
      "c. Low",
      "d. High"
    ],
    "answer": "d. High"
  },
  {
    "question": "172. How would you characterise an air temperature of -55\u00b0C at the 200 hPa level over western Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Within +/-5\u00b0C of ISA",
      "b. High",
      "c. Low",
      "d. Very high"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Within +/-5\u00b0C of ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "173. A 300 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 100",
      "b. FL 390",
      "c. FL 300",
      "d. FL 50"
    ],
    "answer": "c. FL 300"
  },
  {
    "question": "174. A 500 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 180",
      "b. FL 160",
      "c. FL 100",
      "d. FL 390"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 180"
  },
  {
    "question": "175. A 700 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 100",
      "b. FL 180",
      "c. FL 300",
      "d. FL 390"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "176. A 850 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 300",
      "b. FL100",
      "c. FL 50",
      "d. FL 390"
    ],
    "answer": "c. FL 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "177. If you are flying at FL 300 in an air mass that is 15\u00b0C warmer than a standard atmosphere, what is the outside temperature likely to be?",
    "options": [
      "a. -30\u00b0C",
      "b. -45\u00b0C",
      "c. -60\u00b0C",
      "d. -15\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -30\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "178. If you are flying at FL 100 in an air mass that is 10\u00b0C warmer than a standard atmosphere, what is the outside temperature likely to be?",
    "options": [
      "a. +15\u00b0C",
      "b. +5\u00b0C",
      "c. -10\u00b0C",
      "d. -15\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. +5\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "179. If you are flying at FL 120 and the outside temperature is -2\u00b0C, at what altitude will the \"freezing level\" be?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 110",
      "b. FL 130",
      "c. FL 150",
      "d. FL 90"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 110"
  },
  {
    "question": "180. The temperature at 10000 FT in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "options": [
      "a. -20\u00b0C",
      "b. 0\u00b0C",
      "c. -5\u00b0C",
      "d. -35\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -5\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "181. The rate of decrease of temperature with height per 100 m in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "options": [
      "a. 0.65\u00b0C",
      "b. 1\u00b0C",
      "c. 0.5\u00b0C",
      "d. variable"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 0.65\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "182. In the International Standard Atmosphere the decrease in temperature with height below 11 km is",
    "options": [
      "a. 1\u00b0C per 100m",
      "b. 0.65\u00b0C per 100m",
      "c. 0.5\u00b0C per 100m",
      "d. 0.6\u00b0C per 100m"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 0.65\u00b0C per 100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "183. Which statement is correct regarding the International Standard Atmosphere ?",
    "options": [
      "a. At MSL temperature is 15\u00b0C and pressure is 1013.25hPa",
      "b. At MSL temperature is 15\u00b0C and the decrease in temperature with height is 1\u00b0C per 100m",
      "c. At MSL temperature is 10\u00b0C and the decrease in temperature with height is 1\u00b0C per 100m",
      "d. At MSL pressure is 1013.25 hPa and the decrease of temperature with height is 1\u00b0C per 100m"
    ],
    "answer": "a. At MSL temperature is 15\u00b0C and pressure is 1013.25hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "184. In what hPa range is an upper weather chart for FL 340 situated?",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 - 200 hPa",
      "b. 400 - 300 hPa",
      "c. 500 - 400 hPa",
      "d. 600 - 500 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 300 - 200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "185. The international standard atmosphere (ISA)is defined for mean sea level as :",
    "options": [
      "a. 1015.25 hPa, 15\u00b0C, and a density of 1.225 kg/m3.",
      "b. 1015.25 hPa, 15\u00b0C, with a lapse rate of 1.98\u00b0C per 1000 ft.",
      "c. 1013.25 hPa, 15\u00b0C, a temperature lapse rate of 1.98\u00b0C per 1000 ft. and a humidity of 5%.",
      "d. 1013.25 hPa, 15\u00b0C, a temperature lapse rate of 1.98\u00b0C per 1000 ft. and a density of 1.225 kg/m3"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1013.25 hPa, 15\u00b0C, a temperature lapse rate of 1.98\u00b0C per 1000 ft. and a density of 1.225 kg/m3"
  },
  {
    "question": "186. The temperature gradient in the international standard atmosphere (ISA) is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1\u00b0C/100m.",
      "b. 0,5\u00b0C/100m.",
      "c. 0.65\u00b0C/100m",
      "d. 0.6\u00b0C/100m."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 0.65\u00b0C/100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "187. The temperature at sea level in the ISA is:",
    "options": [
      "a. +12,5\u00b0C",
      "b. +25\u00b0C",
      "c. +15\u00b0C",
      "d. 0\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. +15\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "188. The pressure at sea level in the ISA is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1012.35 hPa",
      "b. 1025.13 hPa",
      "c. 1013.25 hPa",
      "d. 29,95 in Hg"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1013.25 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "189. At an altitude of 500 m AMSL, a temperature of +15\u00b0C is measured. What will the temperature be at an altitude of 2500 m, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. +4\u00b0C",
      "b. +2\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. -2\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. +2\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "190. FL 80, an OAT +06\u00b0C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 130, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. -4\u00b0C",
      "b. +2\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. -6\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -4\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "191. FL 110, an OAT -05\u00b0C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 50, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. -3\u00b0C",
      "b. +3\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. +7\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. +7\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "192. FL 140, an OAT -12\u00b0C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 110, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. +2\u00b0C",
      "b. -2\u00b0C",
      "c. -6\u00b0C",
      "d. -18\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -6\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "193. FL 160, an OAT -22\u00b0C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 90, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. -8\u00b0C",
      "b. -4\u00b0C",
      "c. +4\u00b0C",
      "d. 0\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -8\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "194. An OAT of -15\u00b0C at the 700 hPa pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. equals approximately (+/-5\u00b0C) ISA",
      "b. is high",
      "c. is low",
      "d. is almost impossible"
    ],
    "answer": "c. is low"
  },
  {
    "question": "195. An OAT of -30\u00b0C at the 300 hPa pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. equals approximately (+/-5\u00b0C) ISA",
      "b. is high",
      "c. is low",
      "d. is almost impossible"
    ],
    "answer": "b. is high"
  },
  {
    "question": "196. An OAT of -55\u00b0C at the 200 hPa pressure level:",
    "options": [
      "a. equals approximately (+/-5\u00b0C) ISA",
      "b. is high",
      "c. is low",
      "d. is almost impossible"
    ],
    "answer": "a. equals approximately (+/-5\u00b0C) ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "197. An aircraft cruises at FL 300 in an airmass, which is 15\u00b0C warmer than the Standard Atmosphere. The OAT is therefore....",
    "options": [
      "a. -60\u00b0C",
      "b. -30\u00b0C",
      "c. -45\u00b0C",
      "d. -15\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -30\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "198. An aircraft cruises at FL 100 in an airmass, which is 10\u00b0C warmer than the Standard Atmosphere. The OAT is therefore....",
    "options": [
      "a. -10\u00b0C",
      "b. -15\u00b0C",
      "c. +5\u00b0C",
      "d. +15\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. +5\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "199. You cruise at FL 200 and notice an OAT of -35\u00b0C. The airmass has therefore an average temperature which is....",
    "options": [
      "a. 5\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "b. 20\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "c. 10\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "d. 5\u00b0C colder than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 10\u00b0C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "200. What is the ISA temperature at FL 110?",
    "options": [
      "a. -7\u00b0C",
      "b. +7\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C",
      "d. -5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -7\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "201. What is the temperature decrease in the ISA?",
    "options": [
      "a. 0,65\u00b0C/100 m",
      "b. 0,65\u00b0C/1000 ft",
      "c. 2\u00b0C/100 m",
      "d. 1\u00b0C/100 m"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 0,65\u00b0C/100 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "202. A temperature of 10\u00b0C above ISA is observed at FL 180. What is the effective distance between FL 60 and FL 120?",
    "options": [
      "a. 6240 ft",
      "b. 6000 ft",
      "c. 5760 ft",
      "d. 3000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 6240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "203. You intend to overfly a mountain range. The recommended minimum flight altitude is, according to the aviation chart, 15000 FT/AMSL. The air mass that you will fly through is on average 15\u00b0C warmer than the standard atmosphere. The altimeter is set to QNH (1023 hPa). At what altimeter reading will you effectively be at the recommended minimum flight altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15900 FT.",
      "b. 13830 FT.",
      "c. 14370 FT.",
      "d. 14100 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 13830 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "204. You are flying at FL 130, and your true altitude is 12000 FT. What is the temperature deviation from that of the standard atmosphere at FL 130 (QNH 1013,2 hPa) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. ISA +12\u00b0C",
      "b. ISA +/-0\u00b0C",
      "c. ISA +20\u00b0C",
      "d. ISA -20\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. ISA -20\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "205. The QNH of an airport at sea level is 983 hPa and the temperature deviation from ISA is -15\u00b0C below FL 100. What is the true altitude of FL 100?",
    "options": [
      "a. 9790 FT.",
      "b. 10210 FT.",
      "c. 8590 FT.",
      "d. 11410 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 8590 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "206. You plan a flight over a mountain range at a true altitude of 15000 FT/AMSL. The air is on an average 15\u00b0C colder than ISA, the pressure at sea level is 1003 hPa. What indication must the altimeter (setting 1013.2 hPa) read?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15690 FT.",
      "b. 16170 FT.",
      "c. 14370 FT.",
      "d. 13830 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 16170 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "207. During a flight at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1015 hPa), an aircraft remains at a constant true altitude. The reason for this is that :",
    "options": [
      "a. the air at Marseille is colder than that at Palma de Mallorca.",
      "b. the altimeters are erroneous, and need to be tested.",
      "c. the air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca.",
      "d. one of the two QNH values may be incorrect."
    ],
    "answer": "c. the air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca."
  },
  {
    "question": "208. Which of the following conditions would cause the altimeter to indicate a lower altitude than that actually flown ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure altitude the same as indicated altitude.",
      "b. Atmospheric pressure lower than standard",
      "c. Air temperature higher than standard",
      "d. Air temperature lower than standard."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Air temperature higher than standard"
  },
  {
    "question": "209. An aircraft flying at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1006 hPa) experiences no change to true altitude. The reason for this is that :",
    "options": [
      "a. the altimeters are erroneous, and need to be tested",
      "b. the air at Palma de Mallorca is colder than that at Marseille",
      "c. the air at Palma de Mallorca is warmer than that at Marseille",
      "d. one of the two QNH values may be incorrect"
    ],
    "answer": "c. the air at Palma de Mallorca is warmer than that at Marseille"
  },
  {
    "question": "210. During a flight over the sea at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1012 hPa), the true altitude is constantly increasing. What action, if any, should be taken ?",
    "options": [
      "a. None, the reason for the change is that the air around Palma is warmer than the air around Marseille",
      "b. Have your altimeter checked, because its readings are obviously wrong",
      "c. Recheck the QNH because one of the QNH values must be wrong",
      "d. Compensate by heading further to the left"
    ],
    "answer": "a. None, the reason for the change is that the air around Palma is warmer than the air around Marseille"
  },
  {
    "question": "211. During a flight over the sea at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1016 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1016 hPa), the true altitude is constantly decreasing. What is the probable reason for this ?",
    "options": [
      "a. One of the QNH values must be wrong",
      "b. The air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca",
      "c. The altimeter is faulty",
      "d. The aircraft is being blown off track to the left"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca"
  },
  {
    "question": "212. During a flight over the sea at FL 135, the true altitude is 13500 feet; local QNH is 1019 hPa. What information, if any, can be gained about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying?",
    "options": [
      "a. Its average temperature is the same as ISA",
      "b. It is colder than ISA",
      "c. It is warmer than ISA",
      "d. There is insufficient information to make any assumption"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It is colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "213. An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 90; the true altitude is 9100 feet; local QNH is unknown. What assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is colder than ISA",
      "b. There is insufficient information to make any assumption",
      "c. It is warmer than ISA",
      "d. Its average temperature is the same as ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "b. There is insufficient information to make any assumption"
  },
  {
    "question": "214. An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 120, with a true altitude of 12000 feet; local QNH is 1013 hPa. What assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is warmer than ISA",
      "b. It is colder than ISA",
      "c. Its average temperature is the same as ISA",
      "d. There is insufficient information to come to any conclusion"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Its average temperature is the same as ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "215. An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 100, with a true altitude of 10000 feet; local QNH is 1003 hPa. What assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "options": [
      "a. There is insufficient information to come to any conclusion",
      "b. Its average temperature is about ISA",
      "c. It is colder than ISA",
      "d. It is warmer than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It is warmer than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "216. An aircraft is flying through the Alps on a very cold winter's day. The regional QNH is 1013 hPa. During the flight, you circle around a mountain at an altitude of its summit. What reading will the aneroid altimeter give, compared to the elevation of the summit?",
    "options": [
      "a. The same altitude as the elevation of the summit",
      "b. A lower altitude than the elevation of the summit",
      "c. A higher altitude than the elevation of the summit",
      "d. There is insufficient information to come to a conclusion"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A higher altitude than the elevation of the summit"
  },
  {
    "question": "217. An aircraft is flying through the Alps on a warm summer's day. The weather is fine, and there is a high pressure system in the area. During the flight, a mountain is passed at an altitude of its summit. What reading will the aneroid altimeter give, compared to the summit's elevation?",
    "options": [
      "a. There is insufficient information to come to a conclusion",
      "b. A higher altitude than the elevation of the summit",
      "c. The same altitude as the elevation of the summit",
      "d. A lower altitude than the elevation of the summit"
    ],
    "answer": "d. A lower altitude than the elevation of the summit"
  },
  {
    "question": "218. An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B on the upper level contour chart. The altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa. Which of these statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B",
      "b. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A",
      "c. Wind speed at A is higher than at B",
      "d. Wind speed at Paris is higher than at B"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B"
  },
  {
    "question": "219. An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B on the upper level contour chart. The altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa. Which of these statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. Wind speed at A and at B is the same",
      "b. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A",
      "c. Wind speed at A is higher than at B",
      "d. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B"
  },
  {
    "question": "220. An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B on the upper level contour chart. The altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa. Which of these statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A",
      "b. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B",
      "c. Wind speed at Madrid is higher than at A",
      "d. Wind speed at B is higher than at A"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A"
  },
  {
    "question": "221. An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B on the upper level contour chart. The altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa. Which of these statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. The true altitude will be higher at A than at B",
      "b. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A",
      "c. Wind speed at A and at B is the same",
      "d. Wind speed at B is higher than at A"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The true altitude will be higher at B than at A"
  },
  {
    "question": "222. You are flying at FL 200. Outside air temperature is -40\u00b0C, and the pressure at sea level is 1033 hPa. What is the true altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 20660 feet",
      "b. 19340 feet",
      "c. 21740 feet",
      "d. 18260 feet"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 20660 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "223. You are flying at FL 160. Outside air temperature is -27\u00b0C, and the pressure at sea level is 1003 hPa. What is the true altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15630 feet",
      "b. 15090 feet",
      "c. 16370 feet",
      "d. 16910 feet"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 15090 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "224. You are planning to fly across a mountain range. The chart recommends a minimum altitude of 12000 feet above mean sea level. The air mass you will be flying through is an average 10\u00b0C warmer than ISA. Your altimeter is set to 1023 hPa (QNH of a nearby airport at nearly sea level). What altitude will the altimeter show when you have reached the recommended minimum altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 12210 feet",
      "b. 11520 feet",
      "c. 11250 feet",
      "d. 11790 feet"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 11520 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "225. The following temperatures have been observed over a station at 1200 UTC. Assume the station is at MSL. Height in feet. Temperature in degrees C. 20000.-12 18000.-11 16000.-10 14000.-10 12000.-6 10000.-2 8000. +2 6000. +6 4000. +12 2000. +15 surface+15.",
    "options": [
      "a. The layer between 16000 and 18000 FT is absolutely unstable",
      "b. The height of the freezing level over the station is approximately 12000 FT.",
      "c. The temperature at 10000 FT is in agreement with the temperature in the International Standard Atmosphere.",
      "d. Assuming that the MSL pressure is 1013.25 hPa the true altitude of an aircraft would actually be higher than the indicated altitude."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Assuming that the MSL pressure is 1013.25 hPa the true altitude of an aircraft would actually be higher than the indicated altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "226. Assume that an aircraft is flying in the northern hemisphere at the 500 hPa pressure surface on a heading of 270 degrees. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 180 degrees, then true altitude is increasing",
      "b. If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 360 degrees, then true altitude is increasing",
      "c. If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 270 degrees, then true altitude is increasing",
      "d. If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 090 degrees, then true altitude is increasing"
    ],
    "answer": "b. If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 360 degrees, then true altitude is increasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "227. An aircraft is flying at FL 180 on the northern hemisphere with a crosswind from the left. Which of the following is correct concerning its true altitude ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It remains constant",
      "b. It increases",
      "c. It decreases",
      "d. Without knowing temperatures at FL 180 this question can not be answered."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "228. The pressure altitude is equal to the true altitude if",
    "options": [
      "a. the outside air temperature is standard for that height",
      "b. standard atmospheric conditions occur",
      "c. the air pressure is 1013.25 hPa at the surface",
      "d. the indicated altitude is equal to the pressure altitude"
    ],
    "answer": "b. standard atmospheric conditions occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "229. The altimeter is connected to:",
    "options": [
      "a. The pitot tube.",
      "b. The dynamic system.",
      "c. The static system.",
      "d. The elevator."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The static system."
  },
  {
    "question": "230. In spite of a constant altimeter reading your aircraft is loosing altitude. This could be caused by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Flying towards high pressure.",
      "b. Flying towards low pressure.",
      "c. The standard air pressure has fallen.",
      "d. Increased temperature."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Flying towards low pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "231. An aircraft, flying so that the altimeter indicates 2500ft with the current regional QNH set in the subscale, is flying towards an area of lower pressure. If the pilot fails to revise the subscale setting as the QNH changes, then the aircraft will:",
    "options": [
      "a. Gradually climb",
      "b. Gradually descend",
      "c. Maintain 2500ft AMSL",
      "d. no assumption is possible"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Gradually descend"
  },
  {
    "question": "232. What condition would cause that your altimeter is indicating lower than actually flown?",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature higher than standard",
      "b. Temperature lower than standard",
      "c. Standard temperature",
      "d. Pressure lower than standard"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Temperature higher than standard"
  },
  {
    "question": "233. You fly over the sea at FL 90, TA 9100ft, QNH unknown. What can be assumpted ?",
    "options": [
      "a. No assumption is possible, because the information is not sufficient",
      "b. It is warmer than ISA",
      "c. It is colder than ISA",
      "d. The QNH is lower than 1013 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. No assumption is possible, because the information is not sufficient"
  },
  {
    "question": "234. Your altimeter is blocked at 1000 hPa. You have to overfly a mountain (8000 ft) with a terrain clearance of at least 1500 ft. What will be your indicated altitude when the QNH of a nearby airport is 990 hPa and the temperature is 10C colder than ISA?",
    "options": [
      "a. 10150 ft",
      "b. 10501 ft",
      "c. 8850 ft",
      "d. 9500 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 10150 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "235. You are flying at FL 100 in an airmass which is 15\u00b0C colder than ISA, local QNH 983. True altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 8590 ft",
      "b. 11'410 ft",
      "c. 10'000 ft",
      "d. 10'210 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 8590 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "236. Refer to the upper level chart: Flight path A - B, altimeter setting 1013,2 hPa:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your true altitude is higher in B than in A",
      "b. Your true altitude is higher in A than in B",
      "c. The wind speed is higher in A than in B",
      "d. The wind speed in A and in B is the same"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Your true altitude is higher in A than in B"
  },
  {
    "question": "237. Refer to the upper level contour chart: Flight path A - B, altimeter setting 1013,2 hPa:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your true altitude is higher in B than in A",
      "b. Your true altitude is higher in A than in B",
      "c. The wind speed is higher in B than in A",
      "d. The wind speed in A and in B is the same"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Your true altitude is higher in B than in A"
  },
  {
    "question": "238. Refer to the constant pressure chart: Flight path A - B, altimeter setting 1013,2 hPa:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your true altitude is higher in B than in A",
      "b. Your true altitude is higher in A than in B",
      "c. The wind speed is higher in B than in A",
      "d. The wind speed in A and in B is the same"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Your true altitude is higher in B than in A"
  },
  {
    "question": "239. While mountain flying on a cold winter day, under fair weather conditions (QNH 1013 hPa), you circle a mountain of known height at peak elevation. Comparing to the elevation of the mountain, the aneroid altimeter of your aircraft will therefore indicate.....",
    "options": [
      "a. a higher altitude",
      "b. a lower altitude",
      "c. peak elevation",
      "d. cannot be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "a. a higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "240. While mountain flying on a warm summer day under high pressure conditions, you circle a mountain of known height at peak elevation. Comparing to the indication of your altimeter, the peak elevation will therefore be....",
    "options": [
      "a. higher",
      "b. lower",
      "c. equal",
      "d. can not be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "b. lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "241. You are cruising at FL 200, OAT -40\u00b0C, sea level pressure 1033 hPa. Calculate the true altitude:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20660 ft",
      "b. 21740 ft",
      "c. 18260 ft",
      "d. 19340 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 19340 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "242. You intend to overfly a mountain ridge at an altitude of 15000 ft AMSL. The average air temperature is 15\u00b0C lower than ISA, the sea level pressure 1003 hPa. Which altimeter indication (standard setting) is needed?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15630 ft",
      "b. 14370 ft",
      "c. 13830 ft",
      "d. 16170 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 16170 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "243. You intend to overfly a mountain ridge. The recommended minimum altitude for overflight according to your ICAO chart is 12000 ft AMSL. The average air temperature is 10\u00b0C higher than ISA, your altimeter is set to the local QNH of 1023 hPa. Which altimeter indication is needed to maintain the recommended minimum altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. 11250 ft",
      "b. 12210 ft",
      "c. 11520 ft",
      "d. 11790 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 11520 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "244. You have landed at an airport, local QNH 993 hPa. After landing, you notice, that your altimeter subscale is still set to 1013,2 hPa. Your altimeter indicates 1200 ft. What is the airport elevation?",
    "options": [
      "a. 660 ft AMSL",
      "b. 1740 ft AMSL",
      "c. 2280 ft AMSL",
      "d. 1200 ft AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 660 ft AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "245. You are cruising at FL 160 at an OAT of -27\u00b0C. The sea level pressure is 1003 hPa. Your true altitude therefore is...",
    "options": [
      "a. 15630 ft",
      "b. 16370 ft",
      "c. 16910 ft",
      "d. 15090 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 15090 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "246. When the altimeter indicated 0 (zero) ft when the aircraft was parked for the night, and 1000 ft the following morning, this shows that:",
    "options": [
      "a. the barometric pressure has decreased by approx. 37 hPa",
      "b. the barometric pressure is constant, but the temperature has fallen during the night",
      "c. a formation of fog has most probably taken place",
      "d. the barometric pressure has increased by approx. 37 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. the barometric pressure has decreased by approx. 37 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "247. After landing at an aerodrome (aerodrome elevation 1715 FT), the altimeter indicates an altitude of 1310 FT. The altimeter is set to the pressure value of 1013 hPa. What is the QNH at this aerodrome?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1015 hPa.",
      "b. 1028 hPa.",
      "c. 1013 hPa.",
      "d. 998 hPa."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1028 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "248. What is the relationship, if any, between QFE and QNH at an airport situated 50 FT below sea level?",
    "options": [
      "a. No clear relationship exists.",
      "b. QFE is smaller than QNH.",
      "c. QFE equals QNH.",
      "d. QFE is greater than QNH."
    ],
    "answer": "d. QFE is greater than QNH."
  },
  {
    "question": "249. An aircraft lands at an airport (airport elevation 1240 FT, QNH 1008 hPa). The altimeter is set to 1013 hPa. The altimeter will indicate :",
    "options": [
      "a. 1200 FT.",
      "b. 1375 FT.",
      "c. 1105 FT.",
      "d. 1280 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1375 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "250. What pressure is defined as QFE?",
    "options": [
      "a. The pressure reduced to sea level using actual temperatures",
      "b. The pressure of the altimeter",
      "c. The pressure at field elevation",
      "d. The pressure reduced to sea level using ISA temperatures"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The pressure at field elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "251. An aircraft is descending to land under IFR. If the local QNH is 1009 hPa, what will happen to the altitude reading when the altimeter is reset at the transition level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It will increase",
      "b. It will decrease",
      "c. It will remain the same",
      "d. It will not be affected"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "252. During the climb after takeoff, the altimeter setting is adjusted at the transition altitude. If the local QNH is 1023 hPa, what will happen to the altimeter reading during the resetting procedure ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is not possible to give a definitive answer",
      "b. It will increase",
      "c. It will remain the same",
      "d. It will decrease"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "253. During the climb after takeoff, the altimeter setting is adjusted at the transition altitude. If the local QNH is 966 hPa, what will happen to the altimeter reading during the resetting procedure?",
    "options": [
      "a. It will decrease",
      "b. It will increase",
      "c. It will remain the same",
      "d. It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "254. An aircraft lands at an airport (airport elevation 540 FT, QNH 993 hPa) with the altimeter set to 1013 hPa. What will it indicate ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1080 FT",
      "b. 700 FT",
      "c. 380 FT",
      "d. 0 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1080 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "255. After landing at an aerodrome (QNH 993 hPa) it is noticed that the altimeter is still set to 1013,2 hPa and that it reads 1200 feet. What is the elevation of the aerodrome above mean sea level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 660 feet.",
      "b. 1200 feet.",
      "c. 1740 feet.",
      "d. 2280 feet."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 660 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "256. An altimeter adjusted to 1013 hPa indicates an altitude of 3600 FT. Should this altimeter be adjusted to the local QNH value of 991 hPa, the altitude indicated would be",
    "options": [
      "a. 2922 FT.",
      "b. 3006 FT.",
      "c. 4278 FT.",
      "d. 4194 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 3006 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "257. In Geneva, the local QNH is 994 hPa. The elevation of Geneva is 1411 FT. The QFE adjustment in Geneva is",
    "options": [
      "a. 942 hPa.",
      "b. 967 hPa.",
      "c. 961 hPa.",
      "d. 948 hPa."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 942 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "258. An aircraft is flying at FL 80. The local QNH is 1000 hPa. After the second altimeter has been adjusted to the local QNH, the reading will be approximately",
    "options": [
      "a. 7650 FT.",
      "b. 8600 FT.",
      "c. 8350 FT.",
      "d. 8000 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 7650 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "259. The barometric compensator of an altimeter is locked on reference 1013.2 hPa. The aircraft has to land on a point with an elevation of 290 feet where the QNH is 1023 hPa. Assuming that 1 hPa corresponds to 27 FT, the reading on the altimeter on the ground will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20 FT.",
      "b. 11 FT.",
      "c. -10 FT.",
      "d. 560 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 20 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "260. Which of the following statements is true ?",
    "options": [
      "a. QNH is always higher than QFE",
      "b. QNH is always lower than QFE",
      "c. QNH can be equal to QFE",
      "d. QNH is always equal to QFE"
    ],
    "answer": "c. QNH can be equal to QFE"
  },
  {
    "question": "261. Which statement is true ?",
    "options": [
      "a. QNH can be 1013.25 only for a station at MSL",
      "b. QNH can not be 1013.25 hPa",
      "c. QNH is lower than 1013.25 hPa at any time",
      "d. QNH can be lower as well as higher than 1013.25 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. QNH can be lower as well as higher than 1013.25 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "262. When the subscale is set to the QNH of an airfield the pressure altimeter indicates",
    "options": [
      "a. zero while landing",
      "b. elevation while landing",
      "c. elevation while landing only if conditions are as in the International Standard Atmosphere",
      "d. zero while landing only if conditions are as in the International Standard Atmosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "b. elevation while landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "263. The QNH is equal to the QFE if",
    "options": [
      "a. T actual < T standard",
      "b. T actual = T standard",
      "c. T actual > T standard",
      "d. the elevation = 0"
    ],
    "answer": "d. the elevation = 0"
  },
  {
    "question": "264. Which of the following conditions gives the highest value of the QNH?",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE = 1003 hPa, elevation = 1200 FT (366m)",
      "b. QFE = 1000 hPa, elevation = 1200 FT (366m)",
      "c. QFE = 995 hPa, elevation = 1600 FT (488m)",
      "d. QFE = 995 hPa, elevation = 1200 FT (366m)"
    ],
    "answer": "c. QFE = 995 hPa, elevation = 1600 FT (488m)"
  },
  {
    "question": "265. You must make an emergency landing at sea. The QNH of a field on a nearby island with an elevation of 4000 FT is 1025 hPa and the temperature is -20\u00b0C. What is your pressure altimeter reading when landing if 1025 hPa is set in the subscale?",
    "options": [
      "a. Less than 0 FT",
      "b. 0 FT",
      "c. More than 0 FT, but less than 4000 FT",
      "d. 4000 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Less than 0 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "266. For a given airfield the QFE is 980 hPa and the QNH is 1000 hPa. The approximate elevation of the airfield is",
    "options": [
      "a. 120 metres",
      "b. 600 metres",
      "c. 540 metres",
      "d. 160 metres"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 160 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "267. Before landing, an altimeter set to QFE indicates",
    "options": [
      "a. the height of the aircraft's wheels above the runway.",
      "b. the flight level.",
      "c. the aircraft's altitude above the mean sea level.",
      "d. in standard atmosphere, the height of the aircraft above the official airport elevation."
    ],
    "answer": "d. in standard atmosphere, the height of the aircraft above the official airport elevation."
  },
  {
    "question": "268. What altimeter reading would you expect when landing at an airfield 3000 ft above MSL, altimeter setting is QFE for the field and local temperature is + 25\u00b0C?",
    "options": [
      "a. 3300 ft.",
      "b. 3000 ft.",
      "c. 2700 ft.",
      "d. 0 ft."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 0 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "269. The temperature is -15\u00b0C on an airport 3000' above mean sea level. Which of the following statements is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "a. QFF > QNH",
      "b. QFF = QFE",
      "c. QFF = QNH",
      "d. QNH = QFE"
    ],
    "answer": "a. QFF > QNH"
  },
  {
    "question": "270. Which of altimeter settings is used when flying in flight levels ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1013,25 hPa.",
      "b. 1025,13 hPa.",
      "c. QFF.",
      "d. QFE."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1013,25 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "271. While passing the Transition Level, you set the subscale on your altimeter to the local QNH of 1009 hPa:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your indicated altitude decreases",
      "b. Your indicated altitude increases",
      "c. A statement is not possible without the knowledge of the exact OAT",
      "d. Your setting is wrong, the subscale must be set to 1013,2 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Your indicated altitude decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "272. On takeoff, your altimeter is set to the local QNH of 1023 hPa. While passing the Transition Altitude, you adjust the subscale accordingly:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your indicated altitude decreases",
      "b. Your indicated altitude increases",
      "c. A statement is not possible without the knowledge of the exact OAT",
      "d. The altimeter setting must remain at 1023 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Your indicated altitude decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "273. You observe the altimeter in a parked aircraft while a cold front passes the airport. What does the altimeter indicate?",
    "options": [
      "a. It first decreases and then increases",
      "b. It first increases and then decreases",
      "c. It is not affected by a pressure change",
      "d. The pressure changes are very small and therefore, there is no visible change of the indication"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It first increases and then decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "274. You have landed on an airport (elevation 1240 ft, QNH 1008 hPa). Your altimeter subscale is erroneously set to 1013 hPa. Therefore, the indication will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1105 ft",
      "b. 1200 ft",
      "c. 1375 ft",
      "d. 1280 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1375 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "275. You have landed on an airport (elevation 540 ft, QNH 993 hPa). Your altimeter subscale is erroneously set to 1013 hPa. Therefore, the indication will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. 0 ft",
      "b. 380 ft",
      "c. 1080 ft",
      "d. 700 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1080 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "276. Your altimeter indicates 3600 ft, while set to standard pressure. You now adjust the subscale to the local QNH of 991 hPa. What will the indication be?",
    "options": [
      "a. 3006 ft",
      "b. 4194 ft",
      "c. 3600 ft",
      "d. 3320 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 3006 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "277. When the barometric subscale of the altimeter is adjusted to 1013,2 hPa, what type of altitude is being measured?",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure altitude",
      "b. Indicated altitude",
      "c. True altitude",
      "d. Relative height"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "278. You are departing an aerodrome (600 ft AMSL, QNH 1012 hPa) and proceed to another airfield (195 ft AMSL) with the same QNH. After landing, which barometric setting on the altimeter makes it again indicate 600 ft?",
    "options": [
      "a. 997",
      "b. 1032",
      "c. 992",
      "d. 1027"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1027"
  },
  {
    "question": "279. Without readjusting the barometric setting of the altimeter, it will under-read when:",
    "options": [
      "a. flying from a high pressure area into a low pressure area",
      "b. flying in headwind with constant barometric pressure",
      "c. flaing in tailwind with constant barometric pressure",
      "d. flying from a low pressure area into a high pressure area"
    ],
    "answer": "d. flying from a low pressure area into a high pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "280. If atmospheric conditions exist such that the temperature deviation is ISA +10\u00b0C in the lower troposphere up to 18000 FT, what is the actual layer thickness between FL 60 and FL 120 ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 6240 FT.",
      "b. 6000 FT.",
      "c. 5900 FT.",
      "d. 5760 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 6240 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "281. Which weather condition lowers true altitude as compared to pressure altitude to a position where flight over mountains could be dangerous?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold high.",
      "b. Warm depression.",
      "c. Cold low.",
      "d. Warm high."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Cold low."
  },
  {
    "question": "282. A vertical spacing of 1000 FT, is the standard required separation between two FL. Under conditions of cold air advection (ISA -15\u00b0C), what would the true vertical separation be?",
    "options": [
      "a. More than 1000 FT",
      "b. It remains 1000 FT",
      "c. Less than 1000 FT",
      "d. Without QNH information, it can not be determined"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Less than 1000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "283. At which pressure and temperature conditions may you safely assume that the minimum usable flight level at least lies at the same height, as the minimum safe altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. In a cold low pressure region",
      "b. At a temperature greater than or equal to that of the ISA and where the QNH is greater than or equal to 1013 hPa",
      "c. At a temperature less than or equal to that of the ISA and where the QNH is less than 1013 hPa",
      "d. In a warm high pressure region"
    ],
    "answer": "b. At a temperature greater than or equal to that of the ISA and where the QNH is greater than or equal to 1013 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "284. What information is required to convert a minimum safe altitude into a lowest usable flight level?",
    "options": [
      "a. Lowest value of QNH and the highest negative temperature deviation from ISA.",
      "b. Highest value of QNH and the highest negative temperature deviation from ISA.",
      "c. Highest value of QNH and the highest positive temperature deviation from ISA",
      "d. Lowest value of QNH and the lowest negative temperature deviation from ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Lowest value of QNH and the highest negative temperature deviation from ISA."
  },
  {
    "question": "285. An aircraft is in level flight at FL100 over a mountain range, which extends up to 2400 metres AMSL. If the regional QNH is 998 hPa, what is the approximate terrain clearance?",
    "options": [
      "a. 2536 feet",
      "b. 1636 feet",
      "c. 7821 feet",
      "d. 405 feet"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1636 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "286. What is the approximate speed of a 25-knot wind, expressed in kilometres per hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. 60 km/h",
      "b. 35 km/h",
      "c. 55 km/h",
      "d. 45 km/h"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 45 km/h"
  },
  {
    "question": "287. What is the approximate speed of a 90 km/h wind, expressed in knots?",
    "options": [
      "a. 55 kt",
      "b. 50 kt",
      "c. 60 kt",
      "d. 70 kt"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 50 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "288. What is the approximate speed of a 40-knot wind, expressed in m/sec?",
    "options": [
      "a. 25 m/sec",
      "b. 15 m/sec",
      "c. 20 m/sec",
      "d. 30 m/sec"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 20 m/sec"
  },
  {
    "question": "289. What values are used for the forecasted wind at higher levels?",
    "options": [
      "a. Direction relative to grid north and speed in kmh",
      "b. Direction relative to magnetic north and speed in knots",
      "c. Direction relative to magnetic north and speed in kmh",
      "d. Direction relative to true north and speed in knots"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Direction relative to true north and speed in knots"
  },
  {
    "question": "290. Evaporation is the change of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Liquid water to water vapor.",
      "b. Water vapor to ice.",
      "c. Invisible water vapor to liquid water.",
      "d. Ice directly to water vapor."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Liquid water to water vapor."
  },
  {
    "question": "291. Water droplets often condense or persist at temperature colder than 0\u00b0C. What are water droplets called which are colder than 0\u00b0C ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Super-heated water droplets.",
      "b. Supercooled water droplets.",
      "c. Ice.",
      "d. None of the above."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Supercooled water droplets."
  },
  {
    "question": "292. The direction of the gradient force is?",
    "options": [
      "a. Towards high pressure",
      "b. Towards low pressure",
      "c. Parallel to the isobars",
      "d. Same direction as the friction force"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Towards low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "293. Which precipitation type normally indicates freezing rain at some altitude above the ground?",
    "options": [
      "a. Snow.",
      "b. Hail.",
      "c. Ice pellets.",
      "d. Ice crystals."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Ice pellets."
  },
  {
    "question": "294. Thermal turbulence is caused by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Wing-tip vortexes.",
      "b. Vertical movements due convection flow in unstable air.",
      "c. Deviations due to mountain terrain.",
      "d. Smooth air movements upon smooth substratum."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Vertical movements due convection flow in unstable air."
  },
  {
    "question": "295. What relationship exists between the winds at 2000 ft above the surface and the surface winds ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The winds at 2000 ft and the surface winds flow in the same direction, but the surface winds are weaker due to friction.",
      "b. The winds at 2000 ft and the surface winds are approximately the same except when eddies form due to obstructions.",
      "c. The winds at 2000 ft tend to parallel the isobars while the surface winds cross the isobars at an angle toward lower pressure and are weaker.",
      "d. The surface winds tend to veer to the right of the winds at 2000 ft and are visually weaker."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The winds at 2000 ft tend to parallel the isobars while the surface winds cross the isobars at an angle toward lower pressure and are weaker."
  },
  {
    "question": "296. Possible mountain wave turbulence should be anticipated in cases where windspeeds of",
    "options": [
      "a. 20 kts. or greater blow across a mountain ridge, and the air is unstable.",
      "b. 25 kts. or greater blow across a mountain ridge, and the air is stable.",
      "c. 25 kts. or greater blow down a mountain valley, and the air is unstable.",
      "d. 25 kts. or greater blow parallel to a mountain peak, and the air is stable."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 25 kts. or greater blow across a mountain ridge, and the air is stable."
  },
  {
    "question": "297. Winds at 5000' AGL on a particular flight are south-westerly while most of the surface winds are southerly. The difference in direction is primarily due to:",
    "options": [
      "a. A stronger pressure gradient at higher altitudes.",
      "b. Friction between the wind and the surface.",
      "c. Stronger Coriolis force at the surface.",
      "d. The influence of pressure systems at the lower altitudes."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Friction between the wind and the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "298. Which force, in the Northern Hemisphere, acts at a right angle to the wind and deflects it to the right until parallel to the isobars ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Centrifugal.",
      "b. Pressure gradient.",
      "c. Coriolis.",
      "d. Advection."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Coriolis."
  },
  {
    "question": "299. A trough is a:",
    "options": [
      "a. kind of low pressure.",
      "b. high pressure ridge.",
      "c. tropical thunderstorm.",
      "d. tropical wind."
    ],
    "answer": "a. kind of low pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "300. In the Northern Hemisphere the surface wind is blowing around a low pressure:",
    "options": [
      "a. anti-clockwise, oblique to the isobars towards the low pressure centre.",
      "b. parallel to the isobars.",
      "c. across the isobars.",
      "d. opposite the situation described in a)."
    ],
    "answer": "a. anti-clockwise, oblique to the isobars towards the low pressure centre."
  },
  {
    "question": "301. Characteristic of a cold air mass is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Precipitation (drizzle).",
      "b. Extensive fog.",
      "c. Showers and gusty winds.",
      "d. Strong and smooth winds."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Showers and gusty winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "302. Due to the diurnal variations of temperature the following types of wind arise:",
    "options": [
      "a. Sea and land breeze.",
      "b. Trade-winds.",
      "c. Monsoon winds.",
      "d. Anabatic winds."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Sea and land breeze."
  },
  {
    "question": "303. An autumn day with rain showers and terminated by evening clear sky will be followed in the next morning by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Advection fog.",
      "b. Radiation fog.",
      "c. Orografic fog.",
      "d. Frontal fog."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Radiation fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "304. What causes surface winds to flow across the isobars at an angle rather than parallel to the isobars ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Coriolis force.",
      "b. Surface friction.",
      "c. The greater density of the air at the surface.",
      "d. The greater atmospheric pressure at the surface."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Surface friction."
  },
  {
    "question": "305. A high pressure (or anticyclone) is characterized by:",
    "options": [
      "a. The wind is blowing anticlockwise around the high pressure on the Northern Hemisphere.",
      "b. The wind is blowing anticlockwise around the high pressure on the Southern Hemisphere.",
      "c. The wind in the friction layer is blowing at an oblique angle and out from the high pressure in relation to the isobars.",
      "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "306. In a low pressure:",
    "options": [
      "a. The isobars are found in closed and more or less oval circles around the lowest pressure.",
      "b. The isobars are often closer to each other than around a high pressure.",
      "c. The wind will tend to be stronger with increasing altitude and also blow more parallel to the isobars.",
      "d. a) , b) and c) are all correct"
    ],
    "answer": "d. a) , b) and c) are all correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "307. Which clouds have the greatest turbulence ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Towering cumulus.",
      "b. Cumulonimbus.",
      "c. Nimbostratus.",
      "d. Altocumulus castellanus."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "308. Define low pressure:",
    "options": [
      "a. An area with lower pressure than that of the environments.",
      "b. An area of convergence.",
      "c. A trough.",
      "d. None of the above."
    ],
    "answer": "a. An area with lower pressure than that of the environments."
  },
  {
    "question": "309. Define high pressure:",
    "options": [
      "a. An area with higher pressure than that of the environments.",
      "b. A high pressure ridge.",
      "c. An area of divergence.",
      "d. Non of the above."
    ],
    "answer": "a. An area with higher pressure than that of the environments."
  },
  {
    "question": "310. List the two forces in balance in a geostrophic wind:",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure force and friction force.",
      "b. Centrifugal force and friction force.",
      "c. Gradient force and Coriolis force.",
      "d. Coriolis force and centrifugal force."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Gradient force and Coriolis force."
  },
  {
    "question": "311. The expression \"Mechanical turbulence\" means:",
    "options": [
      "a. \"Wake turbulence\".",
      "b. That the terrain or other obstructions interfering with the airflow.",
      "c. Vertical movements in unstable air.",
      "d. That you experience \"finger trouble\"."
    ],
    "answer": "b. That the terrain or other obstructions interfering with the airflow."
  },
  {
    "question": "312. The mechanical turbulence will increase when:",
    "options": [
      "a. Flying from land to sea.",
      "b. temperature falls.",
      "c. pressure rises.",
      "d. the wind increases."
    ],
    "answer": "d. the wind increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "313. What are trade winds?",
    "options": [
      "a. The wind zones towards the Intertropical Convergence Zone.",
      "b. The westerly wind zones.",
      "c. The polar easterly winds.",
      "d. Foen winds in alpine valleys."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The wind zones towards the Intertropical Convergence Zone."
  },
  {
    "question": "314. Mention one of the characteristics of the Monsoons:",
    "options": [
      "a. Daily change of wind direction.",
      "b. Yearly change of wind direction.",
      "c. The wind blowing from one direction all the year.",
      "d. The wind blowing along the 40\u00b0 south, from the west towards the east."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Yearly change of wind direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "315. Describe the change of wind through the friction layer from the ground and up:",
    "options": [
      "a. Decreased force and \"veering\".",
      "b. Increased force and \"veering\".",
      "c. Increased force and \"backing\"",
      "d. Increased force and turning 180\u00b0"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Increased force and \"veering\"."
  },
  {
    "question": "316. How does the geostrophic wind force change with latitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. Increase with increasing latitude to a certain latitude.",
      "b. Decrease with increasing latitude to a certain latitude.",
      "c. Increase with decreasing latitude.",
      "d. Latitude does not affect wind force."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Increase with decreasing latitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "317. Fog which reaches only 2 metres above ground or 10 metres above the sea is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Smog.",
      "b. Mist.",
      "c. Drifting fog.",
      "d. Shallow fog."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Shallow fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "318. If you are flying into an area of low pressure, what drift would you expect to experience in the northern hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. Right drift",
      "b. None",
      "c. Left drift",
      "d. Ice directly to water vapor."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Right drift"
  },
  {
    "question": "319. In contrast to brief showers, prolonged precipitation preceding a front is most likely to be related to:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratiform clouds with moderate turbulence",
      "b. Cumuliform cloud with little or no turbulence",
      "c. Shallow stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Shallow stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "320. The wind which results from air cooling on the side of a valley is known as:",
    "options": [
      "a. A katabatic wind",
      "b. A valley wind",
      "c. An anabatic wind"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A katabatic wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "321. When flying in a sub-zero 0\u00b0C airmass, into which rain is falling, which of the following is most likely?",
    "options": [
      "a. Hoar frost",
      "b. Hail",
      "c. Freezing rain"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Freezing rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "322. A wind who has changed clockwise in direction can be said to have:",
    "options": [
      "a. Reduced",
      "b. Backed",
      "c. Veered",
      "d. Advanced"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Veered"
  },
  {
    "question": "323. If the wind at altitude is 24035KT, the most likely wind on the surface at an inland airfield is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 27040KT",
      "b. 22020KT",
      "c. 22040KT"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 22020KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "324. There is a natural tendency for air to flow from areas of:",
    "options": [
      "a. High pressure to low pressure",
      "b. Low pressure to high pressure",
      "c. Mountainous areas to flat areas",
      "d. Flat terrain towards the sea"
    ],
    "answer": "a. High pressure to low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "325. With respect to high and low pressure systems:",
    "options": [
      "a. A high pressure area or ridge is an area of rising air",
      "b. A high pressure area or ridge is an area of descending air",
      "c. A low pressure area or trough is an area of descending air"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A high pressure area or ridge is an area of descending air"
  },
  {
    "question": "326. With respect to high and low pressure systems:",
    "options": [
      "a. A low pressure area or trough is an area of rising air",
      "b. A high pressure area or ridge is an area of rising air",
      "c. A low pressure area or trough is an area of descending air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A low pressure area or trough is an area of rising air"
  },
  {
    "question": "327. What is the term used to describe streamers of precipitation trailing beneath clouds, but evaporating before reaching the ground:",
    "options": [
      "a. Foehn",
      "b. Virga",
      "c. Dissipation trails"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "328. In the northern hemisphere an aircraft flying directly from low to high pressure would expect to experience:",
    "options": [
      "a. No drift",
      "b. Right drift",
      "c. Left drift"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Left drift"
  },
  {
    "question": "329. Which statement is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. The general visibility associated with a cold front is worse than the visibility associated with a warm front",
      "b. The general visibility associated with a cold front is the same than the visibility associated with a warm front",
      "c. The general visibility associated with a cold front is better than the visibility associated with a warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The general visibility associated with a cold front is better than the visibility associated with a warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "330. A V-shaped extension of a low pressure area is called a:",
    "options": [
      "a. Ridge",
      "b. Col",
      "c. Trough",
      "d. Occlusion"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "331. If you stand with your back to the wind in the northern hemisphere, the low pressure will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. On your left",
      "b. On your right",
      "c. Behind you",
      "d. Ahead of you"
    ],
    "answer": "a. On your left"
  },
  {
    "question": "332. The wind at the surface is 24015KT. What is it most likely to be at 2000ft?",
    "options": [
      "a. 22025KT",
      "b. 26025KT",
      "c. 28015KT"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 26025KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "333. What prevents air from flowing directly from high to low pressure areas over western Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Coriolis force",
      "b. Surface friction",
      "c. Pressure gradient force",
      "d. The presence of occlusions"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "question": "334. The general circulation of air associated with a high pressure area in the northern hemisphere is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Inward, downward and counter clockwise",
      "b. Outward, upward and clockwise",
      "c. Outward, downward and clockwise"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Outward, downward and clockwise"
  },
  {
    "question": "335. The general circulation of air associated with a low pressure area in the northern hemisphere is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Inward, upward and counter clockwise",
      "b. Inward, upward and clockwise",
      "c. Outward, downward and clockwise",
      "d. Inward, downward and counter clockwise"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Inward, upward and counter clockwise"
  },
  {
    "question": "336. What is a feature of air movement in a high pressure area?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ascending from the surface high to lower pressure at higher altitudes",
      "b. Descending to the surface and the outward",
      "c. Moving outward from the high at high altitudes and into the high at the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Descending to the surface and the outward"
  },
  {
    "question": "337. At lower levels of the atmosphere, friction causes the wind to flow across isobars into a low because the friction",
    "options": [
      "a. decreases wind speed and Coriolis force",
      "b. decreases pressure gradient force",
      "c. creates air turbulence and raises atmospheric pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "a. decreases wind speed and Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "question": "338. At which location does Coriolis force have the least effect on wind direction?",
    "options": [
      "a. At the poles",
      "b. Middle latitudes (30\u00b0 to 60\u00b0)",
      "c. At the Equator"
    ],
    "answer": "c. At the Equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "339. How does Coriolis force affect wind direction in the Southern Hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. Causes clockwise rotation around a low",
      "b. Causes wind to flow out of a low toward a high",
      "c. Has exactly the same effect as in the Northern Hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Causes clockwise rotation around a low"
  },
  {
    "question": "340. Which weather condition is defined as an anticyclone?",
    "options": [
      "a. Calm",
      "b. High pressure area",
      "c. Col"
    ],
    "answer": "b. High pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "341. What term describes an elongated area of low pressure?",
    "options": [
      "a. Trough",
      "b. Ridge",
      "c. Hurricane or typhoon"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "342. Which event usually occurs after an aircraft passes through a front into the colder air?",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature/dewpoint spread decreases",
      "b. Wind direction shifts to the left",
      "c. Atmospheric pressure increases"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Atmospheric pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "343. Which atmospheric factor causes rapid movement of surface fronts?",
    "options": [
      "a. Upper winds blowing across the front.",
      "b. Upper low located directly over the surface low.",
      "c. The cold front overtaking and lifting the warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Upper winds blowing across the front."
  },
  {
    "question": "344. In which meteorological conditions can frontal waves and low pressure areas form?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm fronts or occluded fronts",
      "b. Slow-moving cold fronts or stationary fronts",
      "c. Cold front occlusions"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Slow-moving cold fronts or stationary fronts"
  },
  {
    "question": "345. How is wind measured?",
    "options": [
      "a. 8-10 m above the ground on a mast with an anemometer",
      "b. 2 m above the ground in a weather shelter",
      "c. 2 m above the ground on a mast with an anemomenter",
      "d. 8-10 m above the ground on a mast with a pluviometer"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 8-10 m above the ground on a mast with an anemometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "346. What pressure does an observer at point A encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rising pressure",
      "b. Falling pressure",
      "c. A pressure rise first, then an immediate pressure drop",
      "d. No substantial pressure change"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Rising pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "347. What pressure does an observer at point B encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rising pressure",
      "b. Falling pressure",
      "c. A pressure rise first, then an immediate pressure drop",
      "d. No substantial pressure change"
    ],
    "answer": "d. No substantial pressure change"
  },
  {
    "question": "348. What pressure does an observer at point C encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rising pressure",
      "b. Falling pressure",
      "c. A pressure rise first, then an immediate pressure drop",
      "d. No substantial pressure change"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Falling pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "349. What temperature does an observer at point C encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature increases",
      "b. The temperature decreases",
      "c. The temperature first increases and then decreases",
      "d. No substantial temperature change"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "350. What temperature does an observer at point B encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature increases",
      "b. The temperature decreases",
      "c. The temperature first increases and then decreases",
      "d. No substantial temperature change"
    ],
    "answer": "d. No substantial temperature change"
  },
  {
    "question": "351. What temperature does an observer at point A encounter in the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature increases",
      "b. The temperature decreases",
      "c. The temperature first increases and then decreases",
      "d. No substantial temperature change"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "352. What is the name of the low level winds between the subtropical high pressure belt and the ITCZ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Monsoon",
      "b. Trade winds",
      "c. Easterly wave",
      "d. Low level jetstream"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "353. What is the most frequent wind in valleys, caused by thermal effects?",
    "options": [
      "a. Mountain breeze by day",
      "b. Mountain breeze by night",
      "c. Valley breeze by day",
      "d. Valley breeze by night"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Valley breeze by day"
  },
  {
    "question": "354. What does zone A depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A trough",
      "b. A ridge",
      "c. The warm sector",
      "d. The cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "355. Refer to the picture by pressing the \"DLP\" button: What does zone B depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A trough",
      "b. A ridge",
      "c. The warm sector",
      "d. The cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "356. Refer to the picture by pressing the \"DLP\" button: What does zone C depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A trough",
      "b. A ridge",
      "c. The warm sector",
      "d. The cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "357. What can you expect at FL 180, when the wind is geostrophic and your true altitude is 18'000 ft?",
    "options": [
      "a. Crosswind from the right",
      "b. Crosswind from the left",
      "c. No crosswind",
      "d. None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "c. No crosswind"
  },
  {
    "question": "358. Where can a jetstream be observed?",
    "options": [
      "a. On a Significant Weather Chart (SWC)",
      "b. On a high level pressure chart",
      "c. On a surface chart",
      "d. All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "a. On a Significant Weather Chart (SWC)"
  },
  {
    "question": "359. What can on a Significant Weather Chart be depicted?",
    "options": [
      "a. The speed and direction of a surface front",
      "b. The speed and direction of an upper front",
      "c. The amount of rain in a certain area",
      "d. The actual weather situation"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The speed and direction of a surface front"
  },
  {
    "question": "360. What cloud type is prone to +RA?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. AS",
      "c. CC",
      "d. ST"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "361. When is heavy precipitation unlikely?",
    "options": [
      "a. In summer, with SC and AC clouds",
      "b. In summer, with CB and CU clouds",
      "c. In spring and autumn, with NS and CB clouds",
      "d. In winter, with CB clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In summer, with SC and AC clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "362. The precipitation form +TSRA is most probably related to the following cloud type:",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. CU",
      "c. NS",
      "d. CC"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "363. What happens when you descend from 2000 ft to the surface, when no fronts are present?",
    "options": [
      "a. The wind backs and decreases",
      "b. The wind veers and decreases",
      "c. The wind veers and increases",
      "d. The wind backs and the wind speed remains more or less constant"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The wind backs and decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "364. A trough of low pressure on a surface synoptic chart.....",
    "options": [
      "a. is an area of convergence and widespread ascent",
      "b. is an area of divergence and widespread ascent",
      "c. leads to descending air masses",
      "d. is a narrow band of ascent"
    ],
    "answer": "a. is an area of convergence and widespread ascent"
  },
  {
    "question": "365. Name the conditions for the formation of radiation fog:",
    "options": [
      "a. Flat landscape, a clear night, no wind conditions",
      "b. Over the sea with a 20KT wind",
      "c. Mountainous terrain with winds of approx. 10 KT, overcast skies",
      "d. Flat landscape, a clear night, winds of 10-20KT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Flat landscape, a clear night, no wind conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "366. You fly from east to west at the 500 hPa level in the Northern hemisphere:",
    "options": [
      "a. If the wind is from the North, there is a gain in altitude",
      "b. If the wind is from the South, there is a gain in altitude",
      "c. If you encounter a northerly drift, there is a gain in altitude",
      "d. You fly towards an area of low pressure, and, therefore, experience a loss in altitude"
    ],
    "answer": "a. If the wind is from the North, there is a gain in altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "367. Wind at 2000 ft 20040KT. What would you expect at the surface over the sea approximately?",
    "options": [
      "a. 18515KT",
      "b. 18540KT",
      "c. 22020KT",
      "d. 22040KT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 18515KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "368. Which statement is true for condensation?",
    "options": [
      "a. Latent heat is released to the atmosphere",
      "b. Latent heat is transformed into pure energy",
      "c. Latent heat is absorbed from the surrounding air by the water droplet",
      "d. Precipitation forms"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Latent heat is released to the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "369. Of which air mass does the warm sector of a polar front depression consist?",
    "options": [
      "a. Maritime tropical air",
      "b. Maritime polar air",
      "c. Continental tropical air",
      "d. Continental equatorial air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Maritime tropical air"
  },
  {
    "question": "370. Which statement is true, when isobars stand close together on a surface chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. Strong winds are present",
      "b. Lights winds prevail",
      "c. A high pressure area is approaching",
      "d. Westerly winds prevail"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Strong winds are present"
  },
  {
    "question": "371. Refer to the chart: On which route of flight would you expect no icing at FL 180?",
    "options": [
      "a. Zurich-Hamburg",
      "b. Zurich-Madrid",
      "c. Hamburg-Stockholm",
      "d. Zurich-Vienna"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Hamburg-Stockholm"
  },
  {
    "question": "372. Refer to the chart: When flying from Zurich to Shannon at FL 340, your cruising level is.....",
    "options": [
      "a. permanently in the troposphere",
      "b. permanently in the stratosphere",
      "c. first in the troposphere and later in the stratosphere",
      "d. intermittently in the stratosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "b. permanently in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "373. Refer to the chart: Which statement is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. The frontal system south of London has a movement towards the south",
      "b. The freezing level over Madrid is higher than FL 120",
      "c. There is no risk for thunderstorms over France",
      "d. You may encounter turbulence over Madrid at FL 340"
    ],
    "answer": "d. You may encounter turbulence over Madrid at FL 340"
  },
  {
    "question": "374. Refer to the chart: For which route of flight do you expect icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. Hamburg-Oslo",
      "b. Rome-Frankfurt",
      "c. Copenhagen-Helsinki",
      "d. Oslo-Prague"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Rome-Frankfurt"
  },
  {
    "question": "375. Refer to the chart: State the height of the tropopause over Frankfurt:",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 250",
      "b. FL 280",
      "c. FL 310",
      "d. FL 340"
    ],
    "answer": "c. FL 310"
  },
  {
    "question": "376. Refer to the chart: What are the weather conditions for a flight from Zurich to London at your cruising altitude of FL 220?",
    "options": [
      "a. CAT during the first part of the route",
      "b. Severe turbulence and icing during the entire flight",
      "c. Flight mainly in clouds, no turbulence",
      "d. Occasional thunderstorms"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Occasional thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "377. Refer to the chart: Which statements are true?",
    "options": [
      "a. The front south of Frankfurt moves towards the Southeast with a speed of approximately 5 KT",
      "b. The jet stream over Italy shows a maximum wind speed of 120 km",
      "c. CBs have formed over the Iberian peninsula, with tops at about 25'000 ft",
      "d. No significant clouds are present over Rome"
    ],
    "answer": "c. CBs have formed over the Iberian peninsula, with tops at about 25'000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "378. Refer to the chart: Which route is free of turbulence at Fl 340?",
    "options": [
      "a. Shannon-Hamburg",
      "b. Zurich-Rome",
      "c. Zurich-Athens",
      "d. Rom-Berlin"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Shannon-Hamburg"
  },
  {
    "question": "379. Refer to the chart: What are the weather conditions for a flight Zurich-Stockholm at FL 240:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your flight will be mainly in clouds, outside of CAT areas",
      "b. Your flight will be mainly clear of clouds, intermittently in icing conditions",
      "c. No thunderstorms have to be expected",
      "d. Your flight will be permanently clear of clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Your flight will be mainly clear of clouds, intermittently in icing conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "380. Refer to the chart: What wind speed do you expect over Rome at FL 340?",
    "options": [
      "a. 145KT",
      "b. 340KT",
      "c. 95KT",
      "d. 140 km/h"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 145KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "381. Refer to the chart: On which route do you expect moderate to severe CAT at FL 300?",
    "options": [
      "a. Zurich-Rome",
      "b. London-Zurich",
      "c. Zurich-Copenhagen",
      "d. Paris-Bordeaux"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Zurich-Rome"
  },
  {
    "question": "382. Which air mass and cloud depiction matches the routing A-B?",
    "options": [
      "a. B",
      "b. C",
      "c. D",
      "d. A"
    ],
    "answer": "a. B"
  },
  {
    "question": "383. On which route do you expect the cross section below?",
    "options": [
      "a. A-D",
      "b. B-C",
      "c. B-D",
      "d. A-E"
    ],
    "answer": "c. B-D"
  },
  {
    "question": "384. On which route do you expect the cross section below?",
    "options": [
      "a. B-A",
      "b. D-A",
      "c. B-C",
      "d. C-A"
    ],
    "answer": "b. D-A"
  },
  {
    "question": "385. The vertical extension of radiation fog during the winter over flat land is approximately:",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 ft",
      "b. 1000 ft",
      "c. 2000 ft",
      "d. more than 2000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "386. What is sublimation?",
    "options": [
      "a. The change of state from ice to water",
      "b. The change of state from water to water vapour",
      "c. The change of state from water vapour to water",
      "d. The change of state from ice to water vapour or from water vapour to ice"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The change of state from ice to water vapour or from water vapour to ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "387. What is evaporation?",
    "options": [
      "a. The change of state from ice to water",
      "b. The change of state from water to water vapour",
      "c. The change of state from water vapour to water",
      "d. The change of state from ice to water vapour or from water vapour to ice"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The change of state from water to water vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "388. What is condensation?",
    "options": [
      "a. The change of state from ice to water",
      "b. The change of state from water to water vapour",
      "c. The change of state from water vapour to water",
      "d. The change of state from ice to water vapour or from water vapour to ice"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The change of state from water vapour to water"
  },
  {
    "question": "389. What is freezing?",
    "options": [
      "a. The change of state from ice to water",
      "b. The change of state from water to water vapour",
      "c. The change of state from water vapour to water",
      "d. The change of state from water to ice"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The change of state from water to ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "390. In an anticyclone in the Northern Hemisphere, with curved isobars, the speed of the gradient wind.....",
    "options": [
      "a. is lower than the geostrophic wind",
      "b. equals the cyclostrophic wind",
      "c. depends on Coriolis force only",
      "d. is greater than the geostrophic wind"
    ],
    "answer": "d. is greater than the geostrophic wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "391. Why are there no or very few clouds, when a high pressure area is present?",
    "options": [
      "a. Because of subsiding air, subject to adiabatic heating",
      "b. Because of rising air, cooling adiabatically at the saturated adiabatic lapse rate",
      "c. The air is warmed from below",
      "d. Warm air moves over a cold surface, thus, generating stability"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Because of subsiding air, subject to adiabatic heating"
  },
  {
    "question": "392. What is drizzle?",
    "options": [
      "a. Small water droplets of 0,2 to 0,5 mm in diameter",
      "b. Water droplets of more than 0,5 mm in diameter",
      "c. Precipitation which forms mostly in CB and CU clouds",
      "d. Typical precipitation, when NS clouds are present"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Small water droplets of 0,2 to 0,5 mm in diameter"
  },
  {
    "question": "393. What (amongst other) is the purpose for consulting an SWC chart prior to flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. To avoid areas with turbulence",
      "b. To obtain exact weather information for the destination airport",
      "c. To obtain complete weather forecasts for the entire route of flight",
      "d. To obtain weather information for a VFR flight only"
    ],
    "answer": "a. To avoid areas with turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "394. Which forces are balanced with geostrophic winds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Pressure gradient force, Coriolis force.",
      "b. Friction force, pressure gradient force, Coriolis force.",
      "c. Pressure gradient force, Coriolis force, centrifugal force.",
      "d. Pressure gradient force, centrifugal force, friction force."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Pressure gradient force, Coriolis force."
  },
  {
    "question": "395. Whilst flying at FL 180 on the northern hemisphere an aircraft experiences right drift. What effect, if any, will this have on the aircraft's true altitude ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Without knowing the pressure change this question cannot be answered.",
      "b. It increases.",
      "c. It remains constant.",
      "d. It decreases"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "396. In the southern hemisphere what wind effect would you expect when flying from a high pressure area towards a low pressure area at FL 100?",
    "options": [
      "a. Wind from the left.",
      "b. Wind from the right.",
      "c. Tailwind with no drift.",
      "d. Headwind with no drift."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Wind from the right."
  },
  {
    "question": "397. The geostrophic wind is greater than the gradient wind around a low pressure system because the",
    "options": [
      "a. centrifugal force opposes the pressure gradient",
      "b. centrifugal force is added to the pressure gradient",
      "c. coriolis force is added to the pressure gradient",
      "d. coriolis force opposes to the centrifugal force"
    ],
    "answer": "a. centrifugal force opposes the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "398. The geostrophic wind is less than the gradient wind around an anticyclone because the",
    "options": [
      "a. centrifugal force opposes the pressure gradient",
      "b. centrifugal force is added to the pressure gradient",
      "c. effect of coriolis is added to friction",
      "d. coriolis effect opposes the centrifugal force"
    ],
    "answer": "b. centrifugal force is added to the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "399. An aircraft is flying in the southern hemisphere at low altitude (less than 2000 feet) and going directly away from a centre of low pressure. What direction, relative to the aircraft, does the wind come from ?",
    "options": [
      "a. From the left and slightly on the tail",
      "b. From the right and slightly on the nose",
      "c. From the right and slightly on the tail",
      "d. From the left and slightly on the nose"
    ],
    "answer": "d. From the left and slightly on the nose"
  },
  {
    "question": "400. What prevents air from flowing directly from high-pressure areas to low-pressure areas ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The pressure gradient force",
      "b. Surface friction",
      "c. Katabatic force",
      "d. Coriolis force"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "question": "401. An aircraft flying in the southern hemisphere at 2000 feet, has to turn to the right in order to allow for drift. In which direction, relative to the aircraft, is the centre of low pressure ?",
    "options": [
      "a. To the left.",
      "b. Behind.",
      "c. In front.",
      "d. To the right."
    ],
    "answer": "c. In front."
  },
  {
    "question": "402. Wind is caused by",
    "options": [
      "a. the rotation of the earth",
      "b. horizontal pressure differences",
      "c. friction between the air and the ground",
      "d. the movements of fronts"
    ],
    "answer": "b. horizontal pressure differences"
  },
  {
    "question": "403. You are flying from east to west in the northern hemisphere at the 500 hPa pressure surface. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. If you have a tail wind you are losing altitude",
      "b. If the wind is from the south you are gaining altitude",
      "c. If you have a head wind you are gaining altitude",
      "d. If the wind is from the north you are gaining altitude"
    ],
    "answer": "d. If the wind is from the north you are gaining altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "404. Geostrophic wind is the wind when isobars are",
    "options": [
      "a. straight lines and no friction is involved.",
      "b. curved lines and no friction is involved",
      "c. straight lines and friction is involved.",
      "d. curved lines and friction is involved."
    ],
    "answer": "a. straight lines and no friction is involved."
  },
  {
    "question": "405. The wind tends to follow the contour lines (isohypses) above the friction layer because",
    "options": [
      "a. the coriolis force tends to balance with the horizontal pressure gradient force",
      "b. contour lines are lines that connect points with the same windspeed in the upper air",
      "c. the coriolis force acts perpendicular on a line that connects high and low pressure system",
      "d. the friction of the air with the earth's surface gives the airflow a diversion perpendicular to the gradient force."
    ],
    "answer": "a. the coriolis force tends to balance with the horizontal pressure gradient force"
  },
  {
    "question": "406. The wind speed in a system with curved isobars compared to a system with straight isobars is (other conditions being the same)",
    "options": [
      "a. always higher",
      "b. higher if curvature is anticyclonic",
      "c. always lower",
      "d. higher if curvature is cyclonic"
    ],
    "answer": "b. higher if curvature is anticyclonic"
  },
  {
    "question": "407. The geostrophic wind depends on",
    "options": [
      "a. centripetal force, height, pressure gradient",
      "b. earth's rotation, geographic latitude, centripetal force",
      "c. geographic latitude, centripetal force, height",
      "d. density, earth's rotation, geographic latitude"
    ],
    "answer": "d. density, earth's rotation, geographic latitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "408. The difference between geostrophic wind and gradient wind is caused by",
    "options": [
      "a. curvature of isobars",
      "b. friction",
      "c. horizontal temperature gradients",
      "d. slope of pressure surfaces"
    ],
    "answer": "a. curvature of isobars"
  },
  {
    "question": "409. The geostrophic wind speed is directly proportional to the",
    "options": [
      "a. density of the air",
      "b. curvature of isobars",
      "c. sine of latitude",
      "d. horizontal pressure gradient"
    ],
    "answer": "d. horizontal pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "410. Geostrophic wind",
    "options": [
      "a. is perpendicular to the horizontal pressure gradient force",
      "b. is directly proportional to the density of the air",
      "c. always increases with increasing height",
      "d. veers with height if cold air is advected in the northern hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. is perpendicular to the horizontal pressure gradient force"
  },
  {
    "question": "411. For a similar pressure gradient, the geostrophic wind speed will be",
    "options": [
      "a. the same at all latitudes north or south of 15\u00b0",
      "b. greater at 60\u00b0N than at 30\u00b0N",
      "c. greater at 30\u00b0N than at 60\u00b0N",
      "d. equivalent to gradient wind \u00b1 thermal component"
    ],
    "answer": "c. greater at 30\u00b0N than at 60\u00b0N"
  },
  {
    "question": "412. For the same pressure gradient at 60\u00b0N, 50\u00b0N and 40\u00b0N the speed of the geostrophic wind will be",
    "options": [
      "a. greatest at 40\u00b0N",
      "b. the same at all latitudes",
      "c. greatest at 60\u00b0N",
      "d. least at 50\u00b0N"
    ],
    "answer": "a. greatest at 40\u00b0N"
  },
  {
    "question": "413. Under anticyclone conditions in the northern hemisphere, with curved isobars the speed of the gradient wind is",
    "options": [
      "a. less than the geostrophic wind",
      "b. greater than the geostrophic wind",
      "c. the same as the thermal component",
      "d. proportional only to the Coriolis force"
    ],
    "answer": "b. greater than the geostrophic wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "414. Which is a characteristic of low level wind shear as it relates to frontal activity ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The amount of wind shear in cold fronts is insignificant and does not have to be considered.",
      "b. With a warm front, the most critical period is just before the front has passed the airport.",
      "c. With a cold front, the most critical period is just before the front passes the airport.",
      "d. Turbulence will always exist in wind-shear conditions."
    ],
    "answer": "b. With a warm front, the most critical period is just before the front has passed the airport."
  },
  {
    "question": "415. Concerning advection fog, a possible extent and duration is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Tens of meters and many days.",
      "b. Tens of meters and some hours.",
      "c. Hundreds of meters and many days.",
      "d. Hundreds of meters and some hours."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Hundreds of meters and many days."
  },
  {
    "question": "416. Fog formation by warm and humid air flowing over cold areas is often extensive and of long duration. Such fog is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation fog.",
      "b. Advection fog",
      "c. Orografic fog.",
      "d. Frontal fog"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "417. When CAT (clear air turbulence) conditions are anticipated, the following procedure should be used as soon as turbulent air penetration speed is established:",
    "options": [
      "a. The airspeed indicator should be used as primary flight instrument.",
      "b. The attitude indicator should be used as secondary flight instrument.",
      "c. Maintain wings level and control pitch attitude smoothly.",
      "d. Prepare the use of large control inputs to fight the excessive G-forces that may occur."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Maintain wings level and control pitch attitude smoothly."
  },
  {
    "question": "418. Define a warm front:",
    "options": [
      "a. The front side of a heat wave.",
      "b. The situation when cold air displaces warm air.",
      "c. The situation when warm air displaces cold air.",
      "d. The same as an occlusion."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The situation when warm air displaces cold air."
  },
  {
    "question": "419. State in which type of front supercooled raindrops most frequently occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm front.",
      "b. Cold front.",
      "c. Occlusion.",
      "d. Stationary front."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Warm front."
  },
  {
    "question": "420. How would you describe a jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. A zone of wind in the upper troposphere or lower stratosphere with wind forces at 60 knots minimum.",
      "b. The outflow airstream from a turbine engine..",
      "c. Any wind force above 64 knots.",
      "d. A zone of winds in connection with a \"squall line\"."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A zone of wind in the upper troposphere or lower stratosphere with wind forces at 60 knots minimum."
  },
  {
    "question": "421. The wind force at an isobaric surface in the Northern Hemisphere:",
    "options": [
      "a. increases with increased inclination of the isobaric surface.",
      "b. is greatest when the isobaric surface is horizontal.",
      "c. is not influenced by inclination of the isobaric surface.",
      "d. decreases with increased inclination of the isobaric surface."
    ],
    "answer": "a. increases with increased inclination of the isobaric surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "422. Which phenomenon is often associated with a jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. Icing.",
      "b. Clear air turbulence (CAT).",
      "c. Windshear.",
      "d. Both a and b."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Clear air turbulence (CAT)."
  },
  {
    "question": "423. The approximate position of the polar jetstream is:",
    "options": [
      "a. approx. 60\u00b0N",
      "b. approx. 30\u00b0N",
      "c. approx. 80\u00b0N",
      "d. Over the north polar area."
    ],
    "answer": "a. approx. 60\u00b0N"
  },
  {
    "question": "424. When the inclination of isobar surfaces are equal, the geostrophic wind velocity depends upon",
    "options": [
      "a. Air density.",
      "b. Latitude.",
      "c. Temperature.",
      "d. Centrifugal force."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Latitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "425. Buys-Ballot's law of winds states that in the northern hemisphere standing with your back to the wind, you have:",
    "options": [
      "a. A low pressure ahead at an angle to your left, and a high pressure behind you at an angle to the right.",
      "b. A low pressure ahead at an angle to your right, and a high pressure behind you at an angle to the left.",
      "c. A high pressure ahead at an angle to your right, and a low pressure behind you at an angle to the left.",
      "d. A high pressure ahead at an angle to your left, and a low pressure behind you at an angle to the right."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A low pressure ahead at an angle to your left, and a high pressure behind you at an angle to the right."
  },
  {
    "question": "426. The weather most likely as a warm front passes is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Light showers, moderate continuous drizzle",
      "b. Moderate continuous rain, intermittent light drizzle",
      "c. Moderate continuous rain, rain showers"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Moderate continuous rain, intermittent light drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "427. Which of the following processes can produce both fog and clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Divergence",
      "b. Advection",
      "c. Convection"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Advection"
  },
  {
    "question": "428. The wind that flows along straight, parallel isobars is called the:",
    "options": [
      "a. Gradient Wind",
      "b. Geostrophic Wind",
      "c. Isobaric Wind"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Geostrophic Wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "429. Turbulence at low level is more likely to be associated with:",
    "options": [
      "a. Steady drizzle",
      "b. An anticyclone over the ocean",
      "c. A temperature inversion"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "430. Select the true statement concerning isobars and wind flow patterns around high and low pressure systems that are shown on a pressure chart:",
    "options": [
      "a. Surface winds flow perpendicular to the isobars",
      "b. When the isobars are far apart, crests of standing waves may be marked by lenticular clouds",
      "c. When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is stronger, and wind velocities are higher",
      "d. When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is weaker, and wind velocities are lower"
    ],
    "answer": "c. When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is stronger, and wind velocities are higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "431. A sea breeze blows:",
    "options": [
      "a. From the sea by day",
      "b. From the sea by night",
      "c. From the land by day"
    ],
    "answer": "a. From the sea by day"
  },
  {
    "question": "432. A land breeze blows:",
    "options": [
      "a. From the sea by day",
      "b. From the sea by night",
      "c. From the land by night"
    ],
    "answer": "c. From the land by night"
  },
  {
    "question": "433. Within a depression, two air masses meet so that a warm front is formed. In relation to a typical warm front:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm air will be replaced by cold air, the frontal slope will be around 1:150",
      "b. Cold air will be replaced by warm air, the frontal slope will be around 1:150",
      "c. Warm air will be replaced by cold air, the frontal slope will be around 1:50"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cold air will be replaced by warm air, the frontal slope will be around 1:150"
  },
  {
    "question": "434. As a warm front approaches a stationary observer, the cloud base:",
    "options": [
      "a. Remains the same",
      "b. Lowers",
      "c. Rises"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Lowers"
  },
  {
    "question": "435. The cloud sequence that could be expected during the passage of a typical warm front would be:",
    "options": [
      "a. CI, AS, CB, CU",
      "b. AS, CI, CS, ST, NS",
      "c. CI, CS, AS, NS, ST"
    ],
    "answer": "c. CI, CS, AS, NS, ST"
  },
  {
    "question": "436. Where are jetstreams normally located?",
    "options": [
      "a. In areas of strong low pressure systems in the stratosphere",
      "b. At the tropopause where intensified temperature gradients are located",
      "c. In a single continuous band, encircling the Earth, where there is a break between the equatorial and polar tropopause"
    ],
    "answer": "b. At the tropopause where intensified temperature gradients are located"
  },
  {
    "question": "437. Which type clouds may be associated with the jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB cloud line where the jetstream crosses the cold front",
      "b. CI clouds on the equatorial side of the jetstream",
      "c. CS cloud band on the polar side and under the jetstream"
    ],
    "answer": "b. CI clouds on the equatorial side of the jetstream"
  },
  {
    "question": "438. Where do the maximum winds associated with the jetstream usually occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the vicinity of breaks in the tropopause on the polar side of the jet core",
      "b. Below the jet core where a long straight stretch of the jetstream is located",
      "c. On the equatorial side of the jetstream where moisture has formed cirriform clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the vicinity of breaks in the tropopause on the polar side of the jet core"
  },
  {
    "question": "439. Where is the normal location of the jetstream relative to surface lows and fronts?",
    "options": [
      "a. North of the surface systems",
      "b. South of the low and warm front",
      "c. Over the low and crosses both the warm front and the cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. North of the surface systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "440. Which type frontal system is normally crossed by the jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold front and warm front",
      "b. Warm front",
      "c. Occluded front"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Occluded front"
  },
  {
    "question": "441. When flying at FL 180 in the Northern Hemisphere you experience a right drift:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your TA decreases",
      "b. Your TA increases",
      "c. Your TA remains unchanged",
      "d. Not enough information is provided to determine the TA"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Your TA decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "442. When flying at FL 180 in the Northern Hemisphere you experience a left drift:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your TA decreases",
      "b. Your TA increases",
      "c. Your TA remains unchanged",
      "d. Not enough information is provided to determine the TA"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Your TA increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "443. In a warm front, a freezing level of 10'000 ft in the warm air and 2000 ft in the cold air is observed. Where is the probability for FZRA the lowest?",
    "options": [
      "a. 5000 ft",
      "b. 12'000 ft",
      "c. 10'000 ft",
      "d. 1000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 12'000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "444. What can be said about a wind speed of 350 KT in a jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is possible, but rare",
      "b. It is impossible",
      "c. A wind speed of 350 KT is common",
      "d. It is only possible in a subtropical jetstream"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It is possible, but rare"
  },
  {
    "question": "445. A warm front is approaching an airport:",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE and QNH decrease",
      "b. QFE increases and QNH decreases",
      "c. QFE decreases and QNH increases",
      "d. QNH decreases, while QFE remains unchanged"
    ],
    "answer": "a. QFE and QNH decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "446. Where do you encounter the strongest winds close to the ground?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the transition zone between air masses",
      "b. I a cold air mass",
      "c. At a point distant from the center of the occlusion",
      "d. When a ridge is present"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the transition zone between air masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "447. How is the weather in Bombay in early July influenced?",
    "options": [
      "a. By SW monsoon",
      "b. By NE monsoon",
      "c. By the Harmattan",
      "d. By the trade winds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. By SW monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "448. What clouds do you expect approximately 800 km ahead of a warm front?",
    "options": [
      "a. CS",
      "b. AC",
      "c. NS",
      "d. CU"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CS"
  },
  {
    "question": "449. The average slope of a warm front is approximately:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1:150",
      "b. 1:250",
      "c. 1: 500",
      "d. 1:80"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1:150"
  },
  {
    "question": "450. What is the geostrophic wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. It blows along curved isobars, and is affected by Coriolis force and centrifugal force",
      "b. It blows parallel to straight isobars when there are no gradient forces present",
      "c. It blows along curved isobars when frictional forces are present",
      "d. It blows parallel to straight isobars, when no friction is present"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It blows parallel to straight isobars, when no friction is present"
  },
  {
    "question": "451. State the altitude at which the core of the Arctic Jet Stream can be found:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20000 ft",
      "b. 30000 ft",
      "c. 40000 ft",
      "d. 50000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 20000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "452. State the altitude at which the core of the Subtropical Jet Stream can be found:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20000 ft",
      "b. 30000 ft",
      "c. 40000 ft",
      "d. 50000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 40000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "453. What characteristics will the surface winds have in an area where the isobars on the weather map are very close together?",
    "options": [
      "a. Strong and parallel to the isobars.",
      "b. Very weak but gusty and flowing across the isobars.",
      "c. Strong and flowing across the isobars.",
      "d. Moderate and parallel to the isobars."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Strong and flowing across the isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "454. Select the true statement concerning isobars and wind flow patterns around high- and low-pressure systems that are shown on a surface weather chart.",
    "options": [
      "a. When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is greater and wind velocities are stronger.",
      "b. Surface winds flow perpendicular to the isobars.",
      "c. Isobars connect contour lines of equal temperature.",
      "d. When the isobars are far apart, crest of standing waves may be marked by stationary lenticular clouds."
    ],
    "answer": "a. When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is greater and wind velocities are stronger."
  },
  {
    "question": "455. Where are you likely to find the strongest winds close to the ground?",
    "options": [
      "a. At the centre of a high-pressure system",
      "b. At the centre of a low-pressure system",
      "c. In the transition zone between two air masses",
      "d. Where there is little variation in pressure over a large area during the winter months"
    ],
    "answer": "c. In the transition zone between two air masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "456. The greater the pressure gradient the",
    "options": [
      "a. further the isobars will be apart and the weaker the wind",
      "b. closer the isobars and the stronger the wind",
      "c. closer the isobars and the lower the temperatures",
      "d. further the isobars will be apart and the higher the temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "b. closer the isobars and the stronger the wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "457. When isobars, for an area in the mid-latitudes on a weather map, are close together, the wind is most likely to be",
    "options": [
      "a. strong",
      "b. blowing perpendicular to the isobars",
      "c. changing direction rapidly",
      "d. light"
    ],
    "answer": "a. strong"
  },
  {
    "question": "458. Which of the following is true concerning an aircraft that is flying at FL180 in the northern hemisphere, where wind is geostrophic and the true altitude remains constant ?",
    "options": [
      "a. There is a cross wind from the right",
      "b. There is a cross wind from the left",
      "c. There is no cross wind",
      "d. Without knowing temperature at FL 180 this question can not be answered"
    ],
    "answer": "c. There is no cross wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "459. An aircraft is flying on a constant heading with left drift in the northern hemisphere, maintaining a constant indicated pressure altitude. Which of the following is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is likely to be climbing relative to the surface",
      "b. It is likely to be maintaining a constant distance relative to the surface",
      "c. It is likely to be descending relative to the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It is likely to be climbing relative to the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "460. In an area of converging air",
    "options": [
      "a. clouds can not be formed",
      "b. convective clouds can be dissolved",
      "c. stratified clouds can be dissolved",
      "d. clouds can be formed"
    ],
    "answer": "d. clouds can be formed"
  },
  {
    "question": "461. Divergence in the upper air results, near the surface, in",
    "options": [
      "a. falling pressure and likely dissipation of clouds",
      "b. rising pressure and likely formation of clouds",
      "c. rising pressure and likely dissipation of clouds",
      "d. falling pressure and likely formation of clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "d. falling pressure and likely formation of clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "462. In a low pressure system the convergence at the surface is caused by",
    "options": [
      "a. the inbalance of the horizontal gradient force and the Coriolis force",
      "b. centripetal forces",
      "c. frictional forces",
      "d. the curvature of the isobars"
    ],
    "answer": "c. frictional forces"
  },
  {
    "question": "463. Between which latitudes are you most likely to find the subtropical high-pressure belt ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 55\u00b0-75\u00b0.",
      "b. 10\u00b0 -15\u00b0.",
      "c. 35\u00b0 - 55\u00b0.",
      "d. 25\u00b0 -35\u00b0."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 25\u00b0 -35\u00b0."
  },
  {
    "question": "464. Between which latitudes are you most likely to find the region of travelling low pressure systems ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 35\u00b0 - 55\u00b0",
      "b. 55\u00b0-75\u00b0",
      "c. 25\u00b0 - 35\u00b0",
      "d. 10\u00b0 -15\u00b0"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 55\u00b0-75\u00b0"
  },
  {
    "question": "465. In the central part of the Atlantic Ocean between 10\u00b0N and 20\u00b0N the prevailing winds are",
    "options": [
      "a. NE monsoon in winter and SW monsoon in summer",
      "b. NE trade winds",
      "c. SE trade winds",
      "d. SW winds throughout the whole year"
    ],
    "answer": "b. NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "466. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation, the SE trade winds are applicable to zone",
    "options": [
      "a. w",
      "b. t",
      "c. u",
      "d. v"
    ],
    "answer": "b. t"
  },
  {
    "question": "467. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"t\" is an area of",
    "options": [
      "a. NE trade winds",
      "b. SE trade winds",
      "c. travelling low pressure systems",
      "d. subtropical high pressure systems"
    ],
    "answer": "d. subtropical high pressure systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "468. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation the travelling low pressure systems are applicable to zone",
    "options": [
      "a. u and w",
      "b. t only",
      "c. t and x",
      "d. s and y"
    ],
    "answer": "d. s and y"
  },
  {
    "question": "469. Considering Melbourne (C) in July, the weather is predominantly influenced by the zone of",
    "options": [
      "a. equatorial low pressure due to the proximity of the intertropical convergence zone over central Australia",
      "b. antarctic high pressure due to the absence of any protective land mass between south Australia and Antarctica",
      "c. disturbed temperate low pressure, bringing an almost continuous succession of fronts resulting in strong winds, low cloud and rain",
      "d. subtropical high pressure, with the occasional passage of fronts originating in the adjacent zone of disturbed temperate low pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "d. subtropical high pressure, with the occasional passage of fronts originating in the adjacent zone of disturbed temperate low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "470. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"y\" is an area of",
    "options": [
      "a. SE trade winds",
      "b. NE trade winds",
      "c. travelling low pressure systems",
      "d. subtropical high pressure systems"
    ],
    "answer": "c. travelling low pressure systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "471. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation, the NE trade winds are applicable to zone",
    "options": [
      "a. u",
      "b. t",
      "c. v",
      "d. w"
    ],
    "answer": "a. u"
  },
  {
    "question": "472. Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"u\" is in area of",
    "options": [
      "a. SW trade winds",
      "b. travelling depressions",
      "c. NE trade winds",
      "d. subtropical high pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "c. NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "473. When a cold front has passed over an airfield, the wind will:",
    "options": [
      "a. \"reverse\".",
      "b. \"veer\".",
      "c. not change.",
      "d. become laminar."
    ],
    "answer": "b. \"veer\"."
  },
  {
    "question": "474. Bad weather usually follows a low pressure because there will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. Convergence.",
      "b. Divergence.",
      "c. Convergence with lifting of air masses in a deeper layer.",
      "d. A sinking of the air masses."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Convergence with lifting of air masses in a deeper layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "475. What is meant by an area of divergence?",
    "options": [
      "a. An area where air masses are moving in",
      "b. An area where air masses are moving out",
      "c. A frontal zone.",
      "d. A high pressure area"
    ],
    "answer": "b. An area where air masses are moving out"
  },
  {
    "question": "476. What is the cloud-type sequence most likely to be associated with the passage of a cold front?",
    "options": [
      "a. CU/CB, NS and low ST",
      "b. SC/CB, and BKN ST",
      "c. CU/CB, Isol CU"
    ],
    "answer": "c. CU/CB, Isol CU"
  },
  {
    "question": "477. Within a depression, two air masses meet so that a cold front is formed. In relation to a typical cold front:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm air will be replaced by cold air, the frontal slope will be around 1:80",
      "b. Cold air will be replaced by warm air, the frontal slope will be around 1:80",
      "c. Warm air will be replaced by cold air, the frontal slope will be around 1:150"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Warm air will be replaced by cold air, the frontal slope will be around 1:80"
  },
  {
    "question": "478. Name the jetstream(s) which appear all year round:",
    "options": [
      "a. Subtropical and polar front jetstream",
      "b. Subtropical jetstream only",
      "c. Polar front jetstream only",
      "d. Arctical jetstream"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Subtropical and polar front jetstream"
  },
  {
    "question": "479. The ITCZ affects",
    "options": [
      "a. West Africa between 10\u00b0 and 30\u00b0 N, and the north coasts of the Arabian Sea",
      "b. East Africa between 10\u00b0 and 20\u00b0 N",
      "c. West Africa between 10\u00b0 and 30\u00b0 N only",
      "d. The entire African continent"
    ],
    "answer": "a. West Africa between 10\u00b0 and 30\u00b0 N, and the north coasts of the Arabian Sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "480. What can be said about showers at a cold front?",
    "options": [
      "a. Unstable air is present",
      "b. They occur mostly in stable air",
      "c. It is a sign for a cold occlusion",
      "d. NS clouds are present"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Unstable air is present"
  },
  {
    "question": "481. Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Zurich-Hamburg, FL 260:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20015KT",
      "b. 02020KT",
      "c. 23020KT",
      "d. 26025KT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 23020KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "482. Refer to the chart: State the average temperature for the route Zurich-Lissabon, FL 200:",
    "options": [
      "a. -33\u00b0C",
      "b. -30\u00b0C",
      "c. -41\u00b0C",
      "d. -49\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -33\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "483. Refer to the chart: State the height of the -40\u00b0C isotherm over Stockholm:",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 410",
      "b. FL 230",
      "c. FL 390",
      "d. FL 250"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 230"
  },
  {
    "question": "484. Which upper level chart do you use when preparing a flight at a cruising altitude of FL 170?",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 hPa",
      "b. 850 hPa",
      "c. 700 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "485. Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Athens-Geneva, FL 160:",
    "options": [
      "a. 05035KT",
      "b. 26040KT",
      "c. 21025KT",
      "d. 23040KT"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "486. Refer to the chart: State the average temperature for the route Athens-Geneva, FL 150:",
    "options": [
      "a. -21\u00b0C",
      "b. -14\u00b0C",
      "c. -27\u00b0C",
      "d. -11\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -14\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "487. Refer to the chart: State the air temperature and the deviation to ISA over Copenhagen at FL 140:",
    "options": [
      "a. 8\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "b. 4\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "c. 8\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "d. 12\u00b0C colder than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 8\u00b0C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "488. Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Zurich-Rome, FL 110:",
    "options": [
      "a. 23015KT",
      "b. 20030KT",
      "c. 04010KT",
      "d. 25020KT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 23015KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "489. Refer to the chart: State the average air temperature for the route Zurich-Rome, FL 110:",
    "options": [
      "a. -06\u00b0C",
      "b. -09\u00b0C",
      "c. -12\u00b0C",
      "d. +05\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -09\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "490. Refer to the chart: State the height of the freezing level over Shannon by applying the common vertical temperature gradient:",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 140",
      "b. FL 120",
      "c. FL 60",
      "d. FL 20"
    ],
    "answer": "c. FL 60"
  },
  {
    "question": "491. Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Frankfurt-Rome, FL 170:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20050KT",
      "b. 23040KT",
      "c. 06050KT",
      "d. 03035KT"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "492. Refer to the chart: State the height of the freezing level over Tunis, considering the common vertical temperature gradient:",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 260",
      "b. FL 180",
      "c. FL 100",
      "d. FL 20"
    ],
    "answer": "c. FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "493. Refer to the chart: What is the average temperature deviation from ISA for the route Frankfurt-Rome?",
    "options": [
      "a. 10\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "b. 10\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "c. 4\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "d. 4\u00b0C warmer than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 4\u00b0C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "494. Refer to the chart: What is the average temperature for the route Geneva- Stockholm, FL 260:",
    "options": [
      "a. -55\u00b0C",
      "b. -51\u00b0C",
      "c. -63\u00b0C",
      "d. -47\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. -47\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "495. Refer to the chart: What is the average wind for the route Shannon-Lisbon, FL 290:",
    "options": [
      "a. 36080KT",
      "b. 03070KT",
      "c. 19075KT",
      "d. 34090KT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 36080KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "496. The average slope of a cold front is approximately:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1:150",
      "b. 1:250",
      "c. 1: 500",
      "d. 1:80"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1:80"
  },
  {
    "question": "497. Which degree of aircraft turbulence is determined by the following ICAO description? \"There may be moderate changes in aircraft attitude and/or altitude but the aircraft remains in positive control at all times. Usually, small variations in air speed. Changes in accelerometer readings of 0.5 to 1.0 g at the aircraft's center of gravity. Occupants feel strain against seat belts. Loose",
    "options": [
      "a. Severe.",
      "b. Light.",
      "c. Moderate.",
      "d. Violent."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Moderate."
  },
  {
    "question": "498. All pilots encountering Clear Air Turbulence are requested to report it. You experience CAT which causes passengers and crew to feel definite strain against their seat belt or shoulders straps. Unsecured objects are dislodged. Food service and walking are difficult. This intensity of CAT should be reported as",
    "options": [
      "a. light",
      "b. moderate",
      "c. severe",
      "d. extreme"
    ],
    "answer": "b. moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "499. On a weather chart an occlusion is indicated by a coloured line of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Violet.",
      "b. Yellow.",
      "c. Black.",
      "d. Green."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Violet."
  },
  {
    "question": "500. On a weather chart fog is indicated by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Yellow colour or horizontal lines.",
      "b. Green colour.",
      "c. Blue colour.",
      "d. Green comma sign."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Yellow colour or horizontal lines."
  },
  {
    "question": "501. You cross a jet stream 2500 ft below the core at a right angle over Western Europe. While crossing, the temperature is increasing. What wind direction do you encounter?",
    "options": [
      "a. Wind from the right",
      "b. Wind from the left",
      "c. Information insufficient to determine wind direction",
      "d. Calm winds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Wind from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "502. Which of the following symbols show a hazard for IFR flights, according to ICAO?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. A, B",
      "c. C",
      "d. C, D"
    ],
    "answer": "d. C, D"
  },
  {
    "question": "503. Which of the following symbols show a hazard for IFR flights, according to ICAO?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. A, B",
      "c. C",
      "d. C, D"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A"
  },
  {
    "question": "504. Which of the following symbols show a hazard for IFR flights, according to ICAO?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. A, B",
      "c. A, C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "d. D"
  },
  {
    "question": "505. Which of the following symbols show a hazard for IFR flights, according to ICAO?",
    "options": [
      "a. A, C",
      "b. B",
      "c. A, D",
      "d. C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. B"
  },
  {
    "question": "506. What degree of turbulence, if any, is likely to be encountered while flying through a cold front in the summer over Central Europe at FL 100?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moderate turbulence in NS cloud.",
      "b. Severe turbulence in CB cloud.",
      "c. Light turbulence in CB cloud.",
      "d. Light turbulence in ST cloud."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Severe turbulence in CB cloud."
  },
  {
    "question": "507. Which cloud type may indicate the presence of severe turbulence ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Altocumulus lenticularis",
      "b. Stratocumulus",
      "c. Cirrocumulus",
      "d. Nimbostratus"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Altocumulus lenticularis"
  },
  {
    "question": "508. Fair weather cumulus often is an indication of",
    "options": [
      "a. a high risk of thunderstorms",
      "b. poor visibility at surface",
      "c. smooth flying conditions below the cloud level",
      "d. turbulence at and below the cloud level"
    ],
    "answer": "d. turbulence at and below the cloud level"
  },
  {
    "question": "509. On a clear summer day, turbulence caused by solar heating is most pronounced",
    "options": [
      "a. immediately after sunset",
      "b. during the early afternoon",
      "c. during early morning hours before sunrise",
      "d. about midmorning"
    ],
    "answer": "b. during the early afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "510. Generally northern hemisphere winds at 5000 FT/AGL are southwesterly while most of the surface winds are southerly. What is the primary reason of difference between these two wind directions?",
    "options": [
      "a. The influence of warm air at the lower altitude.",
      "b. A strong pressure gradient at higher altitudes.",
      "c. Stronger Coriolis force at the surface.",
      "d. Friction between the wind and the surface."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Friction between the wind and the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "511. Friction between the air and the ground results in the northern hemisphere in:",
    "options": [
      "a. backing of the wind and increase of wind speed at the surface.",
      "b. veering of the wind and decrease of wind speed at the surface.",
      "c. backing of the wind and decrease of wind speed at the surface.",
      "d. veering of the wind and increase of wind speed at the surface."
    ],
    "answer": "c. backing of the wind and decrease of wind speed at the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "512. You are flying at 2 500 FT/AGL, with a southerly wind, and intend to land at an airport, at sea level directly below. From approximately which direction would you expect the surface wind (mid-latitude, northern hemisphere)?",
    "options": [
      "a. South.",
      "b. South-southwest.",
      "c. Southwest.",
      "d. South-southeast."
    ],
    "answer": "d. South-southeast."
  },
  {
    "question": "513. In the lower layers of the atmosphere due to friction the wind changes direction towards the low pressure area because :",
    "options": [
      "a. turbulence is formed and pressure decreases",
      "b. the pressure gradient increases",
      "c. turbulence is formed and pressure increases",
      "d. wind speed decreases and therefore coriolis force decreases"
    ],
    "answer": "d. wind speed decreases and therefore coriolis force decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "514. What causes surface winds to flow across the isobars at an angle rather than parallel to the isobars ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Coriolis force",
      "b. Surface friction",
      "c. Greater density of the air at the surface",
      "d. Greater atmospheric pressure at the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Surface friction"
  },
  {
    "question": "515. If Paris reports a wind of 19015KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 16020KT",
      "b. 22030KT",
      "c. 25025KT",
      "d. 22010KT"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 22030KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "516. If Paris reports a wind of 08010KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 11020KT",
      "b. 08015KT",
      "c. 05020KT",
      "d. 08005KT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 11020KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "517. If Paris reports a wind of 16020KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground?",
    "options": [
      "a. 14020KT",
      "b. 16030KT",
      "c. 19040KT",
      "d. 17015KT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 19040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "518. If Paris reports a wind of 30012KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 30025KT",
      "b. 23030KT",
      "c. 33025KT",
      "d. 27020KT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 33025KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "519. In the northern hemisphere a pilot flying at 1000 FT/AGL directly towards the centre of a low pressure area, will find the wind blowing from",
    "options": [
      "a. about 45 degrees to the right of directly ahead",
      "b. right and behind",
      "c. left and behind",
      "d. directly ahead"
    ],
    "answer": "c. left and behind"
  },
  {
    "question": "520. In the northern hemisphere the wind at the surface blows",
    "options": [
      "a. from a low pressure area to a high pressure area",
      "b. counter-clockwise around, and toward the centre of, a low pressure area",
      "c. clockwise around, and away from the centre of, a low pressure area",
      "d. counter-clockwise around, and away from the centre of, a high pressure area."
    ],
    "answer": "b. counter-clockwise around, and toward the centre of, a low pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "521. During a descent from 2000 FT above the surface to the surface (no frontal passage) the wind normally",
    "options": [
      "a. backs and decreases",
      "b. veers and increases",
      "c. backs and increases",
      "d. veers and decreases"
    ],
    "answer": "a. backs and decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "522. What relationship exists between the wind at 3000 feet and the surface wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. The surface wind is veered compared to the wind at 3000 feet and is usually weaker.",
      "b. They have the same direction, but the surface wind is weaker, caused by friction",
      "c. They are practically the same, except when eddies exist, caused by obstacles",
      "d. The wind at 3000 feet is parallel to the isohypses and the surface wind direction is across the isobars toward the low pressure and the surface wind is weaker."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The wind at 3000 feet is parallel to the isohypses and the surface wind direction is across the isobars toward the low pressure and the surface wind is weaker."
  },
  {
    "question": "523. The vertical extent of the friction layer depends primarily on",
    "options": [
      "a. roughness of surface, temperature, local time",
      "b. wind speed, roughness of surface, temperature",
      "c. stability, wind speed, roughness of surface",
      "d. temperature, local time, environmental lapse rate"
    ],
    "answer": "c. stability, wind speed, roughness of surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "524. During periods of prolonged clear skies associated with anticyclonic conditions, the",
    "options": [
      "a. surface wind speed tends to be highest during the early afternoon",
      "b. surface wind speed tends to be highest at night",
      "c. angle between isobars and surface wind direction tends to be greatest in the early afternoon",
      "d. wind tends to back from early morning until early afternoon"
    ],
    "answer": "a. surface wind speed tends to be highest during the early afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "525. In the northern hemisphere the gradient wind of a cyclonic pressure distribution is 350/24, over the sea the surface wind would approximate",
    "options": [
      "a. 340/20",
      "b. 030/20",
      "c. 340/28",
      "d. 030/28"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 340/20"
  },
  {
    "question": "526. In the northern hemisphere with an anticyclonic pressure system the geostrophic wind at 2000 FT over the sea is 060/15. At the same position the surface wind is most likely to be",
    "options": [
      "a. 060/12",
      "b. 045/12",
      "c. 060/18",
      "d. 075/12"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 045/12"
  },
  {
    "question": "527. Severe turbulence is associated with a jetstream:",
    "options": [
      "a. At the low pressure side.",
      "b. At the high pressure side.",
      "c. In the core of the jetstream.",
      "d. Underneath the core of the jetstream."
    ],
    "answer": "a. At the low pressure side."
  },
  {
    "question": "528. Which of the following is most likely to occur after passage of a cold front?",
    "options": [
      "a. A fall in pressure, a fall in temperature and dew point",
      "b. A rise in pressure, a fall in temperature and dew point",
      "c. A rise in pressure, a fall in temperature and a rise in dew point"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A rise in pressure, a fall in temperature and dew point"
  },
  {
    "question": "529. What is the easterly wave?",
    "options": [
      "a. A wave in the trade wind belt, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity in the rear of its trough",
      "b. A wave in the moderate latitudes, moving from east to west, with mostly stable air in the rear of its trough",
      "c. An orographic-induced wave, moving to the east, in moderate latitudes",
      "d. A wave in the trade wind belt, moving to the east, with severe convective action in the rear of its trough"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A wave in the trade wind belt, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity in the rear of its trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "530. At the approach of a warm front (northern hemisphere) the wind direction changes from the surface up to the tropopause. The effect of this change is that the wind",
    "options": [
      "a. veers in the friction layer and backs above the friction layer",
      "b. backs in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer",
      "c. veers in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer",
      "d. backs in the friction layer and and backs above the friction layer"
    ],
    "answer": "c. veers in the friction layer and veers above the friction layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "531. In a land- and sea-breeze circulation the land-breeze blows :",
    "options": [
      "a. during the day and is stronger than the sea-breeze.",
      "b. during the night and is weaker than the sea-breeze.",
      "c. during the day and is weaker than the sea-breeze.",
      "d. during the night and is stronger than the sea-breeze."
    ],
    "answer": "b. during the night and is weaker than the sea-breeze."
  },
  {
    "question": "532. A high pressure area (shallow pressure gradient) covers an area of the Mediterranean Sea and its nearby airport. What surface wind direction is likely at the airport on a sunny afternoon?",
    "options": [
      "a. Parallel to the coastline.",
      "b. Land to sea.",
      "c. Variable.",
      "d. Sea to land."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Sea to land."
  },
  {
    "question": "533. A mountain breeze (katabatic wind) blows",
    "options": [
      "a. down the slope during the night.",
      "b. up the slope during the day.",
      "c. down the slope during the day.",
      "d. up the slope during the night."
    ],
    "answer": "a. down the slope during the night."
  },
  {
    "question": "534. The most frequent wind direction in a valley caused by thermal effects is toward the :",
    "options": [
      "a. valley during daylight hours.",
      "b. mountain at night.",
      "c. mountain during daylight hours.",
      "d. valley during daylight as much as at night."
    ],
    "answer": "c. mountain during daylight hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "535. Which of the following is true of a land breeze?",
    "options": [
      "a. It blows from land to water",
      "b. It blows from water to land",
      "c. It blows by day",
      "d. It blows only at noon"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It blows from land to water"
  },
  {
    "question": "536. An aircraft is approaching under visual flight rules an airfield whose runway is parallel to the coast. When downwind over the sea, the airfield is on the right. What wind effect should be anticipated on final approach and landing during a sunny afternoon?",
    "options": [
      "a. Crosswind from the left",
      "b. Crosswind from the right",
      "c. Tailwind",
      "d. Headwind"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Crosswind from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "537. An aircraft is approaching under visual flight rules an airfield whose runway is parallel to the coast. When downwind over the sea, the airfield is on the left. What wind effect should be anticipated on final approach and landing during a sunny afternoon ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Crosswind from the left",
      "b. Crosswind from the right",
      "c. Tailwind",
      "d. Headwind"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Crosswind from the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "538. When otherwise calm and clear conditions exist a station on the shore of a large body of water will experience wind",
    "options": [
      "a. continually from land to water",
      "b. from the water in daytime and from the land at night",
      "c. continually from water to the land",
      "d. from the land in daytime and from the water at night"
    ],
    "answer": "b. from the water in daytime and from the land at night"
  },
  {
    "question": "539. The sea breeze is a wind from the sea",
    "options": [
      "a. blowing at night in mid-latitudes",
      "b. that reaches up to the tropopause in daytime",
      "c. occurring only in the lower layers of the atmosphere in daytime",
      "d. occurring only in mid-latitudes and in daytime"
    ],
    "answer": "c. occurring only in the lower layers of the atmosphere in daytime"
  },
  {
    "question": "540. In a mountain-valley wind circulation, the mountain wind blows",
    "options": [
      "a. during the day up from the valley",
      "b. at night up from the valley",
      "c. during the day down from the mountains",
      "d. at night down from the mountains"
    ],
    "answer": "d. at night down from the mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "541. Which type wind flows downslope becoming warmer and dryer?",
    "options": [
      "a. Land breeze",
      "b. Valley wind",
      "c. Katabatic wind"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Katabatic wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "542. What is the main cause for the formation of a polar front jet stream?",
    "options": [
      "a. The varied elevations of the tropopause in the polar front region",
      "b. The pressure difference, close to the ground, between a high over the Azores and a low over Iceland",
      "c. The north-south horizontal temperature gradient at the polar front",
      "d. Strong winds in the upper atmosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The north-south horizontal temperature gradient at the polar front"
  },
  {
    "question": "543. Which jetstream is more or less found continuously around the Earth?",
    "options": [
      "a. The polar front jetstream.",
      "b. The artic front jetstream.",
      "c. The subtropical jetstream.",
      "d. The equatorial jetstream."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The subtropical jetstream."
  },
  {
    "question": "544. An aircraft is flying through the polar front jet stream from south to north, beneath the core. How would the OAT change, in the northern hemisphere, during this portion of the flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. It first increases, then decreases.",
      "b. It increases.",
      "c. It decreases.",
      "d. It remains constant."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "545. What is the minimum speed for a wind to be classified as a jet stream?",
    "options": [
      "a. 70 kt.",
      "b. 50 kt.",
      "c. 60 kt.",
      "d. 100 kt."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 60 kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "546. A wind sounding in the region of a polar front jet stream gives the following windprofile (Northern hemisphere). 900hPa 220/20kt 800hPa 220/25kt 700hPa 230/35kt 500hPa 260/60kt 400hPa 280/85kt 300hPa 300/100kt 250hPa 310/120kt 200hPa 310/80kt Which system is the jet stream associated with?",
    "options": [
      "a. With an easterly wave.",
      "b. With a cold front.",
      "c. With a ITCZ.",
      "d. With a warm front."
    ],
    "answer": "d. With a warm front."
  },
  {
    "question": "547. Which jet stream is connected with a surface front system?",
    "options": [
      "a. The arctic jet stream",
      "b. The polar front jet stream",
      "c. The subtropical jet stream",
      "d. The equatorial jet stream"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The polar front jet stream"
  },
  {
    "question": "548. What is the approximate ratio between height and width for a jet stream cross section?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1/1000",
      "b. 1/1",
      "c. 1/10",
      "d. 1/100"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1/100"
  },
  {
    "question": "549. An aircraft is flying from south to north, above the polar front jet stream, at FL 400 in the southern hemisphere. What change, if any, in temperature will be experienced ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It stays the same.",
      "b. It rises.",
      "c. It falls.",
      "d. It falls and then rises."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It falls."
  },
  {
    "question": "550. A wind speed of 350 kt within a jet stream core should be world-wide regarded as:",
    "options": [
      "a. a common occurence.",
      "b. not possible.",
      "c. possible but a very rare phenomenon.",
      "d. not unusual in polar regions."
    ],
    "answer": "c. possible but a very rare phenomenon."
  },
  {
    "question": "551. An aircraft over Western Europe is crossing a jet stream 2500 FT below its core at right angles. While crossing, the outside temperature is increasing. The prevailing wind is",
    "options": [
      "a. headwind.",
      "b. from the left.",
      "c. tailwind.",
      "d. from the right"
    ],
    "answer": "d. from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "552. Where, as a general rule, is the core of the polar front jet stream to be found?",
    "options": [
      "a. Just below the cold-air tropopause.",
      "b. In the cold air mass.",
      "c. Just above the warm-air tropopause.",
      "d. In the warm air mass."
    ],
    "answer": "d. In the warm air mass."
  },
  {
    "question": "553. You cross a jet stream in horizontal flight at approximately right angles. While crossing, in spite of a strong wind of 120 kt, you notice the temperature barely changes.",
    "options": [
      "a. You assume the front associated with the jet stream to be very weak with practically no temperature difference between the two airmasses.",
      "b. This phenomenon is absolutely normal as you are crossing the jet core.",
      "c. Since the result of such readings seems impossible, you will after landing have the instruments tested.",
      "d. This phenomenon does not surprise you at all, since normally no large temperature differences are possible at these heights."
    ],
    "answer": "b. This phenomenon is absolutely normal as you are crossing the jet core."
  },
  {
    "question": "554. What jet streams are likely to be crossed during a flight from Stockholm to Rio de Janeiro (23\u00b0S) at FL 350 in July ?",
    "options": [
      "a. A polar front jet stream followed by a subtropical jet stream and later, a second polar front jet stream.",
      "b. A subtropical jet stream followed by a polar front jet stream.",
      "c. A polar front jet stream followed by one or two subtropical jet streams.",
      "d. One subtropical jet stream."
    ],
    "answer": "c. A polar front jet stream followed by one or two subtropical jet streams."
  },
  {
    "question": "555. While crossing a jet stream at right angles in Western Europe (3000 FT below its core) and OAT is decreasing, what would be the prevailing wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. A headwind.",
      "b. Crosswind from the right",
      "c. Crosswind from the left",
      "d. A tailwind."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Crosswind from the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "556. Where, in central Europe, are the highest wind speeds to be found ?",
    "options": [
      "a. At about 5500 metres altitude",
      "b. Just below the tropopause",
      "c. Close to the ground",
      "d. In the stratosphere"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Just below the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "557. Which of the following statements concerning jet streams is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the northern hemisphere both westerly and easterly jet streams occur",
      "b. In the northern hemisphere only westerly jet streams occur",
      "c. In the southern hemisphere no jet streams occur",
      "d. In the southern hemisphere only easterly jet streams occur"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the northern hemisphere both westerly and easterly jet streams occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "558. Which of the following statements concerning the core of a polar front jet stream is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It lies in the warm air; its pressure surfaces are horizontal at the height of the core",
      "b. It and its surface projection lie in the warm air",
      "c. It lies at a height where there is no horizontal temperature gradient; the slope of the pressure surfaces at the height of the core is at its maximum",
      "d. It lies in the cold air; the thermal wind reverses direction at the height of the core"
    ],
    "answer": "c. It lies at a height where there is no horizontal temperature gradient; the slope of the pressure surfaces at the height of the core is at its maximum"
  },
  {
    "question": "559. On a particular day part of a polar front jet stream runs from north to south in the northern hemisphere. This means that",
    "options": [
      "a. above the core of the jet the horizontal temperature gradient runs from north to south",
      "b. the polar air is on the eastern side and above the core of the jet",
      "c. below the core of the jet the horizontal temperature gradient runs from north to south",
      "d. the polar air is below and to the east of the core of the jet"
    ],
    "answer": "d. the polar air is below and to the east of the core of the jet"
  },
  {
    "question": "560. What name is given to the jet stream lying across India (A)?",
    "options": [
      "a. Polar front jet stream.",
      "b. Equatorial jet stream.",
      "c. Arctic jet stream.",
      "d. Sub-tropical jet stream."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Equatorial jet stream."
  },
  {
    "question": "561. At approximately what altitude is the subtropical jet stream found over Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 500",
      "b. FL 200",
      "c. FL300",
      "d. FL 400"
    ],
    "answer": "d. FL 400"
  },
  {
    "question": "562. What name is given to the jet stream lying over North Africa (B) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Polar front jet stream",
      "b. Equatorial jet stream",
      "c. Sub-tropical jet stream",
      "d. Arctic jet stream"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Sub-tropical jet stream"
  },
  {
    "question": "563. What is the average height of the arctic jet stream core?",
    "options": [
      "a. 30000 FT.",
      "b. 20000 FT .",
      "c. 40000 FT.",
      "d. 50000 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 20000 FT ."
  },
  {
    "question": "564. Which jet stream blows all year round, over the northern hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. The arctic jet stream.",
      "b. The polar night jet stream.",
      "c. The equatorial jet stream.",
      "d. The subtropical jet stream."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The subtropical jet stream."
  },
  {
    "question": "565. What is the average height of the jet core within a polar front jet stream?",
    "options": [
      "a. 50000 FT.",
      "b. 20000 FT.",
      "c. 40000 FT.",
      "d. 30000 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 30000 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "566. In the month of August you prepare a flight (cruising level FL 370) from Bombay (19\u00b0N - 73\u00b0E) to Bangkok (13\u00b0N - 100\u00b0E). What wind conditions can you expect?",
    "options": [
      "a. Light winds diagonal to the route.",
      "b. Headwinds.",
      "c. Tailwinds.",
      "d. Strong northerly winds."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Headwinds."
  },
  {
    "question": "567. What is the most significant difference between an equatorial jet stream and all the other jet streams ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Horizontal dimension.",
      "b. Vertical dimension.",
      "c. Wind direction.",
      "d. Windspeed."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Wind direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "568. Which of the following types of jet streams can be observed all year round?",
    "options": [
      "a. Equatorial jet stream / arctic jet stream.",
      "b. Equatorial jet stream / polar front jet stream.",
      "c. Arctic jet stream / subtropical jet stream.",
      "d. Subtropical jet stream / polar front jet stream."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Subtropical jet stream / polar front jet stream."
  },
  {
    "question": "569. During the winter months in mid-latitudes in the northern hemisphere, the polar front jetstream moves toward the",
    "options": [
      "a. south and speed decreases",
      "b. north and speed decreases",
      "c. south and speed increases",
      "d. north and speed increases"
    ],
    "answer": "c. south and speed increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "570. The equatorial easterly jet is a jetstream that occurs :",
    "options": [
      "a. only in the summer of the northern hemisphere at approx. 45 000 FT",
      "b. only in the winter of the northern hemisphere at approx. 30 000 FT",
      "c. during the whole year in the southern hemisphere",
      "d. during the whole year in the northern hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "a. only in the summer of the northern hemisphere at approx. 45 000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "571. Most strong air currents at higher levels (jet streams) have a westerly direction. There is, however, an important easterly jet stream. When and where is it likely to be encountered ?",
    "options": [
      "a. In winter along the Russian coast facing the Arctic ocean.",
      "b. In summer from south-east Asia extending over southern India to central Africa.",
      "c. In summer from the Middle East extending over the southern part of the Mediterranean to southern Spain.",
      "d. Throughout the year to the south of the Azorian high."
    ],
    "answer": "b. In summer from south-east Asia extending over southern India to central Africa."
  },
  {
    "question": "572. The jetstream and associated clear air turbulence can sometimes be visually identified in flight by",
    "options": [
      "a. a constant outside air temperature",
      "b. dust or haze at high level",
      "c. long streaks of cirrus clouds.",
      "d. a high-pressure centre at high level"
    ],
    "answer": "c. long streaks of cirrus clouds."
  },
  {
    "question": "573. In which zone of a jet stream is the strongest CAT to be expected ?",
    "options": [
      "a. About 12000 FT above the core.",
      "b. The warm air side of the core.",
      "c. Exactly in the center of the core.",
      "d. The cold air side of the core."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The cold air side of the core."
  },
  {
    "question": "574. Which area of a polar front jet stream in the northern hemisphere has the highest probability of turbulence?",
    "options": [
      "a. Looking downstream, the area to the left of the core.",
      "b. Looking downstream, the area to the right of the core.",
      "c. In the core of the jet stream.",
      "d. Above the core in the boundary between warm and cold air."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Looking downstream, the area to the left of the core."
  },
  {
    "question": "575. Under which of the following conditions is the most severe CAT likely to be experienced ?",
    "options": [
      "a. A jet stream, with great spacing between the isotherms",
      "b. A curved jet stream near a deep trough",
      "c. A westerly jet stream at low latitudes in the summer",
      "d. A straight jet stream near a low pressure area"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A curved jet stream near a deep trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "576. Which of the following conditions are most favourable to the formation of mountain waves ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moist unstable air at mountain top and wind of less than 5 knots blowing across the mountain ridge.",
      "b. Unstable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge.",
      "c. Either stable or unstable air at mountain top and a wind of at least 30 knots blowing parallel to the mountain ridge.",
      "d. Stable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Stable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge."
  },
  {
    "question": "577. At the top of orographic waves, in mountainous regions, the cloud most likely to be encountered is",
    "options": [
      "a. altocumulus lenticularis.",
      "b. cirrostratus.",
      "c. cirrus.",
      "d. cumulus mediocris."
    ],
    "answer": "a. altocumulus lenticularis."
  },
  {
    "question": "578. What of the following is the most important constituent in the atmosphere from a weather stand-point ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Nitrogen",
      "b. Water vapour",
      "c. Oxygen",
      "d. Hydrogen"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Water vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "579. Relative humidity relates to",
    "options": [
      "a. the amount of water vapor present in warm air compared to cold air.",
      "b. actual water vapor present to what could be present.",
      "c. the degree of saturation.",
      "d. both b and c."
    ],
    "answer": "d. both b and c."
  },
  {
    "question": "580. Unsaturated air moving downwards is heated at a certain rate of temperature change, called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Dry adiabatic.",
      "b. Chinook wind.",
      "c. Saturated adiabatic.",
      "d. Ambient lapse rate."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Dry adiabatic."
  },
  {
    "question": "581. Hazardous wind shear is encountered near the ground",
    "options": [
      "a. during periods when the wind velocity is stronger than 35 knots.",
      "b. during periods when the wind velocity is stronger than 35 knots and near mountain valleys.",
      "c. during periods of strong temperature inversion and near thunderstorms.",
      "d. near mountain valleys and on the windward side of hills or mountains."
    ],
    "answer": "c. during periods of strong temperature inversion and near thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "582. The inland climate is characterized by:",
    "options": [
      "a. a cold winter and a warm summer.",
      "b. a warm winter and a cold summer.",
      "c. a dry winter and a wet summer.",
      "d. a wet winter and a dry summer."
    ],
    "answer": "a. a cold winter and a warm summer."
  },
  {
    "question": "583. The formation of a thermal low pressure is by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Advection of warm air.",
      "b. Advection of cold air.",
      "c. A dynamic effect.",
      "d. A temperature rise in an area in relation to the environment."
    ],
    "answer": "d. A temperature rise in an area in relation to the environment."
  },
  {
    "question": "584. \"Instability\" low pressure means:",
    "options": [
      "a. A lee low.",
      "b. Orographic low pressure containing condensation heat.",
      "c. Cold low pressure.",
      "d. A low pressure receiving energy from released condensation heat."
    ],
    "answer": "d. A low pressure receiving energy from released condensation heat."
  },
  {
    "question": "585. Wind shear is experienced when:",
    "options": [
      "a. The wind has been forecasted to be light and variable.",
      "b. Neither wind direction nor force changes at altitude.",
      "c. There is a ground inversion and strong winds above the inversion layer.",
      "d. Gusts have been forecasted or reported."
    ],
    "answer": "c. There is a ground inversion and strong winds above the inversion layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "586. List the characteristics of a typical coastal climate:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm summer and cold winter",
      "b. Chilly summer and mild winter.",
      "c. Small amounts of precipitation.",
      "d. Stable weather."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Chilly summer and mild winter."
  },
  {
    "question": "587. Describe how a cold high pressure changes at altitude:",
    "options": [
      "a. Strengthens.",
      "b. No change.",
      "c. Weakens and may transfer into a low pressure.",
      "d. Impossible to predict."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Weakens and may transfer into a low pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "588. With decreasing temperature and unchanged dew point:",
    "options": [
      "a. The relative humidity will decrease.",
      "b. Water vapor will decrease.",
      "c. Water vapor will increase.",
      "d. The relative humidity will increase."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The relative humidity will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "589. As a parcel of air cools, its ability to hold water vapour:",
    "options": [
      "a. Decreases",
      "b. Increases",
      "c. Remains unaltered",
      "d. Depends, whether the parcel is rising or not"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "590. As a parcel of air warms, its ability to hold water vapour:",
    "options": [
      "a. Decreases",
      "b. Increases",
      "c. Remains unaltered",
      "d. Depends, whether the parcel is rising or not"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "591. Moist air is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Denser than dry air",
      "b. Warmer than dry air",
      "c. Less dense than dry air",
      "d. Colder than dry air"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Less dense than dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "592. Where is the usual location of a thermal low?",
    "options": [
      "a. Over the arctic region",
      "b. Over the eye of a hurricane",
      "c. Over the surface of a dry, sunny region"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Over the surface of a dry, sunny region"
  },
  {
    "question": "593. Which process causes adiabatic cooling?",
    "options": [
      "a. Expansion of air as it rises",
      "b. Movement of air over a colder surface",
      "c. Release of latent heat during the vaporization process"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Expansion of air as it rises"
  },
  {
    "question": "594. What does this picture depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe",
      "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe",
      "c. South foehn",
      "d. North foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe"
  },
  {
    "question": "595. Where do the westerly waves occur in this picture?",
    "options": [
      "a. In Central Europe",
      "b. Over the North Sea",
      "c. In the Mediterranean Sea",
      "d. Over the Baltics"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In Central Europe"
  },
  {
    "question": "596. Where do the westerly waves occur in this picture?",
    "options": [
      "a. In Central Europe",
      "b. Over Scandinavia",
      "c. In the Mediterranean Sea",
      "d. Over the Baltics"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Over Scandinavia"
  },
  {
    "question": "597. Which statement is true for the lifting of an air parcel?",
    "options": [
      "a. Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated",
      "b. Saturated parcels cool more rapidly than unsaturated",
      "c. An air parcel always cools at the dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "d. A stable air mass must be present"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated"
  },
  {
    "question": "598. Refer to the surface chart: Which weather situation can be expected during the day at Geneva airport?",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF LSGG 0716 05014KT 5000 OVC015 BECMG 0810 8000 BKN018 BECMG 1013 05015G30KT 9999 SCT025 =",
      "b. TAF LSGG 0716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN 010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT 030 BKN090=",
      "c. TAF LSGG 0716 26012KT 9999 SCT030 BKN080 TEMPO 1013 25020G35KT 3000 TSRA BKN 030CB BECMG 1316 VRB02KT 3000 BCFG SCT100 =",
      "d. TAF LSGG 0716 VRB03KT 6000 BR SCT020 BECMG0811 23005KT 9999 SCT025TCU PROB40 TEMPO 1216 34012G30KT 3000 TSRA BKN020 CB="
    ],
    "answer": "b. TAF LSGG 0716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN 010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT 030 BKN090="
  },
  {
    "question": "599. Refer to the surface chart: Which weather situation can be expected during the day at Zurich airport?",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF LSZH 1601 05020G35KT 8000 BKN015 TEMPO 1720 05018KT 0300 +SHSN VV002=",
      "b. TAF LSZH 1601 23012KT 6000 RA BKN012 OVC030 TEMPO 2023 22025G40KT 1600 +SNRA BKN003 OVC015 =",
      "c. TAF LSZH 1601 VRB02KT 8000 SCT280 BECMG 1618 00000KT 3500 MIFG BECMG 1820 1500 BCFG BECMG 2022 0100 FG VV001 =",
      "d. TAF LSZH 1601 32008KT 9999 SCT030TCU TEMPO 2201 32020G32KT 3000 TSRA BKN020CB ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. TAF LSZH 1601 VRB02KT 8000 SCT280 BECMG 1618 00000KT 3500 MIFG BECMG 1820 1500 BCFG BECMG 2022 0100 FG VV001 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "600. In which of the following METARs is the probability the biggest for the formation of fog the following night?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1850Z 21003KT 8000 SCT250 12/M08 Q1028 NOSIG =",
      "b. 1850Z 06018G30KT 5000 OVC010 04/01 Q1024 NOSIG =",
      "c. 1850Z 15003KT 6000 SCT120 05/04 Q1032 BECMG 1600 =",
      "d. 1850Z 25010KT 4000 RA BKN012 OBC030 12/10 Q1006 TEMPO 1500 ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1850Z 15003KT 6000 SCT120 05/04 Q1032 BECMG 1600 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "601. What does dewpoint mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature at which ice melts.",
      "b. The temperature to which a mass of air must be cooled in order to reach saturation.",
      "c. The freezing level (danger of icing).",
      "d. The temperature at which the relative humidity and saturation vapour pressure are the same."
    ],
    "answer": "b. The temperature to which a mass of air must be cooled in order to reach saturation."
  },
  {
    "question": "602. Which of the following is the definition of relative humidity ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ratio between the actual mixing ratio and the saturation mixing ratio X 100",
      "b. Ratio between air temperature and dewpoint temperature X 100",
      "c. Ratio between water vapour pressure and atmospheric pressure X 100",
      "d. Ratio between water vapour (g) and air (kg) X 100"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ratio between the actual mixing ratio and the saturation mixing ratio X 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "603. The relative humidity of a sample air mass is 50%. How is the relative humidity of this air mass influenced by changes of the amount of water vapour in it?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is not influenced by changing water vapour.",
      "b. It increases with increasing water vapour.",
      "c. It decreases with increasing water vapour.",
      "d. It is only influenced by temperature."
    ],
    "answer": "b. It increases with increasing water vapour."
  },
  {
    "question": "604. Relative humidity",
    "options": [
      "a. is not affected by temperature changes of the air.",
      "b. is not affected when air is ascending or descending.",
      "c. changes when water vapour is added, even though the temperature remains constant.",
      "d. does not change when water vapour is added provided the temperature of the air remains constant."
    ],
    "answer": "c. changes when water vapour is added, even though the temperature remains constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "605. How, if at all, is the relative humidity of an unsaturated airmass influenced by temperature changes?",
    "options": [
      "a. It increases with increasing temperature.",
      "b. It is not influenced by temperature changes.",
      "c. It decreases with increasing temperature.",
      "d. It is only influenced by the amount of water vapour."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It decreases with increasing temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "606. How does relative humidity and the dewpoint in an unsaturated airmass change with varying temperature?",
    "options": [
      "a. When temperature decreases, the relative humidity and the dewpoint remain constant.",
      "b. When temperature increases, the relative humidity increases, and the dewpoint decreases.",
      "c. When temperature decreases, the relative humidity decreases, and the dewpoint increases.",
      "d. When temperature increases, the relative humidity decreases, and the dewpoint remains constant."
    ],
    "answer": "d. When temperature increases, the relative humidity decreases, and the dewpoint remains constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "607. When a given mass of air descends, what effect will it have on relative humidity?",
    "options": [
      "a. It increases up to 100%, then remains stable.",
      "b. It increases.",
      "c. It remains constant.",
      "d. It decreases."
    ],
    "answer": "d. It decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "608. During the late afternoon an air temperature of +12\u00b0C and a dew point of +5\u00b0C were measured. What temperature change must occur during the night in order to induce saturation?",
    "options": [
      "a. It must decrease to +6\u00b0C.",
      "b. It must decrease by 5\u00b0C.",
      "c. It must decrease to +5\u00b0C.",
      "d. It must decrease to +7\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It must decrease to +5\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "609. Which of the following statements is true of the dew point of an air mass?",
    "options": [
      "a. It can be used to estimate the air mass's relative humidity even if the air temperature is unknown",
      "b. It can be higher than the temperature of the air mass",
      "c. It can be used together with the air pressure to estimate the air mass's relative humidity",
      "d. It can only be equal to, or lower, than the temperature of the air mass"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It can only be equal to, or lower, than the temperature of the air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "610. Relative humidity",
    "options": [
      "a. is higher in cool air than in warm air",
      "b. is higher in warm air than in cool air",
      "c. increases if the air is cooled whilst maintaining the vapour pressure constant",
      "d. decreases if the air is cooled whilst maintaining the vapour pressure constant"
    ],
    "answer": "c. increases if the air is cooled whilst maintaining the vapour pressure constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "611. The difference between temperature and dewpoint is greater in",
    "options": [
      "a. air with low temperature",
      "b. moist air",
      "c. air with high temperature",
      "d. dry air"
    ],
    "answer": "d. dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "612. The dewpoint temperature",
    "options": [
      "a. can not be equal to the air temperature",
      "b. is always lower than the air temperature",
      "c. is always higher than the air temperature",
      "d. can be equal to the air temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "d. can be equal to the air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "613. Relative humidity depends on",
    "options": [
      "a. temperature of the air only",
      "b. moisture content and pressure of the air",
      "c. moisture content of the air only",
      "d. moisture content and temperature of the air"
    ],
    "answer": "d. moisture content and temperature of the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "614. The dewpoint temperature",
    "options": [
      "a. can be reached by lowering the pressure whilst keeping temperature constant",
      "b. can be reached by cooling the air whilst keeping pressure constant",
      "c. can not be equal to the air temperature",
      "d. can not be lower than the air temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "b. can be reached by cooling the air whilst keeping pressure constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "615. The maximum amount of water vapour that the air can contain depends on the",
    "options": [
      "a. dewpoint",
      "b. relative humidity",
      "c. stability of the air",
      "d. air temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "d. air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "616. Dew point is defined as",
    "options": [
      "a. the temperature below which the change of state in a given volume of air will result in the absorption of latent heat",
      "b. the lowest temperature at which evaporation will occur for a given pressure",
      "c. the lowest temperature to which air must be cooled in order to reduce the relative humidity",
      "d. the temperature to which moist air must be cooled to become saturated at a given pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "d. the temperature to which moist air must be cooled to become saturated at a given pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "617. Relative humidity at a given temperature is the relation between",
    "options": [
      "a. dew point and air temperature",
      "b. water vapour weight and dry air weight",
      "c. water vapour weight and humid air volume",
      "d. actual water vapour content and saturated water vapour content"
    ],
    "answer": "d. actual water vapour content and saturated water vapour content"
  },
  {
    "question": "618. The difference between air temperature and dew point temperature is popularly called the \"spread\". As spread increases, relative humidity:",
    "options": [
      "a. increases.",
      "b. decreases.",
      "c. stays the same.",
      "d. first decreases and then increases."
    ],
    "answer": "b. decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "619. If the dew point stays the same, but the air temperature decreases, then:",
    "options": [
      "a. The relative humidity will decrease.",
      "b. Water vapor will decrease.",
      "c. Water vapor will increase.",
      "d. The relative humidity will increase."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The relative humidity will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "620. The amount of water vapor which air can hold largely depends on:",
    "options": [
      "a. Relative humidity.",
      "b. Air temperature.",
      "c. Stability of air.",
      "d. Dew point."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Air temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "621. The danger of experiencing fog is greatest when:",
    "options": [
      "a. dew point temperature is high.",
      "b. dew point temperature is low.",
      "c. there is little dispersion.",
      "d. there is great dispersion."
    ],
    "answer": "c. there is little dispersion."
  },
  {
    "question": "622. When temperature drops without changes of dew point temperature:",
    "options": [
      "a. The amount of water vapor will increase.",
      "b. Relative humidity will increase.",
      "c. The amount of water vapor will decrease.",
      "d. Relative humidity will decrease."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Relative humidity will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "623. Which conditions result in the formation of frost ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature of the collecting surface is at or below freezing and small droplets of moisture are falling.",
      "b. When dew forms and the temperature is below freezing.",
      "c. Temperature of the collecting surface is below the dew point of surrounding air and the dew point is colder than freezing.",
      "d. None of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Temperature of the collecting surface is below the dew point of surrounding air and the dew point is colder than freezing."
  },
  {
    "question": "624. A parcel of air is said to be saturated if it has a relative humidity of:",
    "options": [
      "a. 50 %",
      "b. 100 %",
      "c. Greater than 90 %",
      "d. Greater than 80 %"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 100 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "625. The temperature at which a parcel of air becomes saturated if it cools is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Dew point temperature",
      "b. Saturation temperature",
      "c. Condensation temperature",
      "d. Freezing temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Dew point temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "626. The maximum water in the air depends on the following:",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature",
      "b. Density",
      "c. Cloud type",
      "d. None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "627. What is relative humidity?",
    "options": [
      "a. The actual water vapour content in the air given in per cent",
      "b. The possible saturated water vapour content at a given temperature, given in per cent",
      "c. A term used to indicate the presence of water vapour, or moisture, in the air",
      "d. The ratio of the actual water vapour content in the air to the saturated water vapour content of the air at a given temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The ratio of the actual water vapour content in the air to the saturated water vapour content of the air at a given temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "628. Which of the following changes of state is known as sublimation?",
    "options": [
      "a. Solid direct to liquid",
      "b. Solid direct to vapour",
      "c. Liquid direct to solid",
      "d. Liquid direct to vapour"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Solid direct to vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "629. Clouds, fog or dew will always be formed when:",
    "options": [
      "a. relative humidity reaches 98%.",
      "b. water vapour is present.",
      "c. water vapour condenses.",
      "d. temperature and dew point are nearly equal."
    ],
    "answer": "c. water vapour condenses."
  },
  {
    "question": "630. In which of the following changes of state is latent heat released ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Liquid to gas",
      "b. Solid to liquid",
      "c. Solid to gas",
      "d. Gas to liquid"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Gas to liquid"
  },
  {
    "question": "631. How are high level condensation trails formed that are to be found occasionally behind jet aircraft ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Only through unburnt fuel in the exhaust gases",
      "b. Through a decrease in pressure, and the associated adiabatic drop in temperature at the wing tips while flying through relatively warm but humid air",
      "c. Through water vapour released during fuel combustion",
      "d. In conditions of low humidity, through the particles of soot contained in the exhaust gases"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Through water vapour released during fuel combustion"
  },
  {
    "question": "632. Supercooled droplets are always",
    "options": [
      "a. large and at a temperature below freezing",
      "b. small and at a temperature below freezing",
      "c. at a temperature below freezing",
      "d. at a temperature below -60\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. at a temperature below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "633. Supercooled droplets can be encountered",
    "options": [
      "a. only in winter at high altitude",
      "b. in winter only in high clouds",
      "c. only in winter above 10000 FT",
      "d. at any time of the year"
    ],
    "answer": "d. at any time of the year"
  },
  {
    "question": "634. When water evaporates into unsaturated air",
    "options": [
      "a. relative humidity is decreased",
      "b. heat is released",
      "c. relative humidity is not changed",
      "d. heat is absorbed"
    ],
    "answer": "d. heat is absorbed"
  },
  {
    "question": "635. A super-cooled droplet is",
    "options": [
      "a. a water droplet that is mainly frozen",
      "b. a droplet still in liquid state at a temperature below freezing",
      "c. a small particle of water at a temperature below -50\u00b0C",
      "d. a water droplet that has been frozen during its descent"
    ],
    "answer": "b. a droplet still in liquid state at a temperature below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "636. Supercooled droplets can occur in",
    "options": [
      "a. clouds but not in precipitation",
      "b. clouds, fog and precipitation",
      "c. precipitation but not in clouds",
      "d. clouds but not in fog"
    ],
    "answer": "b. clouds, fog and precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "637. A super-cooled droplet is one that",
    "options": [
      "a. is at an above freezing temperature in below freezing air",
      "b. has frozen to become an ice pellet",
      "c. has a shell of ice with water inside it",
      "d. remains liquid at a below freezing temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "d. remains liquid at a below freezing temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "638. The process by which water vapour is transformed directly into ice is known as",
    "options": [
      "a. supercooling",
      "b. sublimation",
      "c. supersaturation",
      "d. radiation cooling"
    ],
    "answer": "b. sublimation"
  },
  {
    "question": "639. Fog and cloud formation takes place by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Condensation.",
      "b. Evaporation.",
      "c. Sublimation.",
      "d. None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Condensation."
  },
  {
    "question": "640. What is meant by the expression \"Low level windshear\" ?",
    "options": [
      "a. A change of wind direction and force during a limited period of time within a small area.",
      "b. Turbulence containing whirling dust.",
      "c. The effect of friction.",
      "d. The wind when blowing across the isobars."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A change of wind direction and force during a limited period of time within a small area."
  },
  {
    "question": "641. When water vapor condenses into water droplets, there is a:",
    "options": [
      "a. Release of heat energy that increases density of the surrounding air.",
      "b. Sublimation.",
      "c. Release of heat energy that makes the surrounding air warmer.",
      "d. None of the above."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Release of heat energy that makes the surrounding air warmer."
  },
  {
    "question": "642. A VOLMET broadcast is:",
    "options": [
      "a. A recorded broadcast of the METAR for a specific airfield",
      "b. A special ATC broadcast, to all aircraft on frequency, of a significant change in weather conditions",
      "c. A recorded broadcast of METARs for about 10 airports"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A recorded broadcast of METARs for about 10 airports"
  },
  {
    "question": "643. What is the result when water vapor changes to the liquid state while being lifted in a thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Latent heat is released to the atmosphere",
      "b. Latent heat is transformed into pure energy",
      "c. Latent heat is absorbed from the surrounding air by the water droplet"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Latent heat is released to the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "644. What kind of weather conditions are most common in a stationary high pressure area?",
    "options": [
      "a. Calm winds and haze",
      "b. Thunderstorm and showers in the summer",
      "c. Light rain",
      "d. Gusty winds and clear skies"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Calm winds and haze"
  },
  {
    "question": "645. The stable layer at some height in the lower troposphere of an old high pressure area in the moderate latitudes is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Friction inversion",
      "b. Radiation inversion",
      "c. Trade wind",
      "d. Subsidence inversion"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Subsidence inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "646. What does this picture depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe",
      "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe",
      "c. South foehn",
      "d. North foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe"
  },
  {
    "question": "647. What is the dry adiabatic lapse rate per 1000 FT ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1.5\u00b0C",
      "b. 2.0\u00b0C",
      "c. 3.0\u00b0C.",
      "d. 3.5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 3.0\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "648. A parcel of unsaturated air is lifted to just below the condensation level and then returned to its original level. What is the final temperature of the parcel of air?",
    "options": [
      "a. Lower than the starting temperature.",
      "b. Higher than the starting temperature.",
      "c. The same as the starting temperature.",
      "d. It depends upon the QFE."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The same as the starting temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "649. A parcel of moist but not saturated air rises due to adiabatic effects. Which of the following changes ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Specific humidity",
      "b. Absolute humidity",
      "c. Mixing ratio",
      "d. Relative humidity"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Relative humidity"
  },
  {
    "question": "650. If a saturated air mass descends down a slope its temperature increases at",
    "options": [
      "a. the same rate as if the air mass were dry.",
      "b. a lower rate than in dry air, as evaporation absorbs heat.",
      "c. a lower rate than in dry air, as condensation gives out heat.",
      "d. a higher rate than in dry air, as it gives up latent evaporation heat."
    ],
    "answer": "b. a lower rate than in dry air, as evaporation absorbs heat."
  },
  {
    "question": "651. During an adiabatic process heat is",
    "options": [
      "a. neither added nor lost",
      "b. added",
      "c. lost",
      "d. added but the result is an overall loss"
    ],
    "answer": "a. neither added nor lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "652. The decrease in temperature, per 100 metres, in an unsaturated rising parcel of air is",
    "options": [
      "a. 0.65\u00b0C",
      "b. 2\u00b0C",
      "c. 1\u00b0C",
      "d. 0.5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "653. The decrease in temperature, per 100 metres, in a saturated rising parcel of air at lower level of the atmosphere is approximately",
    "options": [
      "a. 1.5\u00b0C",
      "b. 1\u00b0C",
      "c. 0.6\u00b0C",
      "d. 0.35\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 0.6\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "654. The rate of cooling of ascending saturated air is less than the rate of cooling of ascending unsaturated air because:",
    "options": [
      "a. water vapour absorbs the incoming heat from the sun",
      "b. moist air is heavier than dry air",
      "c. water vapour doesn't cool as rapidly as dry air",
      "d. heat is released during the condensation process"
    ],
    "answer": "d. heat is released during the condensation process"
  },
  {
    "question": "655. If the surface temperature is 15\u00b0C , then the temperature at 10000 FT in a current of ascending unsaturated air is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 5\u00b0C",
      "b. 0\u00b0C",
      "c. -15\u00b0C",
      "d. -5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -15\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "656. In a layer of air the decrease in temperature per 100 metres increase in height is more than 1\u00b0C. This layer can be described as being",
    "options": [
      "a. conditionally stable",
      "b. absolutely stable",
      "c. conditionally unstable",
      "d. absolutely unstable"
    ],
    "answer": "d. absolutely unstable"
  },
  {
    "question": "657. Which statement is true for a conditionally unstable layer?",
    "options": [
      "a. The wet adiabatic lapse rate is 0.65\u00b0C/100m",
      "b. The environmental lapse rate is less than 0.65\u00b0C/100m",
      "c. The layer is unstable for unsaturated air",
      "d. The environmental lapse rate is less than 1\u00b0C/100m"
    ],
    "answer": "d. The environmental lapse rate is less than 1\u00b0C/100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "658. The stability in a layer is increasing if",
    "options": [
      "a. warm air is advected in the lower part and cold air in the upper part",
      "b. warm air is advected in the upper part and cold air in the lower part",
      "c. warm and moist air is advected in the lower part",
      "d. cold and dry air is advected in the upper part"
    ],
    "answer": "b. warm air is advected in the upper part and cold air in the lower part"
  },
  {
    "question": "659. Which of the following statements concerning the lifting of a parcel of air is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Unsaturated parcels cool less rapidly than saturated parcels",
      "b. Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated parcels",
      "c. Unsaturated parcels cool at a rate of 0.65\u00b0C per 100m",
      "d. Saturated parcels always cool at a rate of 0.65\u00b0C per 100m"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated parcels"
  },
  {
    "question": "660. A moist but unsaturated parcel of air becomes saturated by",
    "options": [
      "a. lowering the parcel to a lower level",
      "b. lifting the parcel to a higher level",
      "c. moving the parcel to an area with lower pressure and equal temperature",
      "d. moving the parcel to an area with higher pressure and equal temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "b. lifting the parcel to a higher level"
  },
  {
    "question": "661. A sample of moist but unsaturated air may become saturated by",
    "options": [
      "a. expanding it adiabatically",
      "b. raising the temperature",
      "c. lowering the pressure, keeping temperature constant",
      "d. compressing it adiabatically"
    ],
    "answer": "a. expanding it adiabatically"
  },
  {
    "question": "662. The height of the lifting condensation level is determined by",
    "options": [
      "a. temperature and dewpoint at the surface",
      "b. temperature at surface and air pressure",
      "c. wind and dewpoint at the surface",
      "d. wet adiabatic lapse rate and dewpoint at the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "a. temperature and dewpoint at the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "663. A layer is absolutely unstable if the temperature decrease with height is",
    "options": [
      "a. between 1\u00b0C per 100m and 0.65\u00b0C per 100m",
      "b. more than 1\u00b0C per 100m",
      "c. 0.65\u00b0C per 100m",
      "d. less than 0.65\u00b0C per 100m"
    ],
    "answer": "b. more than 1\u00b0C per 100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "664. A layer in which the temperature remains constant with height is",
    "options": [
      "a. neutral",
      "b. unstable",
      "c. absolutely stable",
      "d. conditionally unstable"
    ],
    "answer": "c. absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "665. A layer in which the temperature increases with height is",
    "options": [
      "a. conditionally unstable",
      "b. absolutely unstable",
      "c. absolutely stable",
      "d. neutral"
    ],
    "answer": "c. absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "666. A layer in which the temperature decreases with 1\u00b0C per 100m is",
    "options": [
      "a. absolutely unstable",
      "b. absolutely stable",
      "c. neutral for dry air",
      "d. conditionally unstable"
    ],
    "answer": "c. neutral for dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "667. If in a 100 m thick layer the temperature at the bottom of the layer is 10\u00b0C and at the top of the layer is 8\u00b0C then this layer is",
    "options": [
      "a. absolutely unstable",
      "b. absolutely stable",
      "c. conditionally unstable",
      "d. neutral"
    ],
    "answer": "a. absolutely unstable"
  },
  {
    "question": "668. An inversion is",
    "options": [
      "a. an absolutely stable layer",
      "b. a conditionally unstable layer",
      "c. an unstable layer",
      "d. a layer that can be either stable or unstable"
    ],
    "answer": "a. an absolutely stable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "669. The rate at which descending unsaturated air is heated is about:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1.5\u00b0C per 100 m.",
      "b. 1.5\u00b0C per 1000 ft.",
      "c. 3\u00b0 C per 100 m.",
      "d. 3\u00b0C per 1000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 3\u00b0C per 1000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "670. Which term applies when the temperature of the air changes by compression or expansion with no heat added or removed?",
    "options": [
      "a. Katabatic",
      "b. Advection",
      "c. Adiabatic",
      "d. Atmospheric"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Adiabatic"
  },
  {
    "question": "671. What weather condition occurs at the altitude where the dewpoint lapse rate and the dry adiabatic lapse rate converge?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cloud bases form",
      "b. Precipitation starts",
      "c. Stable air changes to unstable air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cloud bases form"
  },
  {
    "question": "672. When saturated air moves downhill, its temperature increases",
    "options": [
      "a. at a faster rate than dry air because of the release of latent heat",
      "b. at a slower rate than dry air because vaporization uses heat",
      "c. at a slower rate than dry air because condensation releases heat"
    ],
    "answer": "b. at a slower rate than dry air because vaporization uses heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "673. What does this picture depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe",
      "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe",
      "c. Uniform pressure pattern",
      "d. North foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Uniform pressure pattern"
  },
  {
    "question": "674. What can be said about the altimeter indication during a period of 10 minutes, when a uniform pressure pattern prevails?",
    "options": [
      "a. There will be no visible change in the indication",
      "b. The indication decreases",
      "c. The indication increases",
      "d. The altimeter indicates lower when set to 1013,2 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. There will be no visible change in the indication"
  },
  {
    "question": "675. What can be said about this weather situation?",
    "options": [
      "a. Air mass thunderstorms may develop during summertime",
      "b. Strong gradient winds may occur over Central Europe",
      "c. Foehn conditions lead to severe weather south of the Alps",
      "d. No ground fog will be present in Paris and Zurich during the winter"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Air mass thunderstorms may develop during summertime"
  },
  {
    "question": "676. Which of the following is a cause of stratus forming over flat land?",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation during the night from the earth surface in moderate wind.",
      "b. Unstable air.",
      "c. Convection during the day.",
      "d. The release of latent heat."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Radiation during the night from the earth surface in moderate wind."
  },
  {
    "question": "677. Which of the following processes within a layer of air may lead to the building of CU and CB clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Frontal lifting within stable layers.",
      "b. Radiation.",
      "c. Subsidence.",
      "d. Convection."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Convection."
  },
  {
    "question": "678. What process in an air mass leads to the creation of wide spread NS, AS and ST cloud coverage?",
    "options": [
      "a. Convection process",
      "b. Sinking",
      "c. Lifting",
      "d. Radiation"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Lifting"
  },
  {
    "question": "679. Rising air cools because",
    "options": [
      "a. it becomes more moist",
      "b. surrounding air is cooler at higher levels",
      "c. it expands",
      "d. it contracts"
    ],
    "answer": "c. it expands"
  },
  {
    "question": "680. Convective clouds are formed",
    "options": [
      "a. in stable atmosphere",
      "b. in unstable atmosphere",
      "c. in summer during the day only",
      "d. in mid-latitudes only"
    ],
    "answer": "b. in unstable atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "681. In an unstable layer there are cumuliform clouds. The vertical extent of these clouds depends on the",
    "options": [
      "a. air pressure at the surface",
      "b. wind direction",
      "c. thickness of the unstable layer",
      "d. pressure at different levels"
    ],
    "answer": "c. thickness of the unstable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "682. The formation of a cumulonimbus (CB) depends on:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm and humid air.",
      "b. Instability of thick layers of air.",
      "c. Some sort of lifting of the air.",
      "d. all answers are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. all answers are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "683. Formation of an orographic cloud takes place when sufficient wind forces the air over obstacles like a mountain, and further:",
    "options": [
      "a. with sufficient height of the mountain the air temperature reaches the dew point thus creating a cloud.",
      "b. it is true that the necessary amount of lifting of the air depends on the air humidity.",
      "c. the air is supercooled and unstable.",
      "d. a) and b) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. a) and b) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "684. Given a surface temperature of +10\u00b0C, and a dew point of +5\u00b0C, at what height might you expect cumulus clouds to form?",
    "options": [
      "a. 2000ft",
      "b. 4000ft",
      "c. 1000ft",
      "d. 3000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 2000ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "685. If a stable air mass is forced to rise, what type of cloud is most likely:",
    "options": [
      "a. CU",
      "b. NS",
      "c. TCU",
      "d. CB"
    ],
    "answer": "b. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "686. What determines the structure or type of clouds which will form as a result of air being forced to ascend?",
    "options": [
      "a. The stability of the air before lifting occurs",
      "b. The method by which air is lifted",
      "c. The relative humidity of the air after lifting occurs"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The stability of the air before lifting occurs"
  },
  {
    "question": "687. Which process in an air mass lead to NS-AS-ST clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Lifting",
      "b. Sublimation",
      "c. Evaporation",
      "d. The presence of a high pressure area"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Lifting"
  },
  {
    "question": "688. Which of the following types of clouds are evidence of unstable air conditions?",
    "options": [
      "a. ST, CS.",
      "b. CU, CB.",
      "c. SC, NS.",
      "d. CI, SC."
    ],
    "answer": "b. CU, CB."
  },
  {
    "question": "689. Which of the following clouds are classified as medium level clouds in temperate regions ?",
    "options": [
      "a. CI, CC.",
      "b. SC, NS",
      "c. AS, AC.",
      "d. CS, ST."
    ],
    "answer": "c. AS, AC."
  },
  {
    "question": "690. Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of altocumulus castellanus?",
    "options": [
      "a. b)",
      "b. d)",
      "c. a)",
      "d. c)"
    ],
    "answer": "c. a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "691. What is the main composition of clouds classified as \"high level clouds\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. Supercooled water droplets.",
      "b. Ice crystals.",
      "c. Water droplets.",
      "d. Water vapour."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Ice crystals."
  },
  {
    "question": "692. A plain in Western Europe with an average elevation of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform AC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1500 - 7000 FT above the terrain.",
      "b. 100 - 1500 FT above the terrain.",
      "c. 7000 - 15000 FT above the terrain.",
      "d. 15000 - 25000 FT above the terrain."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 7000 - 15000 FT above the terrain."
  },
  {
    "question": "693. Which of the following clouds may extend into more than one layer?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratus.",
      "b. Nimbostratus.",
      "c. Altocumulus.",
      "d. Cirrus."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Nimbostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "694. Which of the following cloud is classified as low level cloud ?",
    "options": [
      "a. ST",
      "b. CS",
      "c. AS",
      "d. CC"
    ],
    "answer": "a. ST"
  },
  {
    "question": "695. Which types of clouds are typical evidence of stable air conditions?",
    "options": [
      "a. ST, AS",
      "b. CU, CB",
      "c. NS, CU",
      "d. CB, CC"
    ],
    "answer": "a. ST, AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "696. Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of altocumulus lenticularis?",
    "options": [
      "a. b",
      "b. a",
      "c. d",
      "d. c"
    ],
    "answer": "a. b"
  },
  {
    "question": "697. Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of a cumulonimbus capillatus?",
    "options": [
      "a. d)",
      "b. a)",
      "c. b)",
      "d. c)"
    ],
    "answer": "a. d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "698. Which of the following types of cloud can extend over the low, medium and high cloud levels ?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. AC",
      "c. ST",
      "d. CI"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "699. A plain in Western Europe with an average height of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform SC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 7000 - 15000 FT above ground",
      "b. 100 - 1500 FT above ground",
      "c. 1500 - 7000 FT above ground",
      "d. 15000 - 25000 FT above ground"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1500 - 7000 FT above ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "700. A plain in Western Europe with an average height of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform CC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. 15000 - 35000 FT above the terrain",
      "b. 7000 - 15000 FT above the terrain",
      "c. 1500 - 7000 FT above the terrain",
      "d. 100 - 1500 FT above the terrain"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 15000 - 35000 FT above the terrain"
  },
  {
    "question": "701. Which of the following cloud types is found at high levels?",
    "options": [
      "a. SC",
      "b. CI",
      "c. AS",
      "d. CU"
    ],
    "answer": "b. CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "702. Which of the following cloud types is a medium level cloud ?",
    "options": [
      "a. ST",
      "b. CS",
      "c. AS",
      "d. SC"
    ],
    "answer": "c. AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "703. The presence of altocumulus lenticularis is an indication of the",
    "options": [
      "a. presence of valley winds",
      "b. risk of orographic thunderstorms",
      "c. development of thermal lows",
      "d. presence of mountain waves"
    ],
    "answer": "d. presence of mountain waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "704. Altostratus clouds are classified as",
    "options": [
      "a. convective clouds",
      "b. low level clouds",
      "c. high level clouds",
      "d. medium level clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "d. medium level clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "705. A cumulonimbus cloud at moderate latitudes in summer contains",
    "options": [
      "a. only water droplets",
      "b. a combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets",
      "c. only ice crystals",
      "d. a combination of ice crystals and water droplets"
    ],
    "answer": "b. a combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "706. Strongly developed cumulus clouds are an indication of",
    "options": [
      "a. the presence of a low level inversion",
      "b. instability in the atmosphere",
      "c. the presence of warm air aloft",
      "d. poor surface visibility"
    ],
    "answer": "b. instability in the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "707. Clouds, classified as being low level are considered to have bases from",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 to 1000 FT",
      "b. 1000 to 2000 FT",
      "c. the surface to 6500 FT",
      "d. 100 to 200 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. the surface to 6500 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "708. Which of the following are medium level clouds ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Altostratus and altocumulus",
      "b. Cirrocumulus and cirrostratus",
      "c. Cumulonimbus",
      "d. All convective clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Altostratus and altocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "709. What type of cloud is being described ? A generally grey cloud layer with fairly uniform base and uniform appearance, which may give drizzle or snow grains. When the sun is visible through the cloud, the outline is clearly discernible. Sometimes it appears in the form of ragged patches.",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratus",
      "b. Altostratus",
      "c. Nimbostratus",
      "d. Cirrostratus"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Stratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "710. The presence of altocumulus castellanus indicates",
    "options": [
      "a. stability in the higher troposphere",
      "b. strong convection at low height",
      "c. instability in the middle troposphere",
      "d. subsidence in a large part of the troposphere"
    ],
    "answer": "c. instability in the middle troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "711. Fallstreaks or virga are",
    "options": [
      "a. water or ice particles falling out of a cloud that evaporate before reaching the ground",
      "b. strong downdraughts in the polar jet stream, associated with jet streaks",
      "c. gusts associated with a well developed Bora",
      "d. strong katabatic winds in mountainous areas and accompanied by heavy precipitation"
    ],
    "answer": "a. water or ice particles falling out of a cloud that evaporate before reaching the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "712. The family of medium clouds include altostratus, altocumulus and nimbostratus. In moderate latitudes their height of base ranges from:",
    "options": [
      "a. 3000 to 5000 feet.",
      "b. 2000 to 10000 feet.",
      "c. 2000 to 12000 feet.",
      "d. 6500 to 23000 feet."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 6500 to 23000 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "713. High clouds are normally composed of",
    "options": [
      "a. Hail.",
      "b. Water droplets.",
      "c. Condensation nuclei.",
      "d. Ice crystals."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Ice crystals."
  },
  {
    "question": "714. State the four families of clouds:",
    "options": [
      "a. High, medium and low clouds",
      "b. High and medium clouds, and clouds with extensive vertical development.",
      "c. Heapclouds, stratified clouds, layered clouds and nimbo clouds.",
      "d. High, medium and low clouds, and clouds with extensive vertical development."
    ],
    "answer": "d. High, medium and low clouds, and clouds with extensive vertical development."
  },
  {
    "question": "715. The type of cloud formed when warm, light air rises rapidly into cooler air is a:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratus-type.",
      "b. Cumulus-type.",
      "c. Strato-cumulus type.",
      "d. Nimbo-status type"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cumulus-type."
  },
  {
    "question": "716. What wil be the classification of high level clouds and where will the base be?",
    "options": [
      "a. above 14000ft, Nimbus",
      "b. above 16500ft, Cumuliform",
      "c. above 16500ft, Cirriform",
      "d. above 7000 ft, Cumuliform"
    ],
    "answer": "c. above 16500ft, Cirriform"
  },
  {
    "question": "717. Which of the following types of cloud is most likely to be associated with prolonged and continuous moderate rain?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. CU",
      "c. ST",
      "d. CI"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "718. The presence of standing lenticular AC clouds is a good indication of:",
    "options": [
      "a. Updrafts and downdrafts",
      "b. An approaching thunderstorm",
      "c. An unstable air mass",
      "d. A stable air mass"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Updrafts and downdrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "719. Which clouds, normally found in the medium level, can extend to the other levels?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. AS",
      "c. CU",
      "d. ST"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "720. Which cloud represent an altocumulus lenticularis?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "b. B"
  },
  {
    "question": "721. Which cloud represent an altocumulus castellanus?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A"
  },
  {
    "question": "722. What does a CB contain at moderate latitudes in summer?",
    "options": [
      "a. A combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets",
      "b. A combination of ice crystals and water droplets",
      "c. Ice crystals, snow, and water droplets",
      "d. Ice crystals only"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "723. Which of the following are medium level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "options": [
      "a. AS, AC",
      "b. ST, CU",
      "c. CI, ST",
      "d. NS, CI"
    ],
    "answer": "a. AS, AC"
  },
  {
    "question": "724. Which of the following are low level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "options": [
      "a. AS, AC",
      "b. ST, NS",
      "c. CI, ST",
      "d. NS, CI"
    ],
    "answer": "b. ST, NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "725. Which of the following are high level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "options": [
      "a. AS, AC",
      "b. ST, NS",
      "c. CI, CC",
      "d. NS, CI"
    ],
    "answer": "c. CI, CC"
  },
  {
    "question": "726. Which cloud, normally found in the medium level, may extend to the low and high levels?",
    "options": [
      "a. AC",
      "b. NS",
      "c. CI",
      "d. CU"
    ],
    "answer": "b. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "727. Which cloud type may extend from low to high level (vertical development)?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. NS",
      "c. CI",
      "d. AC"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "728. Which of the four radio soundings corresponds with a low stratus layer?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "b. B"
  },
  {
    "question": "729. Which of the four radio soundings corresponds with \"OVC015\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A"
  },
  {
    "question": "730. What can be said about the formation of Haze?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dust particles are trapped below an inversion",
      "b. The air is very cold and thus the relative humidity increases",
      "c. A strong lifting action in the atmosphere is necessary",
      "d. A frontal system is the cause"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Dust particles are trapped below an inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "731. What are the characteristics of cumuliform clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Large water droplets, stability, no turbulence, showers and mainly rime ice.",
      "b. Small water droplets, stability, no turbulence and extensive areas of rain.",
      "c. Large water droplets, instability, turbulence, showers and mainly clear ice.",
      "d. Small water droplets, instability, turbulence, extensive areas of rain and rime ice."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Large water droplets, instability, turbulence, showers and mainly clear ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "732. In which of the following conditions is moderate to severe airframe icing most likely to be encountered?",
    "options": [
      "a. Within cloud of any type",
      "b. Below the freezing level in clear air",
      "c. In clear air above the freezing level",
      "d. In Nimbostratus cloud"
    ],
    "answer": "d. In Nimbostratus cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "733. What flying conditions may be encountered when flying in cirrus clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Average horizontal visibility more than 1000 m; light to moderate rime ice.",
      "b. Average horizontal visibility less than 500 m; nil icing.",
      "c. Average horizontal visibility less than 500 m; light to moderate icing.",
      "d. Average horizontal visibility more than 1000 m; nil icing."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Average horizontal visibility more than 1000 m; nil icing."
  },
  {
    "question": "734. Cumulus clouds are an indication for",
    "options": [
      "a. stability",
      "b. up and downdrafts",
      "c. the approach of a cold front",
      "d. the approach of a warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "b. up and downdrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "735. Fair weather cumulus clouds often indicate:",
    "options": [
      "a. Turbulence at and below the cloud level.",
      "b. Smooth flying conditions.",
      "c. Rain and strong winds.",
      "d. Fog."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Turbulence at and below the cloud level."
  },
  {
    "question": "736. Flying conditions associated with cumulonimbus (cb) at summertime are:",
    "options": [
      "a. Hazy weather combined with drizzle and turbulence.",
      "b. Good visibility, intervals of fine weather and little turbulence.",
      "c. Bad visibility, continuous rain and little turbulence.",
      "d. Bad visibility in showers and pronounced turbulence."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Bad visibility in showers and pronounced turbulence."
  },
  {
    "question": "737. What do you expect with fair weather Cumulus clouds?",
    "options": [
      "a. Turbulence at and below the cloud level",
      "b. Smooth flight below the cloud level",
      "c. Continuous rain",
      "d. Turbulence in and above the clouds up to approximately FL 250"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Turbulence at and below the cloud level"
  },
  {
    "question": "738. At what time of day, or night, is radiation fog most likely to occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. At sunset.",
      "b. Shortly after sunrise.",
      "c. Late evening.",
      "d. Shortly after midnight."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Shortly after sunrise."
  },
  {
    "question": "739. What is the average vertical extent of radiation fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. 2 000 FT.",
      "b. 500 FT.",
      "c. 5 000 FT.",
      "d. 10 000 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 500 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "740. What wind conditions, occuring just before dawn, favour the formation of fog at an airport where the temperature is 15\u00b0C and the dew point is 14\u00b0C?",
    "options": [
      "a. Westerly, 10 kt variable.",
      "b. Northerly, 10 kt.",
      "c. Calm.",
      "d. Easterly, 10 kt."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Calm."
  },
  {
    "question": "741. Which of the following weather conditions favour the formation of radiation fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. Light wind, little or no cloud, moist air.",
      "b. Light wind, extensive cloud, dry air.",
      "c. Light wind, extensive cloud, moist air.",
      "d. Strong wind, little or no cloud, moist air."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Light wind, little or no cloud, moist air."
  },
  {
    "question": "742. Which of the following is most likely to lead to the dissipation of radiation fog ?",
    "options": [
      "a. A build up of a high pressure area resulting in adiabatic warming associated with a sinking air mass",
      "b. A marked decrease in wind velocity close to the ground",
      "c. Ground cooling caused by radiation during the night",
      "d. A marked increase in wind velocity near the ground"
    ],
    "answer": "d. A marked increase in wind velocity near the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "743. The most likely reason for radiation fog to dissipate or become low stratus is :",
    "options": [
      "a. increasing surface wind speed.",
      "b. an increasingly stable atmosphere.",
      "c. surface cooling.",
      "d. a low level temperature inversion."
    ],
    "answer": "a. increasing surface wind speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "744. What are the differences between radiation fog and advection fog ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation fog forms due to surface cooling at night in a light wind. Advection fog forms when warm humid air flows over a cold surface.",
      "b. Radiation fog forms only on the ground, advection fog only on the sea.",
      "c. Radiation fog forms due to night cooling and advection fog due to daytime cooling.",
      "d. Radiation fog is formed by surface cooling in a calm wind. Advection fog is formed by evaporation over the sea."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Radiation fog forms due to surface cooling at night in a light wind. Advection fog forms when warm humid air flows over a cold surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "745. What type of fog is most likely to form over flat land during a clear night, with calm or light wind conditions ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation.",
      "b. Advection.",
      "c. Steam.",
      "d. Orographic."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Radiation."
  },
  {
    "question": "746. Under which of these conditions is radiation fog most likely to form?",
    "options": [
      "a. Very dry air",
      "b. Little or no cloud",
      "c. Strong surface winds",
      "d. Very low temperatures"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Little or no cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "747. Which of the following is most likely to lead to the formation of radiation fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dry, warm air passing over warm ground",
      "b. Heat loss from the ground on clear nights",
      "c. The passage of fronts",
      "d. Cold air passing over warm ground"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Heat loss from the ground on clear nights"
  },
  {
    "question": "748. Freezing fog consists of",
    "options": [
      "a. frozen water droplets",
      "b. supercooled water droplets",
      "c. frozen minute snow flakes",
      "d. ice crystals"
    ],
    "answer": "b. supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "749. When the temperature and dew point are less than one degree apart the weather conditions are most likely to be",
    "options": [
      "a. unlimited visibility",
      "b. clear and cool",
      "c. high scattered clouds",
      "d. fog or low cloud"
    ],
    "answer": "d. fog or low cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "750. The morning following a clear, calm night when the temperature has dropped to the dewpoint, is likely to produce",
    "options": [
      "a. a cold front",
      "b. radiation fog",
      "c. advection fog",
      "d. good clear weather"
    ],
    "answer": "b. radiation fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "751. Which of the following circumstances most favour the development of radiation fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm moist air at the windward side of a mountain",
      "b. Moist air over land during clear night with little wind",
      "c. Maritime tropical air flowing over cold sea",
      "d. Advection of very cold air over much warmer sea"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Moist air over land during clear night with little wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "752. The range of wind speed in which radiation fog is most likely to form is :",
    "options": [
      "a. above 15 kt",
      "b. between 10 and 15 kt",
      "c. between 5 and 10 kt",
      "d. below 5 kt"
    ],
    "answer": "d. below 5 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "753. Which type of fog do you expect over flat landscape on a clear night, under no wind conditions?",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation fog",
      "b. Advection fog",
      "c. Orographic fog",
      "d. Steam fog"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Radiation fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "754. Which of the following conditions is most likely to lead to the formation of advection fog ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moist cold air moving over a warm surface",
      "b. Moist warm air moving over a cold surface",
      "c. Dry warm air moving over a cold surface",
      "d. Dry cold air moving over a warm surface"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Moist warm air moving over a cold surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "755. Which type of fog is likely to form when air having temperature of 15\u00b0C and dew point of 12\u00b0C blows at 10 knots over a sea surface having temperatures of 5\u00b0C ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Radiation fog",
      "b. Advection fog",
      "c. Steam fog",
      "d. Frontal fog"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "756. Advection fog can be formed when",
    "options": [
      "a. cold moist air flows over warmer water",
      "b. cold moist air flows over a warmer surface",
      "c. warm moist air flows over a warmer surface",
      "d. warm moist air flows over a colder surface"
    ],
    "answer": "d. warm moist air flows over a colder surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "757. Which of the following statements is true concerning advection fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. It forms slowly and disappears rapidly",
      "b. It forms at night or the early morning",
      "c. It forms when unstable air is cooled adiabatically",
      "d. It can be formed suddenly by day or night"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It can be formed suddenly by day or night"
  },
  {
    "question": "758. Fog forming over the sea in a 20KT wind is most likely to be:",
    "options": [
      "a. Advection fog",
      "b. Radiation fog",
      "c. Neither, fog cannot form above 12KT wind speed"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "759. Name the difference between radiation and advection fog:",
    "options": [
      "a. Vertical movement (radiation fog) versus horizontal movement (advection fog)",
      "b. Advection fog occurs under no wind conditions in a clear night, while radiation fog forms over the sea in a 20 KT wind",
      "c. Flat landscape, a clear night, winds of 10-20KT, for the formation of radiation fog, and mountainous terrain and no wind conditions for advection fog",
      "d. Orographic lifting for radiation fog, and horizontal movement with a 20 KT wind for advection fog"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Vertical movement (radiation fog) versus horizontal movement (advection fog)"
  },
  {
    "question": "760. Which of the following conditions is most likely to lead to the formation of steam fog (arctic smoke)?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm air moving over cold water",
      "b. Cold air moving over warm water",
      "c. The sea is warmed by strong radiation from the sun",
      "d. The coastal region of the sea cools at night"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cold air moving over warm water"
  },
  {
    "question": "761. Steaming fog (arctic sea smoke) occurs in air",
    "options": [
      "a. that is stable",
      "b. with warm mass properties",
      "c. that is absolutely stable",
      "d. with cold mass properties"
    ],
    "answer": "d. with cold mass properties"
  },
  {
    "question": "762. When does frontal fog, also known as mixing fog, occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. When very humid warm air meets with dry cold air.",
      "b. When very humid warm air meets with very humid cold air.",
      "c. When very humid cold air meets with dry warm air.",
      "d. When very dry cold air meets with very dry warm air."
    ],
    "answer": "b. When very humid warm air meets with very humid cold air."
  },
  {
    "question": "763. Frontal fog is most likely to occur",
    "options": [
      "a. in winter in the early morning",
      "b. in rear of a warm front",
      "c. in summer in the early morning",
      "d. in advance of a warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "d. in advance of a warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "764. What conditions are most likely to lead to the formation of hill fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. Humid stable air mass, wind blowing towards the hills.",
      "b. High relative humidity and an unstable air mass",
      "c. Clear skies, calm or light winds, with relatively low humidity",
      "d. Precipitation which is lifted by the action of moderate winds striking the range"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Humid stable air mass, wind blowing towards the hills."
  },
  {
    "question": "765. Which form of precipitation from clouds containing only water is most likely to fall in mid-latitudes?",
    "options": [
      "a. Hail.",
      "b. Moderate rain with large drops.",
      "c. Heavy rain with large drops.",
      "d. Drizzle."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Drizzle."
  },
  {
    "question": "766. How does freezing rain develop?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rain falls on cold ground and then freezes",
      "b. Rain falls through a layer where temperatures are below 0\u00b0C",
      "c. Through melting of sleet grains",
      "d. Through melting of ice crystals"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Rain falls through a layer where temperatures are below 0\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "767. What enhances the growth rate of precipitation ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Advective action.",
      "b. Upward currents.",
      "c. Cyclonic movement.",
      "d. Temperature inversions."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Upward currents."
  },
  {
    "question": "768. When a rain shower approaches and passes an airfield, the following will happen:",
    "options": [
      "a. The temperature drops and dew point rises.",
      "b. The temperature remains unchanged and dew point drops.",
      "c. The temperature rises and dew point remains unchanged.",
      "d. The temperature rises and dew point drops.."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The temperature drops and dew point rises."
  },
  {
    "question": "769. Which of the following are favourable conditions for the formation of freezing rain?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm air aloft from which rain is falling into air with a temperature below 0\u00b0C.",
      "b. Water droplets falling from cold air aloft with a temperature below 0\u00b0C.",
      "c. Cold air aloft from which hail is falling into air that is warm.",
      "d. An isothermal layer aloft with a temperature just above 0\u00b0C through which rain is falling."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Warm air aloft from which rain is falling into air with a temperature below 0\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "770. Which one of the following types of cloud is most likely to produce heavy precipitation ?",
    "options": [
      "a. SC.",
      "b. CS.",
      "c. NS.",
      "d. ST."
    ],
    "answer": "c. NS."
  },
  {
    "question": "771. With what type of clouds are showers most likely associated?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratocumulus.",
      "b. Cumulonimbus.",
      "c. Nimbostratus.",
      "d. Stratus."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "772. What type of cloud can produce hail showers?",
    "options": [
      "a. CS",
      "b. NS",
      "c. CB",
      "d. AC"
    ],
    "answer": "c. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "773. The presence of ice pellets at the surface is evidence that",
    "options": [
      "a. freezing rain occurs at a higher altitude",
      "b. a cold front has passed",
      "c. there are thunderstorms in the area",
      "d. a warm front has passed"
    ],
    "answer": "a. freezing rain occurs at a higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "774. With which of the following types of cloud is \"+RA\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. AC",
      "c. SC",
      "d. ST"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "775. With what type of cloud is \"GR\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "options": [
      "a. CC",
      "b. AS",
      "c. ST",
      "d. CB"
    ],
    "answer": "d. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "776. With what type of cloud is \"DZ\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. ST",
      "c. CC",
      "d. CU"
    ],
    "answer": "b. ST"
  },
  {
    "question": "777. Which of the following cloud types is least likely to produce precipitation ?",
    "options": [
      "a. CI",
      "b. AS",
      "c. CB",
      "d. NS"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "778. With what type of cloud is heavy precipitation unlikely during the summer months ?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS, CC",
      "b. CB, ST",
      "c. SC, AS",
      "d. AS, NS"
    ],
    "answer": "c. SC, AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "779. With what type of cloud is \"+TSRA\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. AS",
      "c. SC",
      "d. NS"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "780. Freezing precipitation occurs",
    "options": [
      "a. only in the precipitation of a warm front",
      "b. only in the precipitation of a cold front",
      "c. mainly in the form of freezing rain or freezing drizzle",
      "d. mainly in the form of freezing hail or freezing snow"
    ],
    "answer": "c. mainly in the form of freezing rain or freezing drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "781. Precipitation in the form of showers occurs mainly from",
    "options": [
      "a. clouds containing only ice crystals",
      "b. stratified clouds",
      "c. cirro-type clouds",
      "d. convective clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "d. convective clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "782. Steady precipitation, in contrast to showery precipitation falls from",
    "options": [
      "a. stratiform clouds with severe turbulence",
      "b. convective clouds with little or no turbulence",
      "c. stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence",
      "d. convective clouds with moderate turbulence"
    ],
    "answer": "c. stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "783. Large hail stones",
    "options": [
      "a. only occur in thunderstorms of mid-latitudes",
      "b. are typically associated with severe thunderstorms",
      "c. are entirely composed of clear ice",
      "d. only occur in frontal thunderstorms"
    ],
    "answer": "b. are typically associated with severe thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "784. Freezing rain occurs when",
    "options": [
      "a. snow falls into an above-freezing layer of air",
      "b. ice pellets melt",
      "c. water vapour first turns into water droplets",
      "d. rain falls into a layer of air with temperatures below 0\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. rain falls into a layer of air with temperatures below 0\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "785. The following statements deal with precipitation, turbulence and icing. Select the list containing the most likely alternatives for NS cloud:",
    "options": [
      "a. Precipitation may be snow, sleet or rain. Icing is probable and may range between light and severe. Turbulence is rarely more than moderate.",
      "b. Precipitation may be snow, sleet or rain. Icing and turbulence are frequently severe.",
      "c. Precipitation is frequently in the form of hail. Icing and turbulence are frequently severe.",
      "d. Precipitation and icing are usually nil. Turbulence is rarely more than moderate."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Precipitation may be snow, sleet or rain. Icing is probable and may range between light and severe. Turbulence is rarely more than moderate."
  },
  {
    "question": "786. From what type of cloud does drizzle fall ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratus.",
      "b. Altostratus",
      "c. Cumulus",
      "d. Cirrostratus."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Stratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "787. What type of clouds are associated with rain showers ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Nimbostratus.",
      "b. Towering cumulus and altostratus.",
      "c. Altostratus and stratus.",
      "d. Towering cumulus and cumulonimbus."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Towering cumulus and cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "788. What type of clouds are associated with snow showers ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Nimbostratus",
      "b. Cumulus and altostratus",
      "c. Altostratus and stratus",
      "d. Cumulus and cumulonimbus"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Cumulus and cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "789. Steady precipitation, in contrast to showers, preceeding a front is an indication of:",
    "options": [
      "a. cumuliform clouds with moderate turbulence.",
      "b. stratiform clouds with moderate turbulence.",
      "c. cumuliform clouds with little or no turbulence.",
      "d. stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence."
    ],
    "answer": "d. stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence."
  },
  {
    "question": "790. Regarding stratus (st) and nimbostratus (ns):",
    "options": [
      "a. Neither does cause precipitation.",
      "b. St does cause drizzle and ns rain showers.",
      "c. St does cause rain showers and ns drizzle.",
      "d. St does cause drizzle and ns rain."
    ],
    "answer": "d. St does cause drizzle and ns rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "791. What type of cloud is pertinent for showers?",
    "options": [
      "a. CB",
      "b. NS",
      "c. CI",
      "d. AS"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "792. An airmass is unstable when",
    "options": [
      "a. temperature increases with height",
      "b. temperature and humidity are not constant",
      "c. pressure shows a marked variation over a given horizontal area",
      "d. an ascending parcel of air continues to rise to a considerable height."
    ],
    "answer": "d. an ascending parcel of air continues to rise to a considerable height."
  },
  {
    "question": "793. An airmass is stable when",
    "options": [
      "a. pressure is constant",
      "b. temperature in a given area drops off very rapidly with height",
      "c. the vertical motion of a rising parcel of air tends to become weaker and disappears.",
      "d. the lapse rate is 1\u00b0C per 100 m"
    ],
    "answer": "c. the vertical motion of a rising parcel of air tends to become weaker and disappears."
  },
  {
    "question": "794. An air mass is a body of air that",
    "options": [
      "a. has similar cloud formations associated with it.",
      "b. creates a wind shift as it moves across the Earth's surface.",
      "c. covers an extensive area and has fairly uniform properties of temperature and moisture.",
      "d. has extensive turbulence associated with it."
    ],
    "answer": "c. covers an extensive area and has fairly uniform properties of temperature and moisture."
  },
  {
    "question": "795. What are the typical differences between the temperature and humidity between an air mass with its origin in the Azores and an air mass with its origin over northern Russia ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The air of the Azores is warmer and more humid than the North-Russian air.",
      "b. The North-Russian air is colder and more humid than the air of the Azores.",
      "c. The air of the Azores is warmer and dryer than the North-Russian air.",
      "d. The North-Russian air is warmer and dryer than the air of the Azores."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The air of the Azores is warmer and more humid than the North-Russian air."
  },
  {
    "question": "796. Where is the source of tropical continental air that affects Europe in summer?",
    "options": [
      "a. The Azores region.",
      "b. Southern Italy.",
      "c. Southern France.",
      "d. The southern Balkan region and the Near East."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The southern Balkan region and the Near East."
  },
  {
    "question": "797. Where does polar continental air originate?",
    "options": [
      "a. The region of the Baltic sea.",
      "b. Areas of arctic water.",
      "c. Siberian landmass.",
      "d. The region of Greenland."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Siberian landmass."
  },
  {
    "question": "798. In which air mass are extremely low temperatures encountered?",
    "options": [
      "a. Arctic maritime air.",
      "b. Polar maritime air.",
      "c. Tropical continental air.",
      "d. Polar continental air."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Polar continental air."
  },
  {
    "question": "799. In which of the following regions does polar maritime air originate ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Baltic Sea",
      "b. Region of British Isles",
      "c. East of Greenland",
      "d. Black Sea"
    ],
    "answer": "c. East of Greenland"
  },
  {
    "question": "800. What is the classification of the airmass affecting position \"Q\" at 0600 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. Tropical continental.",
      "b. Polar maritime.",
      "c. Polar continental.",
      "d. Tropical maritime."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Tropical maritime."
  },
  {
    "question": "801. Which are characteristics of an unstable cold air mass moving over a warm surface?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and poor visibility.",
      "b. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility.",
      "c. Stratiform clouds, smooth air, and poor visibility.",
      "d. Stratiform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "802. A warm air mass:",
    "options": [
      "a. is cooled from below by the base layer.",
      "b. is warmed from below by the base layer.",
      "c. originates at the equator.",
      "d. is characterized by sea breeze."
    ],
    "answer": "a. is cooled from below by the base layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "803. The stability of an air mass increases by:",
    "options": [
      "a. cooling of the lower and heating of the upper layers.",
      "b. heating of the lower and cooling of the upper layers.",
      "c. supply of humidity.",
      "d. decreasing dispersion."
    ],
    "answer": "a. cooling of the lower and heating of the upper layers."
  },
  {
    "question": "804. A body of air over the ocean is referred to as:",
    "options": [
      "a. Polar air",
      "b. Oceanic air",
      "c. Maritime air"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Maritime air"
  },
  {
    "question": "805. What are the most common characteristics of a cold air mass moving over a warm surface?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility",
      "b. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and poor visibility",
      "c. Stratiform clouds, smooth air, and poor visibility",
      "d. Stratiform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "806. What are the most common characteristics of a warm airmass, moving over a cold surface?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility",
      "b. Comuliform clouds, turbulence, and poor visibility",
      "c. Stratiform clouds, smooth air, and poor visibility",
      "d. Stratiform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Stratiform clouds, smooth air, and poor visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "807. Where does a Polar Cold Airmass has its origin?",
    "options": [
      "a. Over the Siberian Landmass",
      "b. Over the Baltic Sea",
      "c. Over the Atlantic Ocean",
      "d. Over the North Pole"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Over the Siberian Landmass"
  },
  {
    "question": "808. Which air masses do most often contribute to the weather situation in Western Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Maritime tropical air, maritime polar air",
      "b. Maritime tropical air, continental polar air",
      "c. Continental tropical air, continental arctic air",
      "d. Maritime equatorial air, maritime polar air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Maritime tropical air, maritime polar air"
  },
  {
    "question": "809. The polar front is the boundary between:",
    "options": [
      "a. maritime polar air and continental polar air.",
      "b. arctic air and polar air.",
      "c. arctic air and tropical air.",
      "d. polar air and tropical air."
    ],
    "answer": "d. polar air and tropical air."
  },
  {
    "question": "810. What type of low pressure area is associated with a surface front?",
    "options": [
      "a. A low on lee side of a mountain.",
      "b. A cold air pool.",
      "c. Polar front low.",
      "d. Heat low."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Polar front low."
  },
  {
    "question": "811. At what time of the year, are the paths of north Atlantic lows moving from west to east generally, at their most southerly position?",
    "options": [
      "a. Autumn.",
      "b. Summer.",
      "c. Spring.",
      "d. Winter."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Winter."
  },
  {
    "question": "812. Examining the pictures, on which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is this cross- section to be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. Track B-C",
      "b. Track B-D",
      "c. Track A-D",
      "d. Track A-E"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Track B-D"
  },
  {
    "question": "813. What type of fronts are most likely to be present during the winter in Central Europe when temperatures close to the ground are below 0\u00b0C, and freezing rain starts to fall?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold occlusions.",
      "b. Warm fronts, warm occlusions.",
      "c. High level cold fronts.",
      "d. Cold fronts."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Warm fronts, warm occlusions."
  },
  {
    "question": "814. Which of the following conditions are you most likely to encounter when approaching an active warm front at medium to low level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Severe thunderstorms at low altitude.",
      "b. Low cloud base and poor visibility.",
      "c. Extreme turbulence and severe lightning striking the ground.",
      "d. High cloud base, good surface visibility, and isolated thunderstorms."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Low cloud base and poor visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "815. During a cross-country flight at FL 50, you observe the following sequence of clouds: Nimbostratus, Altostratus, Cirrostratus, Cirrus. Which of the following are you most likely to encounter ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Strong, gusty winds.",
      "b. Decreasing temperatures.",
      "c. A strong downdraught.",
      "d. Increasing temperatures."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Decreasing temperatures."
  },
  {
    "question": "816. What cloud formation is most likely to occur at low levels when a warm air mass overrides a cold air mass?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulus.",
      "b. Nimbostratus.",
      "c. Altostratus.",
      "d. Cumulonimbus."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Nimbostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "817. The approximate inclined plane of a warm front is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1/50",
      "b. 1/150",
      "c. 1/300",
      "d. 1/500"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1/150"
  },
  {
    "question": "818. In which of the following situations can freezing rain be encountered ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ahead of a warm front in the winter",
      "b. Ahead of a cold front in the winter",
      "c. Behind a warm front in the summer",
      "d. Ahead of a cold front in the summer"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ahead of a warm front in the winter"
  },
  {
    "question": "819. How do air masses move at a warm front ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold air overrides a warm air mass",
      "b. Warm air overrides a cold air mass",
      "c. Cold air undercuts a warm air mass",
      "d. Warm air undercuts a cold air mass"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Warm air overrides a cold air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "820. Thunderstorms in exceptional circumstances can occur in a warm front if",
    "options": [
      "a. the cold air is convectively stable.",
      "b. the cold air is convectively unstable.",
      "c. the warm air is convectively unstable.",
      "d. the warm air is convectively stable."
    ],
    "answer": "c. the warm air is convectively unstable."
  },
  {
    "question": "821. On an aerodrome, when a warm front is approaching",
    "options": [
      "a. QFE increases and QNH decreases.",
      "b. QFE and QNH increase.",
      "c. QFE and QNH decrease.",
      "d. QFE decreases and QNH increases."
    ],
    "answer": "c. QFE and QNH decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "822. What types of cloud will you meet flying towards a warm front ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Extensive areas of fog. At some100 km from the front NS begin",
      "b. At some 800 km CS, later AS, and at some 300 km NS until the front",
      "c. At some 500 km AS, later CS and at some 80 km before the front CB",
      "d. At some 500 km from the front, groups of CB, later at some 250 km thickening AS"
    ],
    "answer": "b. At some 800 km CS, later AS, and at some 300 km NS until the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "823. If you have to fly through a warm front when freezing level is at 10000 feet in the warm air and at 2000 feet in the cold air, at which altitude is the probability of freezing rain the lowest ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 9000 feet",
      "b. 12000 feet",
      "c. 5000 feet",
      "d. 3000 feet"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 12000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "824. Read this description: \"After such a fine day, the ring around the moon was a bad sign yesterday evening for the weather today. And, sure enough, it is pouring down outside. The clouds are making an oppressively low ceiling of uniform grey; but at least it has become a little bit warmer.\" Which of these weather phenomena is being described?",
    "options": [
      "a. A warm front",
      "b. A blizzard",
      "c. Weather at the back of a cold front",
      "d. A cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "825. The main factor which contributes to the formation of very low clouds ahead of a warm front is the",
    "options": [
      "a. saturation of the warm air by rain falling into it and evaporating",
      "b. saturation of the cold air by rain falling into it and evaporating",
      "c. reduction of outgoing radiation due to clouds",
      "d. warm air moving over a cold surface"
    ],
    "answer": "b. saturation of the cold air by rain falling into it and evaporating"
  },
  {
    "question": "826. The following is true concerning a warm front:",
    "options": [
      "a. The associated type of weather is mostly uniform and offers only small variations.",
      "b. When the air is stable, the clouds are stratiform with uniform precipitation.",
      "c. When the air is unstable, the clouds form vertically and showers will develop in the precipitation area.",
      "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "b. When the air is stable, the clouds are stratiform with uniform precipitation."
  },
  {
    "question": "827. After passing at right angles through a very active cold front in the direction of the cold air, what will you encounter, in the northern hemisphere immediately after a marked change in temperature?",
    "options": [
      "a. A decrease in headwind.",
      "b. A backing in the wind direction.",
      "c. An increase in tailwind.",
      "d. A veering in the wind direction."
    ],
    "answer": "d. A veering in the wind direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "828. What type of precipitation would you expect at an active unstable cold front?",
    "options": [
      "a. Showers associated with thunderstorms",
      "b. Freezing rain",
      "c. Light to moderate continuous rain",
      "d. Drizzle"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Showers associated with thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "829. What is the relative movement of the two airmasses along a cold front ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold air slides over a warm air mass",
      "b. Warm air pushes over a cold air mass",
      "c. Cold air pushes under a warm air mass",
      "d. Warm air pushes under a cold air mass"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Cold air pushes under a warm air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "830. What change in pressure, will occur at point A, during the next hour?",
    "options": [
      "a. Approximately constant pressure",
      "b. A drop in pressure",
      "c. Irregular fluctuations",
      "d. A rise in pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "d. A rise in pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "831. Which of the following is typical for the passage of a cold front in the summer ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rapid increase in temperature once the front has passed",
      "b. Mainly layered clouds",
      "c. Rapid drop in pressure once the front has passed",
      "d. Mainly towering clouds"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Mainly towering clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "832. The following is true concerning a cold front:",
    "options": [
      "a. A cold front is normally less steep than a warm front.",
      "b. A cold front is normally moving with less speed than a warm front.",
      "c. A cold front is normally steeper than a warm front.",
      "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "c. A cold front is normally steeper than a warm front."
  },
  {
    "question": "833. The weather associated with a cold front may vary from a minor change of wind to a serious thunderstorm with low cloud base, bad visibility and strong, gusty winds. The type of weather depends on:",
    "options": [
      "a. The amount of humidity in the warm air.",
      "b. The stability of the warm air.",
      "c. The speed and slope of the cold front.",
      "d. All answers are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. All answers are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "834. You observe the altimeter in a parked aircraft shortly before an active cold front passes. What does the altimeter indicate?",
    "options": [
      "a. It increases",
      "b. It decreases",
      "c. It is not affected by a pressure change",
      "d. The pressure changes are very small and therefore, there is no visible change of the indication"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "835. You observe the altimeter in a parked aircraft shorty after an active cold front has passed. What does the altimeter indicate?",
    "options": [
      "a. It increases",
      "b. It decreases",
      "c. It is not affected by a pressure change",
      "d. The pressure changes are very small and therefore, there is no visible change of the indication"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "836. Over Central Europe what type of cloud cover is typical of the warm sector of a depression during winter?",
    "options": [
      "a. CI, CS.",
      "b. ST with drizzle.",
      "c. Fair weather CU.",
      "d. CU, CB."
    ],
    "answer": "b. ST with drizzle."
  },
  {
    "question": "837. What is the surface visibility most likely to be, in a warm sector of tropical maritime air, during the summer?",
    "options": [
      "a. Very good (greater than 50 km).",
      "b. Very poor (less than 1 km).",
      "c. Good (greater than 10 km).",
      "d. Moderate (several km)."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Moderate (several km)."
  },
  {
    "question": "838. What cloud cover is typical for a wide warm sector of a polar front depression over Central Europe in the summer ?",
    "options": [
      "a. BKN CU and CB",
      "b. Fair weather CU",
      "c. Sky clear",
      "d. ST with drizzle"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Fair weather CU"
  },
  {
    "question": "839. What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground during the period following the passage of an active cold front ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It will have increased.",
      "b. It will remain unchanged.",
      "c. It will have decreased.",
      "d. It will show a small increase or decrease."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It will have decreased."
  },
  {
    "question": "840. What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground shortly before an active cold front passes?",
    "options": [
      "a. It will be decreasing.",
      "b. It will remain unchanged.",
      "c. It will be increasing.",
      "d. It will fluctuate up and down by about +/- 50 feet."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It will be increasing."
  },
  {
    "question": "841. What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground as an active cold front is passing?",
    "options": [
      "a. It will first increase then decrease.",
      "b. It will remain unchanged.",
      "c. It will first decrease then increase.",
      "d. It will fluctuate up and down by about +/- 50 feet."
    ],
    "answer": "a. It will first increase then decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "842. What weather conditions are prevalent during the summer, over the North Sea, approximately 300 km behind a quickly moving cold front?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cloud cover mostly scattered, isolated showers.",
      "b. Showers and thunderstorms.",
      "c. Rain covering a large area, 8 octas NS.",
      "d. 8 octas CS, AS without precipitation."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cloud cover mostly scattered, isolated showers."
  },
  {
    "question": "843. Where is the coldest air to be found, in an occlusion with cold front characteristics?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ahead of the front.",
      "b. Behind the front.",
      "c. At the surface position of the front.",
      "d. At the junction of the occlusion."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Behind the front."
  },
  {
    "question": "844. Which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is represented by the cross-section shown on the left ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Track B-A",
      "b. Track C-A",
      "c. Track D-A",
      "d. Track B-C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Track D-A"
  },
  {
    "question": "845. Which cross-section of air mass and cloud presentation is applicable to the straight line A-B?",
    "options": [
      "a. a",
      "b. c",
      "c. b",
      "d. d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. a"
  },
  {
    "question": "846. Which of the following describes a warm occlusion?",
    "options": [
      "a. The air mass ahead of the front is drier than the air mass behind the front",
      "b. The air mass behind the front is more unstable than the air mass ahead of the front",
      "c. The coldest air mass is ahead of the original warm front",
      "d. The warmer air mass is ahead of the original warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The coldest air mass is ahead of the original warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "847. When do cold occlusions occur most frequently in Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Summer",
      "b. Winter",
      "c. Autumn and winter",
      "d. Winter and spring"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "848. How are the air masses distributed in a cold occlusion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The coldest air mass behind and the less cold air in front of the occlusion; the warm air mass is above ground level.",
      "b. The coldest air in front of and the less cold air is behind the occlusion; the warm air mass is above ground level.",
      "c. The coldest air in front of and the warm air behind the occlusion; the less cold air is above ground level.",
      "d. The coldest air behind and the warm air in front of the occlusion; the less cold air mass is above ground level."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The coldest air mass behind and the less cold air in front of the occlusion; the warm air mass is above ground level."
  },
  {
    "question": "849. In a polar front depression, an occlusion is called a warm occlusion when the cold air",
    "options": [
      "a. behind is less cold than the cold air in front, with the warm air at a high altitude.",
      "b. in front of the surface position of front is only at a high altitude.",
      "c. behind is colder than the cold air in front.",
      "d. behind is colder than the cold air in front, with the warm air being at a high altitude."
    ],
    "answer": "a. behind is less cold than the cold air in front, with the warm air at a high altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "850. In a warm front occlusion",
    "options": [
      "a. the warm front becomes a front aloft",
      "b. the warm front overtakes the cold front",
      "c. the warm air is lifted",
      "d. the cold air is lifted"
    ],
    "answer": "c. the warm air is lifted"
  },
  {
    "question": "851. An occlusion takes place when:",
    "options": [
      "a. A cold front catches up with a warm front.",
      "b. Warm air displaces cold air.",
      "c. Cold air displaces warm air.",
      "d. The front no longer moves."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A cold front catches up with a warm front."
  },
  {
    "question": "852. Describe a warm occlusion at a polar front depression:",
    "options": [
      "a. The air behind the cold front is less cold than the air ahead of the warm front",
      "b. The air behind the cold front is colder than the air ahead of the warm front",
      "c. The air ahead of the warm front is warmer than the air behind the cold front",
      "d. Both, the air ahead of the warm front and the air behind the cold front are of approximately the same temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The air behind the cold front is less cold than the air ahead of the warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "853. Describe a cold occlusion at a polar front depression:",
    "options": [
      "a. The air behind the cold front is less cold than the air ahead of the warm front",
      "b. The air ahead of the warm front is colder than the air behind the cold front",
      "c. The air ahead of the warm front is warmer than the air behind the cold front",
      "d. Both, the air ahead of the warm front and the air behind the cold front are of approximately the same temperature"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The air ahead of the warm front is warmer than the air behind the cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "854. What characterizes a stationary front ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The surface wind usually has its direction perpendicular to the front",
      "b. The surface wind usually has its direction parallel to the front",
      "c. The warm air moves at approximately half the speed of the cold air",
      "d. The weather conditions that it originates is a combination between those of an intense cold front and those of a warm and very active front"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The surface wind usually has its direction parallel to the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "855. What is feature of a stationary front?",
    "options": [
      "a. The warm front surface moves about half the speed of the cold front surface",
      "b. Weather conditions are a combination of strong cold front and strong warm front weather",
      "c. Surface winds tend to flow parallel to the frontal zone"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Surface winds tend to flow parallel to the frontal zone"
  },
  {
    "question": "856. In which approximate direction does the centre of a frontal depression move?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the direction of the warm sector isobars.",
      "b. In the direction of the isobars ahead of the warm front.",
      "c. In the direction of the sharpest pressure increase.",
      "d. In the direction of the isobars behind the cold front."
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the direction of the warm sector isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "857. What type of front / occlusion usually moves the fastest?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold front.",
      "b. Warm front.",
      "c. Cold occlusion.",
      "d. Warm occlusion."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cold front."
  },
  {
    "question": "858. This chart shows the weather conditions on the ground at 0600 UTC on May 4. Which of the following reports reflects weather development at Geneva Airport?",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF LSGG 230716 05014KT 5000 OVC015 BECMG 0810 8000 BKN018 BECMG 1013 05015G30KT 9999 SCT025 =",
      "b. TAF LSGG 230716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT030 BKN090 =",
      "c. TAF LSGG 230716 26012KT 9999 SCT030 BKN080 TEMPO 1013 25020G35KT 3000 TSRA or +SHRA BKN030CB BECMG 1316 VRB02KT 3000 BCFG SCT100 =",
      "d. TAF LSGG 230716 VRB03KT 6000 BR SCT020 BECMG 0811 23005KT 9999 SCT025TCU PROB 40 TEMPO 1216 34012G30KT 3000 TSRA BKN020CB ="
    ],
    "answer": "b. TAF LSGG 230716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT030 BKN090 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "859. In Zurich during a summer day the following weather observations were taken: 160450Z 23015KT 3000 +RA SCT008 SCT020 OVC030 13/12 Q1010 NOSIG = 160650Z 25008KT 6000 SCT040 BKN090 18/14 Q1010 RERA NOSIG = 160850Z 25006KT 8000 SCT040 SCT100 19/15 Q1009 NOSIG = 161050Z 24008KT 9999 SCT040 SCT100 21/15 Q1008 NOSIG = 161250Z 23012KT CAVOK 23/16 Q1005 NOSIG = 161450Z 23016KT",
    "options": [
      "a. A cold front passed the station early in the morning and a warm front during late afternoon",
      "b. A warm front passed the station early in the morning and a cold front during late afternoon",
      "c. A trough line passed the station early in the morning and a warm front during late afternoon",
      "d. Storm clouds due to warm air came close to and grazed the station"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A warm front passed the station early in the morning and a cold front during late afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "860. Refer to the diagram. Assuming the usual direction of movement, where will this polar frontal wave have moved ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Position c",
      "b. Position a",
      "c. Position b",
      "d. Position d"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Position c"
  },
  {
    "question": "861. In which main direction does a polar front depression move?",
    "options": [
      "a. Along the front towards the east",
      "b. Along the front towards the west",
      "c. Across the front towards the north",
      "d. Across the front towards the south"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Along the front towards the east"
  },
  {
    "question": "862. Frontal depressions can be assumed to move in the direction of the 2000 feet wind",
    "options": [
      "a. in the warm sector",
      "b. in front of the warm front",
      "c. behind the cold front",
      "d. at the apex of the wave"
    ],
    "answer": "a. in the warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "863. A frontal depression passes through the airport. What form of precipitation do you expect ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rain or snow during about 12 hours until the warm front arrives. Within the warm sector the rain increases. Improvement on the passage of the cold front.",
      "b. Continous rain or snow while the frontal wave passes for a period of some 24 hours.",
      "c. Showers during some 2 hours until the warm front arrives. Drizzle in the warm sector within 12 hours. Rain or snow on the passage of the cold front.",
      "d. Continuous rain or snow during 6 hours until the warm front arrives. The precipitation stops for several hours within the warm sector. On the arrival of the cold front, showers within a couple of hours."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Continuous rain or snow during 6 hours until the warm front arrives. The precipitation stops for several hours within the warm sector. On the arrival of the cold front, showers within a couple of hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "864. Refer to the diagram. Assuming the usual direction of movement, to which position will the polar frontal wave have moved ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Position D",
      "b. Position C",
      "c. Position A",
      "d. Position B"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Position D"
  },
  {
    "question": "865. An observer on the northern hemisphere is under influence of the wind system of a depression, which is moving from West to East. The centre of the depression passes to the South of the observer. For this observer the wind direction is",
    "options": [
      "a. continuously veering",
      "b. continuously backing",
      "c. initially backing, then veering",
      "d. initially veering, then backing"
    ],
    "answer": "b. continuously backing"
  },
  {
    "question": "866. In connection with the passage of a front:",
    "options": [
      "a. The pressure will increase before it passes.",
      "b. The pressure will decrease before it passes.",
      "c. After frontal passage, the wind will veer to the left.",
      "d. Answers b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "b. The pressure will decrease before it passes."
  },
  {
    "question": "867. If a cold front moves at 30 knots, you could expect the warm front to be moving at:",
    "options": [
      "a. 20 knots",
      "b. 30 knots",
      "c. 40 knots",
      "d. 50 knots"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 20 knots"
  },
  {
    "question": "868. In which direction does the polar front move in this picture?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "c. C"
  },
  {
    "question": "869. In which direction does the polar front move in this picture?",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "c. C"
  },
  {
    "question": "870. On a summer day, the following observations are made in Zurich: 0450Z 23015KT 3000 +RA SCT008 SCT020 0VC030 13/12 Q1010 NOSIG= 0650Z 25008KT 6000 SCT040 BKN090 18/14 Q1010 RERA NOSIG= 0850Z 25006KT 8000 SCT040 SCT100 19/15 Q1009 NOSIG= 1050Z 24008KT 9999 SCT040 SCT100 21/15 Q1008 NOSIG= 1250Z 23012KT CAVOK 23/16 Q1005 NOSIG= 1450Z 23016KT 9999 SCT040 BKN090 24/17 Q1003",
    "options": [
      "a. a warm front early in the morning and a cold front late in the afternoon have passed the station",
      "b. a trough line early in the morning and a warm front late in the afternoon have passed the station",
      "c. an air mass thunderstorm only has passed during the entire day",
      "d. a cold front early in the morning and a warm front late in the afternoon have passed the station"
    ],
    "answer": "a. a warm front early in the morning and a cold front late in the afternoon have passed the station"
  },
  {
    "question": "871. On a summer day, the following observations are made in Zurich: 0650Z 19002 KT 3000 SCT280 08/07 Q1019 BECMG 5000 = 0850Z 21004KT 8000 BKN280 10/07 Q1019 NOSIG = 1050Z 22007KT CAVOK 14/06 Q1017 NOSIG = 1250Z 22012KT 9999 SCT040 SCT100 BKN250 16/07 Q1016 NOSIG = 1450Z 22015KT 9999 SCT040 OVC080 17/08 Q1014 NOSIG = 1650Z 23014KT 8000 -RA SCT030 OVC070 16/10 Q1013 TEMPO 30",
    "options": [
      "a. a cold front in the morning, and a second cold front in the afternoon have passed the station",
      "b. a warm front has passed the station during the day",
      "c. a warm front early in the morning, and a cold front in the evening have passed the station",
      "d. a north foehn weather pattern prevailed the entire day"
    ],
    "answer": "b. a warm front has passed the station during the day"
  },
  {
    "question": "872. On a summer day, the following observations are made in Zurich: 0450Z 24009 KT 7000 SCT040 SCT120 15/12 Q1014 NOSIG = 0650Z 24010KT 6000 SCT040 SCT120 17/13 Q1012 NOSIG = 0850Z 23014KT 8000 BKN100 19/13 Q1009 BECMG 26020G35KT TS = 1050Z 28022G33KT 4000 TSRA SCT015 SCT050CB OVC080 16/14 Q1006 BECMG NSW = 1250Z 31016KT 9999 SCT025TCU BKN030 13/09 Q1009 NOSIG = 1450Z 30012",
    "options": [
      "a. a warm front in the morning, and a cold front in the afternoon have passed the station",
      "b. a warm front has passed the station in the morning, and warm sector weather prevailed in the afternoon",
      "c. a cold front has passed the station in the morning, and rear side weather prevailed in the afternoon",
      "d. a cold front in the morning, and a warm front in the afternoon have passed the station"
    ],
    "answer": "c. a cold front has passed the station in the morning, and rear side weather prevailed in the afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "873. Refer to the chart: On which airport do you expect the development of the following weather situation: TAF 1019 21010KT 8000 SCT120 OVC180 BECMG 1013 OVC090 TEMPO -RA BECMG 1417 22016KT 5000 RA BKN020 OVC030 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN012 OVC020 =",
    "options": [
      "a. EGLL",
      "b. LYBE",
      "c. LFPO",
      "d. LSZH"
    ],
    "answer": "d. LSZH"
  },
  {
    "question": "874. Refer to the chart: Which airport has the biggest probability for rain at 12.00 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. EKCH",
      "b. LFPO",
      "c. LIRF",
      "d. LEMD"
    ],
    "answer": "d. LEMD"
  },
  {
    "question": "875. Refer to the chart: Which weather situation do you expect for EGLL at 1150 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. 23015KT 8000 SCT100 BKN200 21/07 Q1002 NOSIG=",
      "b. 32002KT 3000 OBC006 16/12 Q1024 TEMPO 8000 =",
      "c. 17016G28KT 2500 +RA BKN009 OVC 018 12/10 Q0994 BECMG 8000 =",
      "d. 28006KT 4000 -TSRA SCT012 BKN030CB 19/14 Q1022 BECMG NSW ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. 17016G28KT 2500 +RA BKN009 OVC 018 12/10 Q0994 BECMG 8000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "876. Refer to the chart: Which weather situation do you expect for LGAT at 1450 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. 21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 NOSIG =",
      "b. 16002KT 0200 R33L/0600N FG VV001 12/12 Q1031 BECMG 0800 =",
      "c. 26014KT 8000 BKN090 17/12 Q1009 BECMG 4000 =",
      "d. 23018G35KT 9999 SCT035 10/04 Q0988 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "a. 21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "877. Refer to the chart: On which airport do you expect the development of the following weather situation? TAF 1322 24014G32KT 4000 +TSRA SCT005 BKN015 BKN020CB BECMG 1416 29012KT 9999 BKN030TCU SCT100 TEMPO 8000 SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 1922 27012KT 9999 SCT030 OVC220 =",
    "options": [
      "a. ESSA",
      "b. EINN",
      "c. LSZH",
      "d. EKCH"
    ],
    "answer": "b. EINN"
  },
  {
    "question": "878. Refer to the chart: Which airport has the biggest probability for the formation of fog the following night?",
    "options": [
      "a. ENFB",
      "b. EKCH",
      "c. EINN",
      "d. LFPO"
    ],
    "answer": "d. LFPO"
  },
  {
    "question": "879. Where does the frontal depression move in the direction of the 2000 ft wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the warm sector",
      "b. At the rear side",
      "c. Ahead of the warm front",
      "d. In the center of an occlusion"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "880. In which of the following areas do surface high pressure systems usually predominate over the North Atlantic region between 30\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N and the adjoining land areas during the northern summer?",
    "options": [
      "a. Greenland, SW Europe, NE Canada",
      "b. Greenland, Azores, NE Canada",
      "c. Iceland, SW USA, Azores",
      "d. Azores, SE USA, SW Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Azores, SE USA, SW Europe"
  },
  {
    "question": "881. Select the answer which you consider will complete correctly the following statement in relation to the main pressure systems affecting the North Atlantic region between 30\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N. During winter the predominant mean low pressure system at the surface is usually centred over",
    "options": [
      "a. USA",
      "b. Iceland / Greenland",
      "c. Siberia",
      "d. Azores"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Iceland / Greenland"
  },
  {
    "question": "882. Considering the North Atlantic region between 30\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N and the adjacent land areas during mid-summer, the predominant pressure systems are",
    "options": [
      "a. weak low over NE Canada and Scandinavian high",
      "b. Scandinavian high and Azores high",
      "c. Azores high and weak low over NE Canada",
      "d. Azores low and Icelandic high"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Azores high and weak low over NE Canada"
  },
  {
    "question": "883. Considering the North Atlantic region between 30\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N together with the adjacent land areas during winter, the normal disposition of the main anticyclones at the surface is",
    "options": [
      "a. Azores, Siberia",
      "b. Siberia, Iceland, Canaries",
      "c. NE Canada, Iceland",
      "d. Greenland, Iberian peninsula"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Azores, Siberia"
  },
  {
    "question": "884. The formation of high and low pressure areas is normally caused by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Temperature differences.",
      "b. Humidity.",
      "c. Mechanical turbulence.",
      "d. Storms."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Temperature differences."
  },
  {
    "question": "885. Select the answer in relation to the main pressure systems affecting the North Atlantic region between 30\u00b0N and 65\u00b0N: During winter the predominant low pressure system at the surface is usually centered over......",
    "options": [
      "a. USA",
      "b. Siberia",
      "c. Azores",
      "d. Iceland & Greenland"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Iceland & Greenland"
  },
  {
    "question": "886. What is the correct term for the descending air flow in a large high pressure area?",
    "options": [
      "a. Convection.",
      "b. Convergence.",
      "c. Advection.",
      "d. Subsidence."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Subsidence."
  },
  {
    "question": "887. What surface weather is associated with a stationary high pressure region over land in the winter?",
    "options": [
      "a. Thunderstorms.",
      "b. A tendency for fog and low ST.",
      "c. NS with continuous rain.",
      "d. The possibility of snow showers."
    ],
    "answer": "b. A tendency for fog and low ST."
  },
  {
    "question": "888. In temperate latitudes what weather conditions may be expected over land during the summer in the centre of a stationary high pressure zone ?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS.",
      "b. TS, SH.",
      "c. CB, TS.",
      "d. Calm winds, haze."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Calm winds, haze."
  },
  {
    "question": "889. What is the most likely cause of a lack of clouds at higher levels in a stationary high?",
    "options": [
      "a. Instability",
      "b. Rising air",
      "c. Sinking air",
      "d. Divergence at higher levels"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Sinking air"
  },
  {
    "question": "890. Subsidence is :",
    "options": [
      "a. vertically upwards motion of air",
      "b. horizontal motion of air",
      "c. vertically downwards motion of air",
      "d. the same as convection"
    ],
    "answer": "c. vertically downwards motion of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "891. The most effective way to dissipate cloud is by",
    "options": [
      "a. convection",
      "b. subsidence",
      "c. a decrease in temperature",
      "d. a decrease in pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "b. subsidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "892. Areas of sinking air are generally cloudless because as air sinks it",
    "options": [
      "a. reaches warmer layers",
      "b. is heated by compression",
      "c. is heated by expansion",
      "d. loses water vapour"
    ],
    "answer": "b. is heated by compression"
  },
  {
    "question": "893. If the pressure surfaces bulge upwards in all levels then the pressure system is a",
    "options": [
      "a. cold low",
      "b. warm high",
      "c. cold high",
      "d. warm low"
    ],
    "answer": "b. warm high"
  },
  {
    "question": "894. The stable layer at some height in the low troposphere of an older high pressure area in the mid-latitudes is called",
    "options": [
      "a. subsidence inversion",
      "b. friction inversion",
      "c. radiation inversion",
      "d. trade wind inversion"
    ],
    "answer": "a. subsidence inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "895. A blocking anticyclone on the northern hemisphere is",
    "options": [
      "a. a warm anticyclone/quasi stationary/situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N",
      "b. quasi stationary/situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N/ a cold anticyclone",
      "c. situated between 50\u00b0 and 70\u00b0N/a cold anticyclone/steering depressions",
      "d. a cold anticyclone/steering depressions/situated over Scandinavia"
    ],
    "answer": "a. a warm anticyclone/quasi stationary/situated between 50\u00b0N and 70\u00b0N"
  },
  {
    "question": "896. Refer to the upper level chart: Flight path A - B, altimeter setting 1013,2 hPa:",
    "options": [
      "a. Your true altitude is greater in B than in A",
      "b. Your true altitude is greater in A than in B",
      "c. The wind speed is greater in A than in B",
      "d. The wind speed is equal in A and in B"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Your true altitude is greater in A than in B"
  },
  {
    "question": "897. What is encountered during the summer, over land, in the centre of a cold air pool?",
    "options": [
      "a. Nothing (CAVOK).",
      "b. Strong westerly winds.",
      "c. Fine weather CU.",
      "d. Showers and thunderstorms."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Showers and thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "898. How do you recognize a cold air pool?",
    "options": [
      "a. A cold air pool may only be recognized on the surface chart as a low pressure area.",
      "b. As a high pressure area aloft (e.g. on the 500 hPa chart).",
      "c. As a low pressure area aloft (e.g. on the 500 hPa chart).",
      "d. A cold air pool may only be recognized on the surface chart as a high pressure area."
    ],
    "answer": "c. As a low pressure area aloft (e.g. on the 500 hPa chart)."
  },
  {
    "question": "899. What type of air movement is associated with the centre line of a trough?",
    "options": [
      "a. Divergence with lifting.",
      "b. Divergence with descending air.",
      "c. Convergence with lifting.",
      "d. Convergence with descending air."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Convergence with lifting."
  },
  {
    "question": "900. With an intense trough of low pressure over Iceland during wintertime the weather likely to be experienced is :",
    "options": [
      "a. strong wind shear, convection and snow showers",
      "b. light wind, good visibility and a high cloud ceiling",
      "c. strong wind with subsidence at low levels",
      "d. strong wind associated with an almost clear sky"
    ],
    "answer": "a. strong wind shear, convection and snow showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "901. Extensive cloud and precipitation is often associated with a non frontal thermal depression because of :",
    "options": [
      "a. surface divergence and upper level convergence causing widespread descent of air in the depression",
      "b. surface convergence and upper level divergence causing widespread descent of air in the depression",
      "c. surface convergence and upper level divergence causing widespread ascent of air in the depression",
      "d. surface divergence and upper level convergence causing widespread ascent of air in the depression"
    ],
    "answer": "c. surface convergence and upper level divergence causing widespread ascent of air in the depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "902. Which is true of a secondary depression in the northern hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. It tends to move round the primary in a cyclonic sense",
      "b. It tends to move round the primary in an anticyclonic sense",
      "c. It rapidly closes on, and merges with the primary",
      "d. It tends to maintain its position relative to the primary"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It tends to move round the primary in a cyclonic sense"
  },
  {
    "question": "903. A trough of low pressure on a surface synoptic chart is an area of",
    "options": [
      "a. divergence and subsidence",
      "b. convergence and widespread ascent",
      "c. divergence and widespread ascent",
      "d. convergence and subsidence"
    ],
    "answer": "b. convergence and widespread ascent"
  },
  {
    "question": "904. Which is true of a typical non frontal thermal depression?",
    "options": [
      "a. It forms over the ocean in summer",
      "b. It forms over land in summer",
      "c. It forms over the ocean in winter",
      "d. It forms over land in winter"
    ],
    "answer": "b. It forms over land in summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "905. Where is the most dangerous zone in a tropical revolving storm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Anywhere in the eye.",
      "b. In the wall of clouds around the eye.",
      "c. In the centre of the eye.",
      "d. About 600 km away from the eye."
    ],
    "answer": "b. In the wall of clouds around the eye."
  },
  {
    "question": "906. What type of clouds, visible even at a long distance, could indicate the presence of a tropical revolving storm?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS spread over a large area",
      "b. Frequent SC",
      "c. Excessive accumulation of CU",
      "d. Dense CI"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Dense CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "907. Tropical revolving storms do not occur in the southeast Pacific and the south Atlantic because",
    "options": [
      "a. there is no coriolis force present.",
      "b. of the low water temperature.",
      "c. of the strong southeast wind.",
      "d. the southeast trade winds cross over into the northern hemisphere."
    ],
    "answer": "b. of the low water temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "908. What is the main energy source of a tropical revolving storm?",
    "options": [
      "a. The equatorial jet stream.",
      "b. Temperature difference between equatorial low pressure trough and subtropical high pressure belt.",
      "c. Cold air advancing from temperate latitudes.",
      "d. Latent heat released from condensing water vapour."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Latent heat released from condensing water vapour."
  },
  {
    "question": "909. What is the track most likely to be taken by a hurricane in the Carribean area?",
    "options": [
      "a. West in the earlier stages and later south east",
      "b. East",
      "c. West deep into the U.S.",
      "d. West in the earlier stages and later north east"
    ],
    "answer": "d. West in the earlier stages and later north east"
  },
  {
    "question": "910. Which statement is true for hurricanes in the North Atlantic?",
    "options": [
      "a. From the earth's surface up to the tropopause the core is warmer than its surroundings",
      "b. They intensify rapidly after landfall",
      "c. The diameter is 50-500 m",
      "d. Their greatest frequency of occurrence is in winter"
    ],
    "answer": "a. From the earth's surface up to the tropopause the core is warmer than its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "911. Why do tropical revolving storms tend to develop mostly in the western parts of the tropical oceans?",
    "options": [
      "a. Because there is a maximal temperature difference between land mass and sea",
      "b. Because they are areas in which there is a strong progressive windshear with increase of height",
      "c. Because there is a maximum of humidity as a result of the trade winds`long sea passage",
      "d. Because the gulf formation of the coastlines triggers a strong rotary circulation"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Because there is a maximum of humidity as a result of the trade winds`long sea passage"
  },
  {
    "question": "912. What is the likely track for a hurricane in the Carribean area?",
    "options": [
      "a. West in the earlier stages and later turning north east.",
      "b. East then south.",
      "c. West deep into the USA.",
      "d. West in the earlier stages and later turning south east."
    ],
    "answer": "a. West in the earlier stages and later turning north east."
  },
  {
    "question": "913. During which seasons are hurricanes most likely to appear in the northern hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. All seasons.",
      "b. Winter.",
      "c. Winter and spring.",
      "d. Summer and autumn."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Summer and autumn."
  },
  {
    "question": "914. On which coast of North America, is the danger of tropical revolving storms the greatest?",
    "options": [
      "a. NE coast",
      "b. W coast",
      "c. N coast",
      "d. SE coast"
    ],
    "answer": "d. SE coast"
  },
  {
    "question": "915. At what time of the year are typhoons most likely to occur over the southern islands of Japan?",
    "options": [
      "a. January to May.",
      "b. September to January.",
      "c. July to November.",
      "d. May to July."
    ],
    "answer": "c. July to November."
  },
  {
    "question": "916. During which months is the Hurricane season in the Caribbean?",
    "options": [
      "a. January until April.",
      "b. October until January.",
      "c. July until November.",
      "d. April until July."
    ],
    "answer": "c. July until November."
  },
  {
    "question": "917. The region of the globe where the greatest number of tropical revolving storms occur is",
    "options": [
      "a. the northern Indian ocean, affecting India, Sri Lanka and Bangladesh.",
      "b. the carribean sea, affecting the West Indies, Mexico and the south-east coastline of the USA.",
      "c. the south-western Indian ocean, affecting Madagascar, Mauritius and the island of R\u00e9union.",
      "d. the north-west Pacific, affecting Japan, Formosa, Korea and the Chinese coastline."
    ],
    "answer": "d. the north-west Pacific, affecting Japan, Formosa, Korea and the Chinese coastline."
  },
  {
    "question": "918. The arrows labelled \"r\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "options": [
      "a. June to October and are called typhoons",
      "b. December to April and are called tornadoes",
      "c. December to April and are called cyclones",
      "d. June to October and are called hurricanes"
    ],
    "answer": "c. December to April and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "919. The arrows labelled \"s\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "options": [
      "a. December to April and are called cyclones",
      "b. May to November and are called cyclones",
      "c. May to November and are called hurricanes",
      "d. December to April and are called typhoons"
    ],
    "answer": "b. May to November and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "920. The arrows labelled \"u\" represent the tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "options": [
      "a. January to March and are called willy-willies",
      "b. July to October and are called typhoons",
      "c. May to July and are called cyclones",
      "d. December to April and are called tornadoes"
    ],
    "answer": "b. July to October and are called typhoons"
  },
  {
    "question": "921. When, if at all, is a tropical revolving storm most likely to affect Darwin, on the central north coast of Australia?",
    "options": [
      "a. December to April",
      "b. May to July",
      "c. August to October",
      "d. Not experienced at Darwin"
    ],
    "answer": "a. December to April"
  },
  {
    "question": "922. At about what geographical latitude as average is assumed for the zone of prevailing westerlies?",
    "options": [
      "a. 50\u00b0N.",
      "b. 10\u00b0N.",
      "c. 30\u00b0N.",
      "d. 80\u00b0N."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 50\u00b0N."
  },
  {
    "question": "923. The reason for the fact, that the Icelandic low is normally deeper in winter than in summer is that",
    "options": [
      "a. the strong winds of the north Atlantic in winter are favourable for the development of lows.",
      "b. the low pressure activity of the sea east of Canada is higher in winter.",
      "c. the temperature contrasts between arctic and equatorial areas are much greater in winter.",
      "d. converging air currents are of greater intensity in winter."
    ],
    "answer": "c. the temperature contrasts between arctic and equatorial areas are much greater in winter."
  },
  {
    "question": "924. What is the type, intensity and seasonal variation of precipitation in the equatorial region ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Precipitation is generally in the form of showers but continuous rain occurs also. The greatest intensity is in July.",
      "b. Warm fronts are common with continuous rain. The frequency is the same throughout the year",
      "c. Rainshowers, hail showers and thunderstorms occur the whole year, but frequency is highest during two periods: April-May and October-November.",
      "d. Showers of rain or hail occur throughout the year; the frequency is highest in January."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Rainshowers, hail showers and thunderstorms occur the whole year, but frequency is highest during two periods: April-May and October-November."
  },
  {
    "question": "925. In which month does the humid monsoon in India start?",
    "options": [
      "a. June",
      "b. December",
      "c. March",
      "d. October"
    ],
    "answer": "a. June"
  },
  {
    "question": "926. When are the rainy seasons in equatorial Africa?",
    "options": [
      "a. March to May and October to November.",
      "b. December to February and July to October.",
      "c. March to May and August to October.",
      "d. April to July and December to February."
    ],
    "answer": "a. March to May and October to November."
  },
  {
    "question": "927. During July flights from Bangkok (13\u00b0N - 100\u00b0E) to Karachi (25\u00b0N - 67\u00b0E) experience an average tailwind component of 22 kt. In January the same flights, also operating at FL 370, have an average headwind of 50 kt. What is the reason for this difference?",
    "options": [
      "a. The flights happen to be in the area of the polar front jet stream.",
      "b. The flights during the summer encountered, by chance, very unusual, favorable conditions.",
      "c. The flights in January encountered, by chance, very unusual, adverse conditions.",
      "d. The wind components correspond to the seasonal change of the regional wind system."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The wind components correspond to the seasonal change of the regional wind system."
  },
  {
    "question": "928. Which of the following statements concerning trade winds is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. They reach up to the tropopause and are more pronounced over the continents",
      "b. They occur only in the lower part of the troposphere and more pronounced over the oceans",
      "c. They reach up to the tropopause and are more pronounced over the oceans",
      "d. They occur only in the lower part of the troposphere and are more pronounced over the continents"
    ],
    "answer": "b. They occur only in the lower part of the troposphere and more pronounced over the oceans"
  },
  {
    "question": "929. Which one of the following statements regarding the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. The ITCZ does not change its position during the course of the year.",
      "b. Thunderstorms seldom occur within the area of the ITCZ.",
      "c. The ITCZ is always associated with a strong jet stream.",
      "d. Frequent and widespread thunderstorms are to be expected within the area of the ITCZ."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Frequent and widespread thunderstorms are to be expected within the area of the ITCZ."
  },
  {
    "question": "930. In which of the following bands of latitude is the intertropical convergence zone most likely to be encountered in January, between Dakar and Rio de Janeiro?",
    "options": [
      "a. 8\u00b0 - 12\u00b0S.",
      "b. 3\u00b0 - 8\u00b0S.",
      "c. 0\u00b0 - 7\u00b0N.",
      "d. 7\u00b0 - 12\u00b0N."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 3\u00b0 - 8\u00b0S."
  },
  {
    "question": "931. Which of the following best describes the intertropical convergence zone ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The zone where the Harmattan meets the northeasterly trade winds over Africa.",
      "b. The zone where the trade winds of the northern hemisphere meet those of the southern hemisphere.",
      "c. The zone where cold fronts form in the tropics.",
      "d. The zone where the west winds meet the subtropical high pressure belt."
    ],
    "answer": "b. The zone where the trade winds of the northern hemisphere meet those of the southern hemisphere."
  },
  {
    "question": "932. Where, during a flight from Marseille to Dakar, in July, may the ITCZ be encountered?",
    "options": [
      "a. At the latitudes of Algeria",
      "b. Near the Canary Islands",
      "c. At the latitudes of Gibraltar",
      "d. In the vicinity of Dakar"
    ],
    "answer": "d. In the vicinity of Dakar"
  },
  {
    "question": "933. Which wind systems converge on the ITCZ, when it lies at the equator?",
    "options": [
      "a. SE trade winds and NE trade winds",
      "b. SW monsoon and NW monsoon",
      "c. SW monsoon and NW trade winds",
      "d. NW monsoon and SW trade winds"
    ],
    "answer": "a. SE trade winds and NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "934. The intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) particularly affects",
    "options": [
      "a. western Africa, at a latitude of 25\u00b0N in July.",
      "b. western Africa between 10\u00b0 and 20\u00b0N and the northern coasts of the Arabian sea in July.",
      "c. the atlantic ocean, between latitudes 10\u00b0N and 30\u00b0N, depending on the time of year.",
      "d. western Africa, where it is situated between the 10\u00b0N and 30\u00b0N parallels, depending on the time of the year."
    ],
    "answer": "b. western Africa between 10\u00b0 and 20\u00b0N and the northern coasts of the Arabian sea in July."
  },
  {
    "question": "935. Which one of the following statements is correct concerning the movement of the ITCZ in the region of West Africa?",
    "options": [
      "a. It reaches its maximum southerly position of 5\u00b0 S in January",
      "b. It reaches its maximum northerly position of 15\u00b0 - 20\u00b0 N in July",
      "c. It oscillates during the year between 10 degrees North and 10 degrees South.",
      "d. It oscillates during the year between the Equator and 10 degrees North."
    ],
    "answer": "b. It reaches its maximum northerly position of 15\u00b0 - 20\u00b0 N in July"
  },
  {
    "question": "936. What weather conditions are most likely to affect an approach to Dakar during July?",
    "options": [
      "a. Reduced visibility due to the rising sand of the Harmattan",
      "b. Dry and clear due to the influence of the Azores high pressure system",
      "c. Generally clear skies - NW trade winds",
      "d. Wet and thundery due to the proximity of intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ)"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Wet and thundery due to the proximity of intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ)"
  },
  {
    "question": "937. Which of the following statements concerning the intertropical convergence zone is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. There are frequent occurrences of CB",
      "b. It lies totally in the northern hemisphere in July and totally in the southern hemisphere in January",
      "c. It does not change its position over the oceans during the year",
      "d. It is an area of low pressure and low relative humidity"
    ],
    "answer": "a. There are frequent occurrences of CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "938. The line labelled \"Y\" represents the",
    "options": [
      "a. mean position of the temperate/tropical front during July",
      "b. axis of the subtropical jet stream during January",
      "c. mean position of the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) during July",
      "d. mean position of the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) during January"
    ],
    "answer": "d. mean position of the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) during January"
  },
  {
    "question": "939. What weather conditions are indications of the summer monsoon in India?",
    "options": [
      "a. Fog.",
      "b. Stratus clouds and drizzle.",
      "c. Sandstorms.",
      "d. Thunderstorms, showers of heavy rain."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Thunderstorms, showers of heavy rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "940. What winds are mainly associated with the winter monsoon in the monsoon regions of the Indian sub-continent ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Northeasterly winds bringing dry and hazy air.",
      "b. Southwesterly winds carrying warm and humid air.",
      "c. Northwesterly winds bringing dry and hazy air.",
      "d. Southeasterly winds carrying warm and humid air."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Northeasterly winds bringing dry and hazy air."
  },
  {
    "question": "941. What name is given to the low level wind system between the subtropical high pressure belt and the equatorial trough of low pressure (ITCZ) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Trade winds.",
      "b. Doldrums.",
      "c. Westerly winds.",
      "d. Monsoon."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Trade winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "942. From which direction do the trade winds blow, in the southern hemisphere?",
    "options": [
      "a. N",
      "b. NE",
      "c. SW",
      "d. SE"
    ],
    "answer": "d. SE"
  },
  {
    "question": "943. In which month does the humid monsoon in India start?",
    "options": [
      "a. In October.",
      "b. In June.",
      "c. In December.",
      "d. In March."
    ],
    "answer": "b. In June."
  },
  {
    "question": "944. What is the name of the wind or airmass which gives to the main part of India its greatest proportion of precipitation?",
    "options": [
      "a. Indian, maritime tropical air mass.",
      "b. South-east trade wind.",
      "c. South-west monsoon.",
      "d. Winter monsoon."
    ],
    "answer": "c. South-west monsoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "945. Weather conditions at Bombay during early July are mainly influenced by the",
    "options": [
      "a. NE monsoon and the proximity of the ITCZ",
      "b. SW monsoon",
      "c. passage of frontal system generated in the south indian ocean",
      "d. high incidence of tropical revolving storms originating in the persian gulf"
    ],
    "answer": "b. SW monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "946. Weather conditions at Bombay during January are mainly influenced by the",
    "options": [
      "a. SW monsoon",
      "b. NE monsoon",
      "c. NW monsoon",
      "d. SE monsoon"
    ],
    "answer": "b. NE monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "947. The transition from SW to NE monsoon in India occurs in",
    "options": [
      "a. September, October, November",
      "b. July, August, September",
      "c. December, January, February",
      "d. February, March, April"
    ],
    "answer": "a. September, October, November"
  },
  {
    "question": "948. The prevailing surface wind in the area of the west coast of Africa north of the equator (gulf of Guinea) is a",
    "options": [
      "a. NE monsoon in winter and SE tradewind in summer",
      "b. SW monsoon in winter and NE monsoon in summer",
      "c. NE tradewind in summer and SE tradewind in winter",
      "d. SW monsoon in summer and NE tradewind in winter"
    ],
    "answer": "c. NE tradewind in summer and SE tradewind in winter"
  },
  {
    "question": "949. Along the West coast of India the prevailing winds are the",
    "options": [
      "a. NE monsoon in July and a SW monsoon in January",
      "b. SW monsoon in July and a SE monsoon in January",
      "c. SW monsoon in July and a NE monsoon in January",
      "d. SE monsoon in July and a SW monsoon in January"
    ],
    "answer": "c. SW monsoon in July and a NE monsoon in January"
  },
  {
    "question": "950. To build a hurricane, the following conditions, among others, must be fulfilled:",
    "options": [
      "a. The surface temperature at least +27\u00b0C, and the building area 8 - 15\u00b0 away from the equator.",
      "b. Building area 5 - 6\u00b0 away from the equator.",
      "c. Building area in the equatorial area.",
      "d. The hurricane must be in the western areas of the ocean."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The surface temperature at least +27\u00b0C, and the building area 8 - 15\u00b0 away from the equator."
  },
  {
    "question": "951. Which is the greatest region of tropical revolving storms?",
    "options": [
      "a. The north-west Pacific, affecting Japan, Formosa, Korea and the Chinese coastline",
      "b. The Bermuda Triangle",
      "c. The Carribean Sea, affecting Florida and the Bahamas",
      "d. The Gulf of Mexico, affecting Texas, Louisiana and Florida"
    ],
    "answer": "a. The north-west Pacific, affecting Japan, Formosa, Korea and the Chinese coastline"
  },
  {
    "question": "952. What weather is prevalent in the zone of easterly waves?",
    "options": [
      "a. Thunderstorms and rain.",
      "b. Continuous rain.",
      "c. Clear skies.",
      "d. Frontal weather."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Thunderstorms and rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "953. An easterly wave is a",
    "options": [
      "a. wave in a trade wind belt, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity in rear of its trough",
      "b. wave-like disturbance in the monsoon regime of India, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity ahead of its trough",
      "c. small scale wave disturbance in the tropics, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity ahead of its trough",
      "d. disturbance in the higher levels associated with the equatorial easterly jet, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity in rear of its trough"
    ],
    "answer": "a. wave in a trade wind belt, moving from east to west, with severe convective activity in rear of its trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "954. Which typical weather condition is shown by the design for the area of Central Europe ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Westerly waves",
      "b. Uniform pressure pattern",
      "c. Cutting wind",
      "d. Easterly waves"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Westerly waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "955. Which typical weather condition is shown by the design for northern Italy?",
    "options": [
      "a. Westerly wind",
      "b. Warm southerly wind",
      "c. High pressure",
      "d. Easterly wind"
    ],
    "answer": "c. High pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "956. The attached chart shows the weather conditions on the ground at 1200 UTC on May 23. Which of the following reports reflects weather development at Zurich Airport?",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF LSZH 101601 05020G35KT 8000 BKN015 TEMPO 1720 05018KT 0300 +SHSN VV002 =",
      "b. TAF LSZH 101601 VRB02KT 8000 SCT280 BECMG 1618 00000KT 3500 MIFG BECMG 1820 1500 BCFG BECMG 2022 0100 FG VV001 =",
      "c. TAF LSZH 101601 23012KT 6000 RA BKN012 OVC030 TEMPO 2023 22025G40KT 1600 +SNRA BKN003 OVC015 =",
      "d. TAF LSZH 101601 32008KT 9999 SCT030TCU TEMPO 2201 32020G32KT 3000 TSRA BKN020CB ="
    ],
    "answer": "b. TAF LSZH 101601 VRB02KT 8000 SCT280 BECMG 1618 00000KT 3500 MIFG BECMG 1820 1500 BCFG BECMG 2022 0100 FG VV001 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "957. The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"R\" is",
    "options": [
      "a. early morning fog lifting to low stratus",
      "b. fine and warm with little or no cloud",
      "c. increasing high and medium cloud cover and generally good visibility",
      "d. mainly overcast with anticyclonic gloom"
    ],
    "answer": "b. fine and warm with little or no cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "958. Which typical weather situation is shown on the weather chart ? (spacing of the isobars: 5 hPa)",
    "options": [
      "a. Uniform pressure pattern.",
      "b. Cutting wind.",
      "c. West wind condition.",
      "d. Warm south wind condition (Foehn)."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Uniform pressure pattern."
  },
  {
    "question": "959. With a uniform pressure pattern and no thunderstorms around, what will the indication of the aneroid altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground do over a period of about ten minutes?",
    "options": [
      "a. Apparently nothing, because any changes would be small.",
      "b. Increase rapidly.",
      "c. Show strong fluctuations.",
      "d. Decrease rapidly."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Apparently nothing, because any changes would be small."
  },
  {
    "question": "960. A cold pool",
    "options": [
      "a. normally disappears at night and occurs almost exclusively in summer",
      "b. develops usually in winter when very unstable maritime polar or maritime arctic air currents stream southwards along the eastern side of an extensive ridge of high pressure, in association with occluded systems",
      "c. is usually most evident in the circulation and temperature fields of the middle troposphere and may show little or no sign on a surface chart",
      "d. occurs frequently in winter to the south of the Alps when this region is under the influence of cold north-westerly airstream"
    ],
    "answer": "c. is usually most evident in the circulation and temperature fields of the middle troposphere and may show little or no sign on a surface chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "961. What kind of weather conditions do you encounter in a cold air pool centre?",
    "options": [
      "a. Showers and thunderstorms",
      "b. Light drizzle",
      "c. Light rain",
      "d. Mostly clear skies"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Showers and thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "962. Which of the following zones is most likely to encounter little or no precipitation?",
    "options": [
      "a. The north side of the alps with a prevailing Foehn from the south.",
      "b. The north side of the alps with a prevailing Foehn from the north.",
      "c. Frontal zones.",
      "d. Occlusions."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The north side of the alps with a prevailing Foehn from the south."
  },
  {
    "question": "963. For an aircraft what are the meteorological dangers associated with a Harmattan wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. Sand up to FL 150.",
      "b. Thunderstorms.",
      "c. Dust and poor visibility.",
      "d. Hail."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Dust and poor visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "964. What is the strong relatively cold katabatic wind, blowing down the northern Adriatic coast, mainly during the winter and spring called?",
    "options": [
      "a. Mistral.",
      "b. Ghibli.",
      "c. Bora.",
      "d. Scirocco."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Bora."
  },
  {
    "question": "965. Which weather phenomena are typical for the northern side of the Alps with stormy winds from the south (Foehn)?",
    "options": [
      "a. Good visibility, turbulence.",
      "b. Continuous precipitation, severe turbulence.",
      "c. Decrease in temperature, moderate to severe icing.",
      "d. Icing, huge mass of clouds."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Good visibility, turbulence."
  },
  {
    "question": "966. What is characteristic of the pamperos?",
    "options": [
      "a. Foehn conditions in the Spanish Pyrenees",
      "b. Katabatic winds in the Atlas Mountains",
      "c. A marked advance of cold arctic air in North America",
      "d. A marked advance of cold air in South America"
    ],
    "answer": "d. A marked advance of cold air in South America"
  },
  {
    "question": "967. What weather conditions in the region of the Alps would you expect with Foehn from south?",
    "options": [
      "a. Heavy airframe icing conditions on the northern side of the Alps",
      "b. Heavy clear air turbulence on the southern side of the Alps",
      "c. Strong north winds on the southern side of the Alps",
      "d. Clouds, on the southern sides of passes in the Alps"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Clouds, on the southern sides of passes in the Alps"
  },
  {
    "question": "968. Under the weather conditions depicted, which of the following statements is likely to apply?",
    "options": [
      "a. Severe gradient wind likely over Central Europe.",
      "b. Thunderstorms may occur in the summer months over Central Europe.",
      "c. Moderate to strong Foehn in the Alps.",
      "d. Radiation fog is unlikely in Central Europe in the winter."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Thunderstorms may occur in the summer months over Central Europe."
  },
  {
    "question": "969. Considering the route indicates from Lisbon to Freetown, the Harmattan is a",
    "options": [
      "a. warm southerly dust-bearing wind affecting the coast of North Africa.",
      "b. SW monsoonal wind causing extensive areas of advection fog along the West African coast south of 15\u00b0N.",
      "c. NE wind affecting north-west Africa during November to April reducing visibility in rising dust.",
      "d. localised depression giving squally winds."
    ],
    "answer": "c. NE wind affecting north-west Africa during November to April reducing visibility in rising dust."
  },
  {
    "question": "970. The Foehn wind is a",
    "options": [
      "a. warm anabatic wind",
      "b. cold fall wind",
      "c. warm fall wind",
      "d. cold anabatic wind"
    ],
    "answer": "c. warm fall wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "971. The Chinook is a",
    "options": [
      "a. warm and dry wind that forms as air descends on the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains",
      "b. very cold wind with blowing snow",
      "c. downslope wind that occurs particularly at night as air cools along mountain slopes",
      "d. warm anabatic wind up the slopes of snowfields or glaciers"
    ],
    "answer": "a. warm and dry wind that forms as air descends on the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "972. A strong, dry and warm katabatic wind, produced by prior enforced ascent of air over hills or mountains is known as a",
    "options": [
      "a. Bora",
      "b. Harmattan",
      "c. Mistral",
      "d. Foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "973. A dry, sand- and dust-laden North Easterly wind that blows in winter over large parts of North West Africa is known as a",
    "options": [
      "a. Scirocco",
      "b. Harmattan",
      "c. Pampero",
      "d. Khamsin"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Harmattan"
  },
  {
    "question": "974. What is the name of the northerly, cold and strong wind, that sometimes blows over a certain part of Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Bora.",
      "b. Foehn.",
      "c. Mistral.",
      "d. Typhoon."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Mistral."
  },
  {
    "question": "975. What are the characteristics of the Bora ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is a warm and moist, southwesterly wind experienced in the eastern Mediterranean, that usually carries precipitation.",
      "b. It is a very cold wind that blows mainly in winter from a northwesterly direction in the Mediterranean",
      "c. It is a cold and very strong wind that blows mainly in winter from a tableland downwards to the Adriatic",
      "d. It is a dry and hot southerly wind experienced in the Sahara desert, that often carries dust."
    ],
    "answer": "c. It is a cold and very strong wind that blows mainly in winter from a tableland downwards to the Adriatic"
  },
  {
    "question": "976. What is the name of the hot, local wind, that blows downwards from mountain chains? In the Alps, for instance, it may exist both as a southerly or northerly wind depending on the weather situation.",
    "options": [
      "a. Foehn.",
      "b. Mistral.",
      "c. Bora.",
      "d. Scirocco."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Foehn."
  },
  {
    "question": "977. Which one of the following local winds is a Foehn wind?",
    "options": [
      "a. Harmattan",
      "b. Scirocco",
      "c. Chinook",
      "d. Bora"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Chinook"
  },
  {
    "question": "978. The Bora is a",
    "options": [
      "a. cold catabatic wind with gusts associated with a maritime air mass",
      "b. squally warm catabatic wind which occurs mainly in summer",
      "c. cold catabatic wind with the possibility of violent gusts",
      "d. cold catabatic wind always associated with clouds and heavy showers"
    ],
    "answer": "c. cold catabatic wind with the possibility of violent gusts"
  },
  {
    "question": "979. A Foehn wind occurs on the",
    "options": [
      "a. leeward side of a mountain range and is caused by the condensation level being lower on the leeward side than on the windward side",
      "b. windward side of a mountain range and is caused by surface heating",
      "c. windward side of a mountain range and is caused by surface cooling and reverse air flow",
      "d. leeward side of a mountain range and is caused by significant moisture loss by precipitation from cloud"
    ],
    "answer": "d. leeward side of a mountain range and is caused by significant moisture loss by precipitation from cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "980. Which of the following is a cold katabatic wind flowing towards the Adriatic Sea?",
    "options": [
      "a. Bora",
      "b. Scirocco",
      "c. Ghibli",
      "d. Mistral"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Bora"
  },
  {
    "question": "981. What typical weather do you encounter during foehn conditions north of the Alps?",
    "options": [
      "a. Good weather",
      "b. Turbulence during south foehn",
      "c. Heavy rain and NS clouds",
      "d. Icing"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Turbulence during south foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "982. What does this picture depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe",
      "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe",
      "c. South foehn",
      "d. North foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "c. South foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "983. What does this picture depict?",
    "options": [
      "a. A westerly wave over Central Europe",
      "b. A high pressure area over Central Europe",
      "c. South foehn",
      "d. North foehn"
    ],
    "answer": "d. North foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "984. What can be said about this weather situation?",
    "options": [
      "a. VFR flights over the Alps can easily be conducted",
      "b. The Alps are in clouds from the south",
      "c. Severe turbulence in the south and icing in the north can be encountered",
      "d. Very good VFR conditions prevail on the south side of the Alps"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The Alps are in clouds from the south"
  },
  {
    "question": "985. What can be said about this weather situation?",
    "options": [
      "a. VFR flights over the Alps can easily be conducted",
      "b. Precipitation can be expected north of the Alps",
      "c. The Alps are in clouds from the south",
      "d. Marginal VFR conditions prevail on the south side of the Alps"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Precipitation can be expected north of the Alps"
  },
  {
    "question": "986. Define the Chinook:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains",
      "b. Cold and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Appalachian Mountains",
      "c. A dust and sand laden northeasterly wind in Northwest Africa",
      "d. Warm and dry air ascending on the West Side of the Rocky Mountains"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Warm and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "987. Define the Foehn:",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Alps",
      "b. Cold and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Appalachian Mountains",
      "c. Strong, cold wind, mostly observed in the Rhone valley, blowing towards Southern France",
      "d. Warm and dry air ascending on the west side of the Alps"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Warm and dry air descending at the leeward side of the Alps"
  },
  {
    "question": "988. What is a dry, sand and dust-laden northeasterly wind in the winter in Northwest Africa?",
    "options": [
      "a. Harmattan",
      "b. Khamsin",
      "c. Scirocco",
      "d. Pampero"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Harmattan"
  },
  {
    "question": "989. You have been flying for some time in dense layered cloud. The outside air temperature is -25\u00b0C. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. If you do not have weather radar on board there is no need to worry, as CB is unlikely to form in such cloud",
      "b. Severe airframe icing is quite likely under these conditions",
      "c. Severe airframe icing is unlikely under these conditions",
      "d. In a dense layered cloud icing is unlikely also at an outside air temperature of -5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Severe airframe icing is unlikely under these conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "990. Atmospheric soundings give the following temperature profile : 3000 FT +15\u00b0C 6000 FT +8\u00b0C 10000 FT +1\u00b0C 14000 FT -6\u00b0C 18000 FT -14\u00b0C 24000 FT -26\u00b0C At which of the following flight levels is the risk for aircraft icing, in cloud, greatest?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 80",
      "b. FL 150",
      "c. FL 180",
      "d. FL 220"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 150"
  },
  {
    "question": "991. On the approach, the surface temperature is given as -5\u00b0C. The freezing level is at 3000 FT/AGL. At 4000 FT/AGL, there is a solid cloud layer from which rain is falling. According to the weather briefing, the clouds are due to an inversion caused by warm air sliding up and over an inclined front. Would you expect icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. Yes, between ground level and 3000 FT/AGL.",
      "b. Yes, but only between 3000 and 4000 FT/AGL.",
      "c. No, flights clear of cloud experience no icing.",
      "d. No, absolutely no icing will occur."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Yes, between ground level and 3000 FT/AGL."
  },
  {
    "question": "992. In which environment is aircraft structural ice most likely to have the highest rate of accretion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cirrus clouds.",
      "b. Freezing rain.",
      "c. Stratus clouds.",
      "d. Snow."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Freezing rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "993. In which of these temperature bands is ice most likely to form on the aircraft's surface?",
    "options": [
      "a. -20\u00b0C to -35\u00b0C",
      "b. +10\u00b0C to 0\u00b0C",
      "c. 0\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C",
      "d. -35\u00b0C to -50\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 0\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "994. Which of the following statements is true regarding moderate-to-severe airframe icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. It may occur in the uppermost levels of a cumulonimbus capillatus formation",
      "b. It will occur in clear-sky conditions",
      "c. It is likely to occur in nimbostratus cloud",
      "d. It always occurs in altostratus cloud"
    ],
    "answer": "c. It is likely to occur in nimbostratus cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "995. Which of the following statements is true regarding moderate-to-severe airframe icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. It may occur in the uppermost levels of a cumulonimbus capillatus formation",
      "b. It always occurs in altostratus cloud",
      "c. It is unlikely to occur in nimbostratus cloud",
      "d. It will not occur in clear-sky conditions"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It will not occur in clear-sky conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "996. In which of these cloud types can icing be virtually ruled out?",
    "options": [
      "a. CU",
      "b. SC",
      "c. NS",
      "d. CI"
    ],
    "answer": "d. CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "997. In which of these cloud types can icing be virtually ruled out?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. AS",
      "c. SC",
      "d. CS"
    ],
    "answer": "d. CS"
  },
  {
    "question": "998. Which of the following conditions is most likely to cause airframe icing ?",
    "options": [
      "a. PE",
      "b. GR",
      "c. SHSN",
      "d. +FZRA"
    ],
    "answer": "d. +FZRA"
  },
  {
    "question": "999. Continuous freezing rain is observed at an airfield. Which of the four diagrams is most likely to reflect temperatures above the airfield concerned?",
    "options": [
      "a. Diagram b)",
      "b. Diagram c)",
      "c. Diagram d)",
      "d. Diagram a)"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Diagram d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1000. In which of the following situations is an aircraft most susceptible to icing ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Level flight below a rain producing cloud when OAT is below zero degrees C.",
      "b. Flying in dense cirrus clouds.",
      "c. Level flight in snowfall below a nimbostratus layer.",
      "d. Flying in heavy drizzle."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Level flight below a rain producing cloud when OAT is below zero degrees C."
  },
  {
    "question": "1001. Which of the following cloud types are most likely to produce light to moderate icing when they are not subject to orographic lifting and consist of supercooled cloud droplets?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratocumulus and cirrostratus",
      "b. Altocumulus and altostratus.",
      "c. Stratus and cumulonimbus",
      "d. Altostratus and cirrocumulus"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Altocumulus and altostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "1002. A winter day in northern Europe with a thick layer of stratocumulus clouds and temperature close to zero degrees C at ground level, you can expect:",
    "options": [
      "a. Reduced visibility and light icing in clouds",
      "b. Decreasing visibility due to snowfall below cloud base, but only light icing in clouds.",
      "c. A high probability for icing in clouds. Severe icing in the upper part due to accumulation of large droplets.",
      "d. Turbulence due to a strong inversion, but no icing because clouds consist of ice crystals"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A high probability for icing in clouds. Severe icing in the upper part due to accumulation of large droplets."
  },
  {
    "question": "1003. Which one of the following statements concerning the formation of aircraft icing is most correct ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Risk for icing increases when cloud temperature decreases well below minus 12 degrees C.",
      "b. Greatest risk of icing conditions is experienced in cirrus clouds.",
      "c. A cloud consisting of both supercooled cloud droplets and ice crystals produces aircraft icing",
      "d. Probability of icing increases when dry snow starts to fall from a cloud."
    ],
    "answer": "c. A cloud consisting of both supercooled cloud droplets and ice crystals produces aircraft icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "1004. Which of the following factors have the greatest effect on the formation of the various types of ice on an aircraft ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Relative humidity inside the cloud",
      "b. Aircraft speed and size of cloud droplets",
      "c. Aircraft speed and curvature of the airfoil",
      "d. Cloud temperature and droplet size"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Cloud temperature and droplet size"
  },
  {
    "question": "1005. A vertical temperature profile indicates the possibility of severe icing when the temperature profile",
    "options": [
      "a. coincides with a dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "b. intersects the 0\u00b0C isotherm twice",
      "c. indicates temperatures below -40\u00b0C",
      "d. indicates temperatures above 3\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. intersects the 0\u00b0C isotherm twice"
  },
  {
    "question": "1006. Freezing fog exists if fog droplets",
    "options": [
      "a. are frozen",
      "b. are supercooled",
      "c. are freezing very rapidly",
      "d. freeze when temperature falls below zero"
    ],
    "answer": "b. are supercooled"
  },
  {
    "question": "1007. In which meteorological environment is aircraft structural icing most likely to have the highest rate of accumulation ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulonimbus clouds.",
      "b. High humidity and freezing temperature.",
      "c. Heavy wet snow.",
      "d. Freezing rain."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Freezing rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "1008. If you fly into rain which freezes on impact ?",
    "options": [
      "a. You have flown into an area of thunderstorms.",
      "b. Temperatures are above freezing at some higher altitude.",
      "c. You have flown through a cold front.",
      "d. If you descend, you will fly out of the icing condition."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Temperatures are above freezing at some higher altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "1009. Carburettor icing is unlikely:",
    "options": [
      "a. In clouds",
      "b. At temperatures between -10\u00b0C and -30\u00b0C",
      "c. When the relative humidity is 40%"
    ],
    "answer": "b. At temperatures between -10\u00b0C and -30\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1010. Airframe icing:",
    "options": [
      "a. Cannot occur outside cloud or precipitation",
      "b. Can occur outside cloud or precipitation",
      "c. Can only occur if the Outside Air Temperature (OAT) is below freezing",
      "d. Occurs only, when the temperature is below -15C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Can occur outside cloud or precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "1011. Observation: Surface temperature -5\u00b0C, FZLVL 3000 ft: The solid cloud deck at 4000 ft with RA is an inversion. Do you expect icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. Yes, between GND and 3000 ft AGL",
      "b. No",
      "c. Yes, at approx. 4000 ft",
      "d. Yes, between 3000 and approx. 8000 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Yes, between GND and 3000 ft AGL"
  },
  {
    "question": "1012. In which cloud type does moderate to severe airframe icing most probably occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. ST",
      "c. CS",
      "d. AC"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "1013. What can be said about supercooled water droplets?",
    "options": [
      "a. They remain liquid at a below-freezing temperature",
      "b. They don't contribute to clear ice",
      "c. They only occur in CB clouds",
      "d. They cool to a below-freezing temperature on impact"
    ],
    "answer": "a. They remain liquid at a below-freezing temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "1014. Which cloud type of the following is most prone to airframe icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. NS",
      "b. AS",
      "c. CC",
      "d. ST"
    ],
    "answer": "a. NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "1015. In which cloud type of the following does no airframe icing occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. CI",
      "b. NS",
      "c. CB",
      "d. AS"
    ],
    "answer": "a. CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "1016. What can be said if you encounter +FZRA during flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. Icing will most probably occur",
      "b. There is no significant icing to expect",
      "c. Freezing rain consists of water droplets which supercool to below-freezing temperatures on impact",
      "d. Only light rime ice has to be expected"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Icing will most probably occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "1017. In which temperature range does clear ice most commonly occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. -5\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C",
      "b. -10\u00b0C to -15\u00b0C",
      "c. below -15\u00b0C",
      "d. 0\u00b0C to -6\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 0\u00b0C to -6\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1018. In which temperature range does rime ice most commonly occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. -5\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C",
      "b. -10\u00b0C to -15\u00b0C",
      "c. around freezing level",
      "d. 0\u00b0C to -6\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -10\u00b0C to -15\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1019. In which temperature range does mixed ice most commonly occur?",
    "options": [
      "a. -5\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C",
      "b. -10\u00b0C to -15\u00b0C",
      "c. around freezing level",
      "d. 0\u00b0C to -6\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -5\u00b0C to -10\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1020. Rime ice forms through the freezing onto aircraft surfaces of",
    "options": [
      "a. water vapour.",
      "b. large supercooled water drops.",
      "c. small supercooled water drops.",
      "d. snow."
    ],
    "answer": "c. small supercooled water drops."
  },
  {
    "question": "1021. Under which conditions would you expect the heaviest clear ice accretion to occur in a CB?",
    "options": [
      "a. Close to the freezing level",
      "b. Between -20\u00b0C and -30\u00b0C",
      "c. Between -2\u00b0C and -15\u00b0C",
      "d. Between -30\u00b0C and -40\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Between -2\u00b0C and -15\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1022. Clear ice forms on an aircraft by the freezing of :",
    "options": [
      "a. water vapour",
      "b. large supercooled water drops",
      "c. small supercooled water drops",
      "d. snow"
    ],
    "answer": "b. large supercooled water drops"
  },
  {
    "question": "1023. Hoar frost is most likely to form when",
    "options": [
      "a. flying inside convective clouds.",
      "b. taking off from an airfield with a significant ground inversion.",
      "c. flying inside stratiform clouds.",
      "d. flying in supercooled drizzle."
    ],
    "answer": "b. taking off from an airfield with a significant ground inversion."
  },
  {
    "question": "1024. While descending through a cloud cover at high level, a small amount of a white and rough powderlike contamination is detected along the leading edge of the wing. This contamination is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Clear ice.",
      "b. Rime ice.",
      "c. Mixed ice.",
      "d. Frost."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Rime ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "1025. A small supercooled cloud droplet that collides with an airfoil will most likely",
    "options": [
      "a. freeze immediately and create rime ice.",
      "b. freeze immediately and create clear ice.",
      "c. travel back over the wing, creating rime ice.",
      "d. travel back over the wing, creating clear ice."
    ],
    "answer": "a. freeze immediately and create rime ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "1026. Glaze or clear ice is formed when supercooled droplets are",
    "options": [
      "a. small and at a temperature just below freezing",
      "b. large and at a temperature just below freezing",
      "c. small and freeze rapidly",
      "d. of any size at temperatures below -35\u00b0C."
    ],
    "answer": "b. large and at a temperature just below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "1027. Clear ice is dangerous because it",
    "options": [
      "a. spreads out and contains many air particles",
      "b. is translucent and only forms at the leading edges",
      "c. is not translucent and forms at the leading edges",
      "d. is heavy and is difficult to remove from the aircraft surfaces"
    ],
    "answer": "d. is heavy and is difficult to remove from the aircraft surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "1028. During the formation of rime ice in flight, water droplets freeze",
    "options": [
      "a. rapidly and do not spread out",
      "b. slowly and do not spread out",
      "c. slowly and spread out",
      "d. rapidly and spread out"
    ],
    "answer": "a. rapidly and do not spread out"
  },
  {
    "question": "1029. Hoar frost forms on an aircraft as a result of",
    "options": [
      "a. water vapour turning directly into ice crystals on the aircraft surface",
      "b. freezing rain striking the aircraft",
      "c. droplets forming on the aircraft and then freezing",
      "d. small super-cooled droplets striking the aircraft"
    ],
    "answer": "a. water vapour turning directly into ice crystals on the aircraft surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "1030. Clear ice forms as a result of",
    "options": [
      "a. supercooled water droplets spreading during the freezing process",
      "b. water vapour freezing to the aircraft",
      "c. ice pellets splattering on the aircraft",
      "d. supercooled droplets freezing on impact"
    ],
    "answer": "a. supercooled water droplets spreading during the freezing process"
  },
  {
    "question": "1031. Large supercooled water drops, which freeze on impact on an airplane, form",
    "options": [
      "a. rime ice",
      "b. clear ice",
      "c. hoar frost",
      "d. cloudy ice"
    ],
    "answer": "b. clear ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "1032. The type of icing that occurs in dense clouds with large supercooled drops that have a temperature of -5\u00b0C is most likely to be",
    "options": [
      "a. clear ice",
      "b. hoar frost",
      "c. rime ice",
      "d. cloudy ice"
    ],
    "answer": "a. clear ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "1033. Clear ice is most often experienced, when the outside temperature is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 0\u00b0 to minus 20\u00b0 C.",
      "b. Minus 5\u00b0 to minus 10\u00b0.",
      "c. Minus 5\u00b0 to plus 5\u00b0.",
      "d. 0\u00b0 to minus 5\u00b0 C."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 0\u00b0 to minus 5\u00b0 C."
  },
  {
    "question": "1034. While forming rime ice in flight, water droplets freeze........",
    "options": [
      "a. rapidly and do not spread out",
      "b. rapidly and spread out extensively",
      "c. slowly and do not spread out",
      "d. on impact, at temperatures near the freezing level"
    ],
    "answer": "a. rapidly and do not spread out"
  },
  {
    "question": "1035. While forming clear ice in flight, water droplets freeze........",
    "options": [
      "a. rapidly and do not spread out",
      "b. and spread out extensively",
      "c. slowly and do not spread out",
      "d. on impact, at temperatures lower than -10\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. and spread out extensively"
  },
  {
    "question": "1036. When is clear ice formed?",
    "options": [
      "a. When supercooled droplets are large and at a temperature just below freezing",
      "b. When supercooled droplets freeze rapidly and do not spread out",
      "c. When supercooled droplets are small and at a temperature just below freezing",
      "d. When supercooled droplets impact the structure and at a temperature well below -10\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. When supercooled droplets are large and at a temperature just below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "1037. Which airframe icing is the most dangerous?",
    "options": [
      "a. Clear ice",
      "b. Rime ice",
      "c. Hoar frost",
      "d. Mixed ice"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Clear ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "1038. How does a pilot react to heavy freezing rain at 2000 FT/AGL, when he is unable to deice, nor land?",
    "options": [
      "a. He turns back before the aircraft loses manoeuvrability.",
      "b. He descends to the warm air layer below.",
      "c. He ascends to the cold air layer above.",
      "d. He continues to fly at the same altitude."
    ],
    "answer": "a. He turns back before the aircraft loses manoeuvrability."
  },
  {
    "question": "1039. The most dangerous form of airframe icing is",
    "options": [
      "a. rime ice.",
      "b. hoar frost.",
      "c. dry ice.",
      "d. clear ice."
    ],
    "answer": "d. clear ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "1040. At what degree of icing should ICAO's \"Change of course and/or altitude desirable\" recommendation be followed?",
    "options": [
      "a. Light",
      "b. Moderate",
      "c. Severe",
      "d. Extreme"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "1041. At what degree of icing should ICAO's \"Change course and/or altitude immediately\" instruction be followed?",
    "options": [
      "a. Light",
      "b. Severe",
      "c. Moderate",
      "d. Extreme"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "1042. At what degree of icing can ICAO's \"No change of course and altitude necessary\" recommendation be followed?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moderate",
      "b. Light",
      "c. Severe",
      "d. Extreme"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Light"
  },
  {
    "question": "1043. Two aircraft, one with a sharp wing profile (S), and the other with a thick profile (T), are flying through the same cloud with same true airspeed. The cloud consists of small supercooled droplets. Which of the following statements is most correct concerning ice accretion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Aircraft T experiences more icing than S.",
      "b. Aircraft S experiences more icing than T.",
      "c. Aircraft S and T experience the same amount of icing",
      "d. Neither of the aircraft accumulate ice due to the small size of droplets."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Aircraft S experiences more icing than T."
  },
  {
    "question": "1044. Why is frost considered hazardous to flight ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The increased weight requires a greater takeoff distance.",
      "b. Frost changes the basic aerodynamic shape of the airfoil.",
      "c. Frost decreases control effectiveness.",
      "d. Frost causes early airflow separation resulting in a loss of lift."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Frost causes early airflow separation resulting in a loss of lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "1045. The possibility of significant icing at altitude, should be expected when on ground you observe:",
    "options": [
      "a. Ice grains.",
      "b. Hail.",
      "c. Snow.",
      "d. Corn-snow."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ice grains."
  },
  {
    "question": "1046. How does moderate turbulence affect an aircraft?",
    "options": [
      "a. Large, abrupt changes in altitude or attitude occur but the aircraft may only be out of control momentarily.",
      "b. Rapid and somewhat rhythmic bumpiness is experienced without appreciable changes in altitude or attitude.",
      "c. Changes in altitude or attitude occur but the aircraft remains in positive control at all times.",
      "d. Continued flight in this environment will result in structural damage."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Changes in altitude or attitude occur but the aircraft remains in positive control at all times."
  },
  {
    "question": "1047. A zone of strong convection currents is encountered during a flight. In spite of moderate gust you decide to continue the flight. What are your precautionary measures?",
    "options": [
      "a. Increase the speed / try to descend below the zone of convective currents.",
      "b. Increase the speed / try to climb above the zone of convective currents, if aircraft performance parameters allow.",
      "c. Decrease the speed / try to descend below the zone of convective currents.",
      "d. Decrease the speed / try to climb above the zone of convective currents if aircraft performance parameters allow."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Decrease the speed / try to climb above the zone of convective currents if aircraft performance parameters allow."
  },
  {
    "question": "1048. What is normally the most effective measure to reduce or avoid CAT effects?",
    "options": [
      "a. Decrease of speed.",
      "b. Change of course.",
      "c. Increase of speed.",
      "d. Change of flight level."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Change of flight level."
  },
  {
    "question": "1049. An aircraft is approaching a cold front from the warm air mass side at FL 270 and experiencing moderate to severe turbulence. A jet stream is forecast to be at FL 310. The shortest way to get out of this turbulence is by :",
    "options": [
      "a. Climbing",
      "b. Descending",
      "c. Turn right",
      "d. Maintain FL 270"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Descending"
  },
  {
    "question": "1050. A flight is to depart from an airport with runways 09 and 27. Surface wind is 270/05; an inversion is reported at 300 feet with turbulence and wind shear. The wind just above the inversion is 090/30. What is the safest departure procedure ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Depart runway 27 with as steep an ascent as possible.",
      "b. Depart runway 27 with maximum throttle during the passage through the inversion.",
      "c. Depart on runway 09 with a tailwind.",
      "d. Take-off is not possible under these conditions."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Depart on runway 09 with a tailwind."
  },
  {
    "question": "1051. Wake turbulence is created by:",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulonimbus clouds.",
      "b. Behind high buildings less than 300 m from the runway.",
      "c. Wind forces greater than 50 kts.",
      "d. The wingtips of heavy aircraft during takeoff and landing."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The wingtips of heavy aircraft during takeoff and landing."
  },
  {
    "question": "1052. The degree of clear air turbulence experiencied by an aircraft is proportional to the",
    "options": [
      "a. intensity of the solar radiation",
      "b. height of the aircraft",
      "c. stability of the air",
      "d. intensity of vertical and horizontal windshear"
    ],
    "answer": "d. intensity of vertical and horizontal windshear"
  },
  {
    "question": "1053. The turbulence which occurs at high flight levels (above FL 250) is mainly of the type Clear Air Turbulence. In what way can moderate to severe clear air turbulence affect an aircraft, the flight and the passengers?",
    "options": [
      "a. The turbulence is a small scale one and can cause damage of worn out type. The manoeuvring of the aircraft will be made more difficult or even impossible. For the passengers the flight will be inpleasant.",
      "b. The turbulence is a large scale one (waving) so that the aircraft will be difficult to manoeuvre. The passengers will feel some discomfort.",
      "c. The turbulence can be resembled with the roughness of a washing-board (small scale) and will not have influence on the aircraft and its solidity, but will make flight a little more difficult. The passengers will seldom notice anything of this turbulence.",
      "d. The turbulence is wave like which makes the flight unpleasent for the passengers but the manoeuvring will not be affected essentially."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The turbulence is a small scale one and can cause damage of worn out type. The manoeuvring of the aircraft will be made more difficult or even impossible. For the passengers the flight will be inpleasant."
  },
  {
    "question": "1054. Clear air turbulence (CAT) should be anticipated when:",
    "options": [
      "a. Immediately after the passage of a thunderstorm.",
      "b. A sharp trough area aloft is present with wind speed considerably higher than that of jetstream winds.",
      "c. A sharp trough area aloft is present, even though the wind speeds may be considerably less than that of jetstream winds.",
      "d. Whenever a high pressure is present close to a thunderstorm area."
    ],
    "answer": "c. A sharp trough area aloft is present, even though the wind speeds may be considerably less than that of jetstream winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "1055. What is the effect of a strong low level inversion ?",
    "options": [
      "a. It results in good visual conditions.",
      "b. It promotes extensive vertical movement of air.",
      "c. It prevents vertical windshear.",
      "d. It promotes vertical windshear."
    ],
    "answer": "d. It promotes vertical windshear."
  },
  {
    "question": "1056. Low level wind shear is likely to be greatest",
    "options": [
      "a. at the condensation level when there is strong surface friction.",
      "b. at the condensation level when there is no night radiation.",
      "c. at the top of a marked surface-based inversion.",
      "d. at the top of the friction layer."
    ],
    "answer": "c. at the top of a marked surface-based inversion."
  },
  {
    "question": "1057. Vertical wind shear is",
    "options": [
      "a. horizontal variation in the horizontal wind",
      "b. vertical variation in the vertical wind",
      "c. vertical variation in the horizontal wind",
      "d. horizontal variation in the vertical wind"
    ],
    "answer": "c. vertical variation in the horizontal wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "1058. What is meant by the expression \"windshear\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. A change of wind- direction and/or speed in horizontal and/or vertical direction.",
      "b. Whirlwind.",
      "c. The retardation of wind at the friction layer.",
      "d. Interference when to wind streams meet."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A change of wind- direction and/or speed in horizontal and/or vertical direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "1059. Low level vertical wind shear can be expected during the night",
    "options": [
      "a. and early morning only in summer",
      "b. in unstable atmospheres",
      "c. and early morning only in winter",
      "d. in association with radiation inversions"
    ],
    "answer": "d. in association with radiation inversions"
  },
  {
    "question": "1060. The most dangerous low level wind shears are encountered",
    "options": [
      "a. when strong ground inversions are present and near thunderstorms",
      "b. in areas with layered clouds and wind speeds higher than 35 kts",
      "c. during any period when wind speed is greater than 35 kt and near valleys",
      "d. near valleys and at the windward side of mountains."
    ],
    "answer": "a. when strong ground inversions are present and near thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1061. Above and below a low level inversion the wind is likely to",
    "options": [
      "a. experience little or no change in speed and direction",
      "b. change in speed but not in direction",
      "c. change in direction but not in speed",
      "d. change significantly in speed and direction"
    ],
    "answer": "d. change significantly in speed and direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "1062. Where is a squall line to be expected?",
    "options": [
      "a. At the surface position of a warm front.",
      "b. Behind a cold front.",
      "c. In front of a cold front occlusion at higher levels.",
      "d. In front of an active cold front."
    ],
    "answer": "d. In front of an active cold front."
  },
  {
    "question": "1063. What are squall lines?",
    "options": [
      "a. Unusual intensive cold fronts.",
      "b. Bands of intensive thunderstorms.",
      "c. The surface weather associated with upper air troughs.",
      "d. The paths of tropical revolving storms."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Bands of intensive thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "1064. What weather condition would you expect at a squall line?",
    "options": [
      "a. Strong steady rain",
      "b. Thunderstorms",
      "c. Fog",
      "d. Strong whirlwinds reaching up to higher levels"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1065. At which altitude, at temperate latitudes, may hail be expected in connection with a CB?",
    "options": [
      "a. From the ground up to a maximum of FL 450.",
      "b. From the ground up to about FL 200.",
      "c. From the ground up to about FL 100.",
      "d. From the base of the clouds up to FL 200."
    ],
    "answer": "a. From the ground up to a maximum of FL 450."
  },
  {
    "question": "1066. A squall line usually is most likely to be encountered",
    "options": [
      "a. at an occluded front",
      "b. ahead of a cold front",
      "c. in an airmass with cold mass properties",
      "d. behind a stationary front"
    ],
    "answer": "b. ahead of a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "1067. During the life cycle of a thunderstorm, which stage is characterized predominantly by downdrafts?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dissipating stage",
      "b. Cumulus stage",
      "c. Mature stage",
      "d. Anvil stage"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Dissipating stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "1068. What feature is normally associated with the cumulus stage of a thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Frequent lightning",
      "b. Roll cloud",
      "c. Continuous updraft",
      "d. Rain or hail at the surface"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Continuous updraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "1069. A gustfront is",
    "options": [
      "a. normally encountered directly below a thunderstorm",
      "b. formed by the cold air outflow from a thunderstorm",
      "c. characterized by heavy lightning",
      "d. another name for a cold front"
    ],
    "answer": "b. formed by the cold air outflow from a thunderstorm"
  },
  {
    "question": "1070. In which stage of the life cycle of a single thunderstorm cell occur both up- and downdrafts simultaneously?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dissipating stage",
      "b. Cumulus stage",
      "c. Mature stage",
      "d. In all stages"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Mature stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "1071. Which thunderstorms generally produce the most severe conditions, such as heavy hail and destructive winds ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Warm front.",
      "b. Squall line.",
      "c. Air mass.",
      "d. Cold front."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Squall line."
  },
  {
    "question": "1072. Where can wind shear associated with a thunderstorm be found ? (Choose the most complete answer.)",
    "options": [
      "a. In front of the thunderstorm cell (anvil side).",
      "b. Ahead of the roll clouds or gust front.",
      "c. In front of the thunderstorm cell and directly under the cell.",
      "d. On all sides of the thunderstorm cell and directly under the cell."
    ],
    "answer": "d. On all sides of the thunderstorm cell and directly under the cell."
  },
  {
    "question": "1073. Between the external appearance of a severe thunderstorm and the turbulence and hail that are contained within it, there is:",
    "options": [
      "a. A strong correlation.",
      "b. Apparently no correlation.",
      "c. A moderate correlation.",
      "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Apparently no correlation."
  },
  {
    "question": "1074. Which type of clouds are associated with \"Microburst\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stratus (st).",
      "b. Altocumulus (ac).",
      "c. Cumulonimbus (cb).",
      "d. Cumulus (cu)."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Cumulonimbus (cb)."
  },
  {
    "question": "1075. In a microburst you may experience strong wind shear, the horizontal extension of this area being:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1 - 3 km.",
      "b. 8 km.",
      "c. 10 km.",
      "d. 15 km."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1 - 3 km."
  },
  {
    "question": "1076. Which of the following weather factors will not cause the formation of thunderstorms?",
    "options": [
      "a. An occlusion.",
      "b. A warm front.",
      "c. A cold front.",
      "d. Sea fog."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Sea fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "1077. What is a squall line?",
    "options": [
      "a. A band of intense thunderstorms",
      "b. A band of cumulus clouds",
      "c. Extended areas of nimbostratus clouds",
      "d. Fog patches ahead of a warm front"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A band of intense thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1078. What is the location of a squall line?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ahead of a cold front",
      "b. Ahead of a warm front",
      "c. Between cold and warm front",
      "d. On the rear side of a frontal system"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ahead of a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "1079. Which statement is true with regard to a thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Updrafts in CU clouds, up- and downdrafts as well as downdrafts only in the CB (mature and dissipating stage)",
      "b. Up- and downdrafts can occur in CU and CB clouds",
      "c. Only downdrafts may be expected in the mature and dissipating stage (CB) of a thunderstorm",
      "d. Hail must be expected in all stages"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Updrafts in CU clouds, up- and downdrafts as well as downdrafts only in the CB (mature and dissipating stage)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1080. What is a microburst?",
    "options": [
      "a. A downdraught of a CB in the mature stage",
      "b. A downdraught, occurring when a warm front passes by",
      "c. Severe windshear, caused by a low level jet stream",
      "d. Up- and downdraughts during a thunderstorm"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A downdraught of a CB in the mature stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "1081. What is the size of a microburst?",
    "options": [
      "a. Approximately 4 kms in diameter",
      "b. Approximately 200 metres in diameter",
      "c. A widespread area of approximately 10 kms",
      "d. A small, clearly defined area of about 50 metres in diameter"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Approximately 4 kms in diameter"
  },
  {
    "question": "1082. Describe the microburst:",
    "options": [
      "a. A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings",
      "b. Sinking air of higher temperature than its surroundings",
      "c. Precipitation at the base of a cumulonimbus cloud",
      "d. Horizontal movement of air, generally colder than its surroundings"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "1083. What is true about thunderstorms?",
    "options": [
      "a. They occur at cold fronts only",
      "b. They only occur, when a cold front occlusion is present",
      "c. They can exceptionally occur at a warm front, when warm air is unstable",
      "d. They occur only in the summertime"
    ],
    "answer": "c. They can exceptionally occur at a warm front, when warm air is unstable"
  },
  {
    "question": "1084. In Central Europe when is the greatest likelihood for thunderstorms due to warm updrafts?",
    "options": [
      "a. Mid - afternoon.",
      "b. Around midnight.",
      "c. Early morning.",
      "d. Late morning."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Mid - afternoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "1085. During which stage of thunderstorm development are rotor winds characterized by roll clouds most likely to occur ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Dissipating stage.",
      "b. Cumulus stage.",
      "c. Mature stage.",
      "d. Cumulus stage and mature stage."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "1086. What are the meteorological prerequisites, at low level, for thunderstorms formed by lifting processes, over land?",
    "options": [
      "a. Low temperatures, low humidity.",
      "b. High air pressure (> 1013 hPa), high temperatures.",
      "c. High temperatures, high humidity.",
      "d. Subsidence, inversion."
    ],
    "answer": "c. High temperatures, high humidity."
  },
  {
    "question": "1087. Which of the following meteorological phenomenon indicates upper level instability which may lead to thunderstorm development ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Red cirrus.",
      "b. AC lenticularis.",
      "c. Halo.",
      "d. AC castellanus."
    ],
    "answer": "d. AC castellanus."
  },
  {
    "question": "1088. Isolated thunderstorms of a local nature are generally caused by",
    "options": [
      "a. frontal lifting (warm front).",
      "b. thermal triggering.",
      "c. frontal lifting (cold front).",
      "d. frontal occlusion."
    ],
    "answer": "b. thermal triggering."
  },
  {
    "question": "1089. Which thunderstorms move forward the fastest?",
    "options": [
      "a. Thunderstorms formed by lifting processes.",
      "b. Frontal thunderstorms.",
      "c. Thermal thunderstorms.",
      "d. Orographic thunderstorms."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Frontal thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "1090. The initial phase of a thunderstorm is characterized by",
    "options": [
      "a. rain starting at surface",
      "b. continuous downdraughts",
      "c. frequent lightning",
      "d. continuous updraughts"
    ],
    "answer": "d. continuous updraughts"
  },
  {
    "question": "1091. In addition to a lifting action, what are two other conditions necessary for thunderstorm formation ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Stable conditions and high moisture content",
      "b. Unstable conditions and high moisture content",
      "c. Stable conditions and low atmospheric pressure",
      "d. Unstable conditions and low atmospheric pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Unstable conditions and high moisture content"
  },
  {
    "question": "1092. Continuous updraughts occur in a thunderstorm during the",
    "options": [
      "a. dissipating stage.",
      "b. mature stage.",
      "c. cumulus stage.",
      "d. period in which precipitation is falling."
    ],
    "answer": "c. cumulus stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "1093. Thunderstorms reach their greatest intensity during the",
    "options": [
      "a. dissipating stage.",
      "b. cumulus stage.",
      "c. mature stage.",
      "d. period in which precipitation is not falling."
    ],
    "answer": "c. mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "1094. What are the requirements for the formation of a thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Water vapour and high pressure",
      "b. An adequate supply of moisture, conditional instability and a lifting action",
      "c. A stratocumulus cloud with sufficient moisture",
      "d. A cumulus cloud with sufficient moisture associated with an inversion"
    ],
    "answer": "b. An adequate supply of moisture, conditional instability and a lifting action"
  },
  {
    "question": "1095. Which thunderstorms generally develop in the afternoon in summer over land in moderate latitudes?",
    "options": [
      "a. Occlusion thunderstorms",
      "b. Warm front thunderstorms",
      "c. Cold mass thunderstorms",
      "d. Airmass thunderstorms"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Airmass thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1096. In which of the following areas is the highest frequency of thunderstorms encountered ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Tropical",
      "b. Polar",
      "c. Subtropical",
      "d. Temperate"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "1097. Thunderstorms can occur on a warm front if the",
    "options": [
      "a. warm air is moist and the environmental lapse rate exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate",
      "b. cold air is moist and the environmental lapse rate is less than the dry adiabatic lapse rate",
      "c. warm air is moist and the environmental lapse rate is less than the saturated adiabatic lapse rate",
      "d. cold air is moist and the environmental lapse rate exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate"
    ],
    "answer": "a. warm air is moist and the environmental lapse rate exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "1098. What are the requirements for the formation of a thunderstorm ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Sufficient water vapor and a lifting action.",
      "b. A cumulus cloud with sufficient moisture.",
      "c. A cumulus cloud with sufficient moisture and an inverted lapse rate.",
      "d. Sufficient moisture, an unstable lapse rate, and a lifting action."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Sufficient moisture, an unstable lapse rate, and a lifting action."
  },
  {
    "question": "1099. During the life cycle of a thunderstorm, which stage is characterized predominately by downdrafts ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulus.",
      "b. Dissipating.",
      "c. Mature.",
      "d. Anvil."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Dissipating."
  },
  {
    "question": "1100. Which weather phenomenon signals the beginning of the mature stage of a thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. The start of rain at the surface.",
      "b. Growth rate cloud is maximum.",
      "c. Strong turbulence in the cloud.",
      "d. The appearance of an anvil top."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The start of rain at the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "1101. Which weather phenomenon signals the beginning of the mature stage of a thunderstorm:",
    "options": [
      "a. The appearance of an anvil top",
      "b. Growth rate of cloud is maximum",
      "c. The start of precipitation"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The start of precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "1102. Which of the following are not essential factors for thunderstorm development?",
    "options": [
      "a. High temperature",
      "b. An unstable atmosphere",
      "c. A supply of moist air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. High temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "1103. In which stage do rotor winds and roll clouds occur in a strong thunderstorm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Mature stage",
      "b. Dissipating stage",
      "c. Cumulus stage",
      "d. Rain stage"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Mature stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "1104. What type of thunderstorms develop in the afternoon in summer over land in moderate latitudes?",
    "options": [
      "a. Airmass thunderstorms",
      "b. Cold mass thunderstorms",
      "c. Warm front thunderstorms",
      "d. Occlusion thunderstorms"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Airmass thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1105. Which air mass can be related to thunderstorms during summer in Central Europe?",
    "options": [
      "a. Maritime tropical air",
      "b. Maritime polar air",
      "c. Continental tropical air",
      "d. Continental equatorial air"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Maritime tropical air"
  },
  {
    "question": "1106. What conditions (amongst others) have to be met for the development of CBs and thunderstorms?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moist air must be present",
      "b. Warm air has to move over a cold surface",
      "c. There have to be significant pressure differences over a small area",
      "d. A front has to be present"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Moist air must be present"
  },
  {
    "question": "1107. The most hazardous type of cloud that may be encountered on a cross country flight is",
    "options": [
      "a. cirrus",
      "b. stratocumulus",
      "c. cumulus",
      "d. cumulonimbus"
    ],
    "answer": "d. cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "1108. Concerning the radar reflectivity in relation to a thunderstorm, the following is true:",
    "options": [
      "a. Reflectivity decreases with severity and frequency of turbulence.",
      "b. Reflectivity increases with severity and frequency of turbulence.",
      "c. Reflectivity is a function of the number and size of water droplets in a given unit of volume",
      "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Both b) and c) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "1109. In a thunderstorm pilots should be on alert for hail when radar echoes:",
    "options": [
      "a. show turbulence.",
      "b. are well defined.",
      "c. are ill-defined.",
      "d. None of the above is correct."
    ],
    "answer": "b. are well defined."
  },
  {
    "question": "1110. The hazards that thunderstorms pose to aviation include:",
    "options": [
      "a. Windshear, severe turbulence, hail",
      "b. Heavy precipitation, lightning, severe icing",
      "c. All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "c. All of the above"
  },
  {
    "question": "1111. What is the approximate maximum diameter of a microburst ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 20 km",
      "b. 400 m",
      "c. 4 km",
      "d. 50 km"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "1112. What is a microburst?",
    "options": [
      "a. A small low pressure system where the wind circulates with very high speeds.",
      "b. A concentrated downdraft with high speeds and a higher temperature than the surrounding air.",
      "c. An extremely strong wind gust in a tropical revolving storm.",
      "d. A concentrated downdraft with high speeds and a lower temperature than the surrounding air."
    ],
    "answer": "d. A concentrated downdraft with high speeds and a lower temperature than the surrounding air."
  },
  {
    "question": "1113. How long does a typical microburst last?",
    "options": [
      "a. About 30 minutes.",
      "b. Less than 1 minute.",
      "c. 1 to 2 hours.",
      "d. 1 to 5 minutes."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 1 to 5 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "1114. A microburst phenomenon can arise in the",
    "options": [
      "a. downdraught of a cumulonimbus at the mature stage.",
      "b. updraught of a cumulonimbus at the mature stage.",
      "c. downdraught of a cumulonimbus at the formation stage.",
      "d. updraught of a cumulonimbus at the growth stage."
    ],
    "answer": "a. downdraught of a cumulonimbus at the mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "1115. A microburst",
    "options": [
      "a. is always associated with thunderstorms",
      "b. has a life time of more than 30 minutes",
      "c. has a diameter up to 4 km",
      "d. occurs only in tropical areas"
    ],
    "answer": "c. has a diameter up to 4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "1116. Which of the following statements describes a microburst ?",
    "options": [
      "a. A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings",
      "b. A high speed downdraft of air with a higher temperature than its surroundings",
      "c. An extremely strong wind gust associated with a tropical revolving storm",
      "d. A small low pressure system where the wind circulates at high speed"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "1117. The diameter and the life time of a typical microburst are in the order of",
    "options": [
      "a. 8 km and 5-15 minutes",
      "b. 4 km and 30-40 minutes",
      "c. 4 km and 1-5 minutes",
      "d. 12 km and 5-10 minutes"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 4 km and 1-5 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "1118. Aircraft struck by lightning may sometimes get considerable damage and at least temporarily the manoeuvring of the aircraft will be made more difficult. Which one of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "a. An aircraft has in the atmosphere the same qualities as a \"Faradays cage\", which means that struck of lightning seldom occurs. But if it happens, the result will be an occasional engine failure. The crew may get a shock.",
      "b. An aircraft made by metal has a certain capacity to attract a lightning, but the lightning will follow the surface and therefore no damage will be caused.",
      "c. Aircraft made by composite material may get severe damage, the crew may be blinded and temporarily lose the hearing.",
      "d. Aircraft made by composite material can't conduct a lightning and will therefore very seldom be struck."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Aircraft made by composite material may get severe damage, the crew may be blinded and temporarily lose the hearing."
  },
  {
    "question": "1119. At what time of the year are tornadoes most likely to occur in North America?",
    "options": [
      "a. Spring, summer.",
      "b. Summer, autumn.",
      "c. Autumn, winter.",
      "d. Winter."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Spring, summer."
  },
  {
    "question": "1120. With which type of cloud are tornadoes normally associated ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Cumulonimbus",
      "b. Cumulus",
      "c. Stratus",
      "d. Nimbostratus"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "1121. The diameter of a typical tornado is",
    "options": [
      "a. only a few metres",
      "b. 100 to 150 metres",
      "c. about 2 to 6 km",
      "d. in the order of 10 km"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 100 to 150 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "1122. A wide body takes off on a clear night in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. Shortly after take off the aircraft's rate of climb drops to zero. This can be due to",
    "options": [
      "a. a very strong temperature inversion",
      "b. sand/dust in the engines",
      "c. very pronounced downdrafts",
      "d. low relative humidity"
    ],
    "answer": "a. a very strong temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "1123. Which of the following phenomena are formed when a moist, stable layer of air is forced to rise against a mountain range ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Inversions",
      "b. Stratified clouds",
      "c. Showers and thunderstorms",
      "d. Areas of severe turbulence"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Stratified clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "1124. You are flying with an outside air temperature of -12\u00b0C and a TAS of 250 kt at FL 150 through 8 octas NS. What type and degree of icing is most probable?",
    "options": [
      "a. In clouds pushed up against the mountains, moderate to severe rime ice.",
      "b. In clouds pushed up against the mountains, moderate to severe mixed ice.",
      "c. Over flat terrain, away from fronts, moderate to severe mixed ice.",
      "d. Over flat terrain, moderate hoar frost."
    ],
    "answer": "b. In clouds pushed up against the mountains, moderate to severe mixed ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "1125. You intend to carry out a VFR flight over the Alps, on a hot summer day, when the weather is unstable. What is the best time of day to conduct this flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. Morning.",
      "b. Mid-day.",
      "c. Afternoon.",
      "d. Early evening."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Morning."
  },
  {
    "question": "1126. CAP clouds are one three groups of mountain wave clouds.",
    "options": [
      "a. They appear to be harmless.",
      "b. Downdrafts as great as 5000 feet per minute can be expected on the leeward side.",
      "c. They cool adiabatically and therefore evaporate.",
      "d. Both a) and b) are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Both a) and b) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "1127. Mention 3 types of weather phenomena associated with mountain waves:",
    "options": [
      "a. Rotor , cap and lenticular clouds.",
      "b. Fog, lenticular and medium height clouds.",
      "c. Low clouds, downdrafts and thunderstorms.",
      "d. Turbulence, advection and convection clouds."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Rotor , cap and lenticular clouds."
  },
  {
    "question": "1128. Should a mountain wave situation occur without creating mountain wave clouds, this would indicate:",
    "options": [
      "a. Stable air mass.",
      "b. Too strong winds.",
      "c. Too dry air.",
      "d. Too strong turbulence."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Too dry air."
  },
  {
    "question": "1129. The meteorological conditions required to form mountain waves are among others:",
    "options": [
      "a. The height of the mountain must be at least 3000 ft.",
      "b. The air must be unstable.",
      "c. Wind velocity on top of the mountain must be 50 kts or more.",
      "d. A wind profile whereby the wind velocity increases with increasing altitude and a strong, steady wind flow at higher levels often extending to the tropopause."
    ],
    "answer": "d. A wind profile whereby the wind velocity increases with increasing altitude and a strong, steady wind flow at higher levels often extending to the tropopause."
  },
  {
    "question": "1130. What is likely when mountain waves are observed?",
    "options": [
      "a. Strong wind and turbulence in the mountains.",
      "b. Unstable air.",
      "c. Rain on the leeward side of the mountain.",
      "d. Convection clouds."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Strong wind and turbulence in the mountains."
  },
  {
    "question": "1131. A mountain range runs north-south, and a strong wind is blowing from the west. What meteorological phenomena is most likely and where will it be at its most dangerous?",
    "options": [
      "a. Fog in the valleys",
      "b. Mountain wave activity to the west of the mountains",
      "c. Mountain wave activity to the east of the mountains"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Mountain wave activity to the east of the mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "1132. Which would be the best time for nice weather conditions when flying in the Alps during summertime?",
    "options": [
      "a. In the morning",
      "b. In the afternoon",
      "c. In the evening",
      "d. Anytime during the day"
    ],
    "answer": "a. In the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "1133. In general, the meteorological visibility during rainfall compared to during drizzle is",
    "options": [
      "a. less",
      "b. the same",
      "c. greater",
      "d. in rain - below 1 km, in drizzle - more than 2 km"
    ],
    "answer": "c. greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "1134. In unstable air, surface visibility is most likely to be restricted by",
    "options": [
      "a. low stratus",
      "b. haze",
      "c. drizzle",
      "d. showers of rain or snow"
    ],
    "answer": "d. showers of rain or snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "1135. In the vicinity of industrial areas, smoke is most likely to affect surface visibility when",
    "options": [
      "a. the surface wind is strong and gusty",
      "b. there is a low level inversion",
      "c. cumulus clouds have developed in the afternoon",
      "d. a rapid moving cold front has just passed the area"
    ],
    "answer": "b. there is a low level inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "1136. Visibility is reduced by haze when",
    "options": [
      "a. a cold front just passed",
      "b. a light drizzle falls",
      "c. dust particles are trapped below an inversion",
      "d. small waterdroplets are present"
    ],
    "answer": "c. dust particles are trapped below an inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "1137. Below a low level inversion visibility is often",
    "options": [
      "a. moderate or poor due to heavy snow showers.",
      "b. very good at night",
      "c. very good in the early morning",
      "d. moderate or poor because there is no vertical exchange"
    ],
    "answer": "d. moderate or poor because there is no vertical exchange"
  },
  {
    "question": "1138. Flight visibility from the cockpit during approach in a tropical downpour can decrease to minimal",
    "options": [
      "a. about 500 metres",
      "b. about 200 metres",
      "c. tens of metres",
      "d. about 1000 metres"
    ],
    "answer": "c. tens of metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "1139. You are flying in a layer of haze, late on a winter afternoon. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. Flight visibility into sun will be worse",
      "b. Flight visibility \"down sun\" will be worse",
      "c. The position of the sun will not effect flight visibility"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Flight visibility into sun will be worse"
  },
  {
    "question": "1140. Compare meteorological visibility:",
    "options": [
      "a. Visibility is greater in RA than in DZ",
      "b. Visibility is lower in RA than in DZ",
      "c. Visibility is equal in RA and in DZ",
      "d. Visibility is greater in FG than in DZ"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Visibility is greater in RA than in DZ"
  },
  {
    "question": "1141. The flight visibility from the cockpit of an aircraft in a tropical downpour can decrease to minimal....",
    "options": [
      "a. about 500 metres",
      "b. about 1000 metres",
      "c. about 200 metres",
      "d. tens of metres"
    ],
    "answer": "d. tens of metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "1142. What is the relationship between meteorological visibility (met.vis.) and RVR in homogeneous fog?",
    "options": [
      "a. The met. vis. generally is the same as the RVR.",
      "b. The met. vis. generally is greater than the RVR.",
      "c. The met. vis. is generally less than the RVR.",
      "d. There is no specific relationship between the two."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The met. vis. is generally less than the RVR."
  },
  {
    "question": "1143. The wind indicator for a weather observation receives the measured value from an anemometer. Where is this instrument placed?",
    "options": [
      "a. On the roof of the weather station.",
      "b. 1 m above the runway.",
      "c. Close to the station about 2 m above the ground.",
      "d. On a mast 8-10 m above the ground."
    ],
    "answer": "d. On a mast 8-10 m above the ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "1144. What is the meaning of the abbreviation \"BKN\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. 6 - 8 octas.",
      "b. 3 - 4 octas.",
      "c. 5 - 7 octas.",
      "d. 8 octas."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 5 - 7 octas."
  },
  {
    "question": "1145. When is the RVR reported at most airports?",
    "options": [
      "a. When the RVR decreases below 2000 m.",
      "b. When the meteorological visibility decreases below 800 m.",
      "c. When the RVR decreases below 800 m.",
      "d. When the meteorological visibility decreases below 1500 m."
    ],
    "answer": "d. When the meteorological visibility decreases below 1500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "1146. When will the surface wind in a METAR record a gust factor ?",
    "options": [
      "a. When gusts are at least 10 knots above the mean wind speed",
      "b. When gusts are at least 15 knots above the mean wind speed",
      "c. With gusts of at least 25 knots",
      "d. With gusts of at least 35 knots"
    ],
    "answer": "a. When gusts are at least 10 knots above the mean wind speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "1147. While approaching your target aerodrome you receive the following message: RVR runway 23: 400m This information indicates the",
    "options": [
      "a. portion of runway which a pilot on the threshold of any of the runways would see, with runway 23 in service.",
      "b. meteorological visibility on runway 23.",
      "c. length of runway which a pilot in an aircraft on the ground would see, on the threshold of runway 23.",
      "d. minimum visibility at this aerodrome, with runway 23 being the one in service."
    ],
    "answer": "c. length of runway which a pilot in an aircraft on the ground would see, on the threshold of runway 23."
  },
  {
    "question": "1148. Runway Visual Range (RVR) is",
    "options": [
      "a. measured with ceilometers alongside the runway",
      "b. reported when meteorological visibility is less than 2000m",
      "c. reported in TAF and METAR",
      "d. usually better than meteorological visibility"
    ],
    "answer": "d. usually better than meteorological visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "1149. The wind direction in a METAR is measured relative to",
    "options": [
      "a. the 0-meridian",
      "b. magnetic north",
      "c. true north",
      "d. grid north"
    ],
    "answer": "c. true north"
  },
  {
    "question": "1150. The cloud base, reported in the METAR, is the height above",
    "options": [
      "a. the highest terrain within a radius of 8 km from the observation station",
      "b. mean sea level",
      "c. the pressure altitude of the observation station at the time of observation",
      "d. airfield level"
    ],
    "answer": "d. airfield level"
  },
  {
    "question": "1151. What does a Transmissiometer measure ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Wind speed.",
      "b. Cloud base.",
      "c. Visibility.",
      "d. Breaking action."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "1152. What does RVR stand for ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Reduced visibility range.",
      "b. Reduced vertical range.",
      "c. Runway visual range.",
      "d. Radio VHF and range."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Runway visual range."
  },
  {
    "question": "1153. RVR is measured when meteorological visibility falls below:",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 m",
      "b. 1500 m.",
      "c. 2000 m.",
      "d. 2500 m."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "1154. When last 10 minutes wind velocity deviates more than 10 kts from mean value during the same period of time, this will be indicated as:",
    "options": [
      "a. A gust",
      "b. A squall",
      "c. Tempo 10 kts",
      "d. Geostrophic wind."
    ],
    "answer": "a. A gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "1155. The horizontal visibility given for VFR flight planning by a MET Office is:",
    "options": [
      "a. The average flight visibility for the planned flight.",
      "b. Meteorological visibility at an average altitude of 500 meters.",
      "c. Meteorological visibility on ground.",
      "d. Vertical visibility."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Meteorological visibility on ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "1156. The information about visibility to be used planning a VFR flight is:",
    "options": [
      "a. Observed horizontal visibility on ground.",
      "b. Forecasted horizontal visibility on ground.",
      "c. Observed vertical visibility.",
      "d. RVR"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Forecasted horizontal visibility on ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "1157. Among the ten groups of clouds, the following two are mentioned specifically in MET-reports and forecasts intended for aviation:",
    "options": [
      "a. Altocumulus and stratus.",
      "b. Cirrostratus and cumulonimbus.",
      "c. Cumulonimbus and towering cumulus.",
      "d. Cumulonimbus and nimbostratus."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Cumulonimbus and towering cumulus."
  },
  {
    "question": "1158. Under what conditions is RVR measured?",
    "options": [
      "a. When the meteorological visibility is lower than 1500 metres",
      "b. When the meteorological visibility is lower than 1000 metres",
      "c. When fog is present",
      "d. When the technical equipment for the measurement at an airport is available"
    ],
    "answer": "a. When the meteorological visibility is lower than 1500 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "1159. Of the four radio soundings, select the one that indicates ground fog:",
    "options": [
      "a. c)",
      "b. b)",
      "c. a)",
      "d. d)"
    ],
    "answer": "d. d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1160. Of the four radio soundings, select the one that indicates low stratus:",
    "options": [
      "a. 4",
      "b. 3",
      "c. 1",
      "d. 2"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "1161. The average visibility as seen from the cockpit in flight is called:",
    "options": [
      "a. Cockpit visibility.",
      "b. Flight visibility.",
      "c. RVR.",
      "d. Slant visibility."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Flight visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "1162. What are the images of satellites provided daily by the Weather Service used for?",
    "options": [
      "a. To locate fronts in areas with few observation stations",
      "b. To measure wind currents on the ground",
      "c. To help provide 14-day forecasts",
      "d. To locate precipitation zones"
    ],
    "answer": "a. To locate fronts in areas with few observation stations"
  },
  {
    "question": "1163. Which of the following causes echoes on meteorological radar screens?",
    "options": [
      "a. Hail",
      "b. Water vapour",
      "c. Fog",
      "d. Any cloud"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Hail"
  },
  {
    "question": "1164. An airborne weather radar installation makes it possible to detect the location of",
    "options": [
      "a. cumulonimbus, but provided that cloud of this type is accompanied by falls of hail",
      "b. all clouds",
      "c. zones of precipitation, particulary liquid-state precipitation, and also their intensity",
      "d. stratocumulus and its vertical development"
    ],
    "answer": "c. zones of precipitation, particulary liquid-state precipitation, and also their intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "1165. In which meteorological forecast chart is information about CAT regions found?",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 hPa chart.",
      "b. 24 hour surface forecast.",
      "c. 500 hPa chart.",
      "d. Significant Weather Chart."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Significant Weather Chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "1166. On which of the following aviation weather charts can a pilot most easily find a jetstream?",
    "options": [
      "a. Upper air chart.",
      "b. Wind / temperature chart.",
      "c. Surface chart.",
      "d. Significant weather chart."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Significant weather chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "1167. Which weather chart gives information about icing and the height of the freezing level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Surface chart",
      "b. 500 hPa chart",
      "c. 700 hPa chart",
      "d. Significant weather chart"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Significant weather chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "1168. What information is given on a Significant Weather Chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. The significant weather in a period 3 hours before and 3 hours after the time given on the chart",
      "b. The significant weather that is observed at the time given on the chart",
      "c. The significant weather forecast for the time given on the chart",
      "d. The significant weather forecast for a period 6 hours after the time given on the chart"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The significant weather forecast for the time given on the chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "1169. Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 4781 FT pressure level (FL50)?",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 hPa.",
      "b. 700 hPa.",
      "c. 850 hPa.",
      "d. 300 hPa."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 850 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "1170. How is the direction and speed of upper winds described in forecasts ?",
    "options": [
      "a. The direction is relative to magnetic north and the speed is in miles per hour.",
      "b. The direction is relative to magnetic north and the speed is in knots.",
      "c. The direction is relative to true north and the speed is in knots.",
      "d. The direction is relative to true north and the speed is in miles per hour."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The direction is relative to true north and the speed is in knots."
  },
  {
    "question": "1171. What positions are connected with contour lines on the weather chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. Positions with the same air density.",
      "b. Positions with the same thickness between two constant pressure levels.",
      "c. Positions with the same height in a chart of constant pressure.",
      "d. Positions with the same wind velocity."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Positions with the same height in a chart of constant pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "1172. Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 9882 FT pressure level (FL 100) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 850 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1173. Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 18289 FT pressure level (FL 180) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 200 hPa",
      "b. 300 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 700 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1174. Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 30065 FT pressure level (FL 300)?",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 hPa",
      "b. 200 hPa",
      "c. 700 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1175. Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 38662 FT pressure level (FL 390) ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 700 hPa",
      "b. 300 hPa",
      "c. 500 hPa",
      "d. 200 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1176. If you are planning a flight at FL 170, which of these upper wind and temperature charts would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 hPa",
      "b. 500 hPa",
      "c. 850 hPa",
      "d. 700 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1177. If you are planning a flight at FL 290, which of these upper wind and temperature charts would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 850 hPa",
      "b. 500 hPa",
      "c. 700 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1178. When planning a flight at FL 60, which upper wind and temperature chart would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 hPa",
      "b. 700 hPa",
      "c. 850 hPa",
      "d. 300 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 850 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1179. When planning a flight at FL 110, which upper wind and temperature chart would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 hPa",
      "b. 850 hPa",
      "c. 700 hPa",
      "d. 500 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1180. The upper wind and temperature chart of 250 hPa corresponds, in a standard atmosphere, to about",
    "options": [
      "a. 34 000 FT",
      "b. 39 000 FT",
      "c. 30 000 FT",
      "d. 32 000 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 34 000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "1181. An isohypse of the 500 hPa pressure surface is labelled with the number 552. This means that for all points on the isohypse the",
    "options": [
      "a. topography is 552 decameters above MSL",
      "b. pressure is 552 hPa",
      "c. topography is 552 meters above MSL",
      "d. pressure altimeter will overread by 552 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. topography is 552 decameters above MSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "1182. What units of measurement are used in forecasts for winds aloft?",
    "options": [
      "a. Magnetic direction and knots.",
      "b. Magnetic direction and MPH.",
      "c. True direction and knots.",
      "d. True direction and MPH."
    ],
    "answer": "c. True direction and knots."
  },
  {
    "question": "1183. How are well separated CB clouds described on the Significant Weather Chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. ISOL CB.",
      "b. EMBD CB.",
      "c. FREQ CB.",
      "d. OCNL CB."
    ],
    "answer": "d. OCNL CB."
  },
  {
    "question": "1184. The cold front is indicated with a number at position:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1",
      "b. 2",
      "c. 3",
      "d. 4"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "1185. What does the symbol indicate on a significant weather chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. The center of a tropopause \"high\", where the tropopause is at FL 400.",
      "b. The center of a high pressure area at 400 hPa.",
      "c. The upper limit of significant weather at FL 400.",
      "d. The lower limit of the tropopause."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The center of a tropopause \"high\", where the tropopause is at FL 400."
  },
  {
    "question": "1186. Which of the following symbols represents a squall line?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbol c)",
      "b. Symbol b)",
      "c. Symbol a)",
      "d. Symbol d)"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1187. Which of the following symbols represents a tropical revolving storm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbol c)",
      "b. Symbol b)",
      "c. Symbol a)",
      "d. Symbol d)"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1188. The front labelled \"Z\" is a:",
    "options": [
      "a. Cold front",
      "b. Warm front",
      "c. Warm front occlusion",
      "d. Cold front occlusion"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "1189. A trough is indicated by letter:",
    "options": [
      "a. B",
      "b. A",
      "c. C",
      "d. D"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A"
  },
  {
    "question": "1190. The warm sector is indicated by letter:",
    "options": [
      "a. A",
      "b. B",
      "c. D",
      "d. C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. D"
  },
  {
    "question": "1191. Which of the following best describes Zone A?",
    "options": [
      "a. Depression",
      "b. Col",
      "c. Ridge of high pressure",
      "d. Trough of low pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Trough of low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "1192. Which of the following best describes Zone B?",
    "options": [
      "a. Col",
      "b. Ridge of high pressure",
      "c. Depression",
      "d. Trough of low pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Col"
  },
  {
    "question": "1193. Which of the following best describes Zone C?",
    "options": [
      "a. Ridge of high pressure",
      "b. Col",
      "c. Trough of low pressure",
      "d. Depression"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Ridge of high pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "1194. Which of the following best describes Zone D?",
    "options": [
      "a. Anticyclone",
      "b. Ridge of high pressure",
      "c. Depression",
      "d. Trough of low pressure"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "1195. According to ICAO, which symbol indicates severe icing ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbol a)",
      "b. Symbol b)",
      "c. Symbol c)",
      "d. Symbol d)"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1196. According to ICAO, which symbol indicates a tropical revolving storm?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbol d)",
      "b. Symbol c)",
      "c. Symbol b)",
      "d. Symbol a)"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Symbol d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1197. According to ICAO, which symbol indicates danger to an aircraft in flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbol b)",
      "b. Symbol d)",
      "c. Symbol a)",
      "d. Symbol c)"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Symbol b)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1198. According to ICAO, which symbol indicates danger to an aircraft in flight?",
    "options": [
      "a. Symbols c) and d)",
      "b. Symbol d)",
      "c. Symbols a) and b)",
      "d. Symbol c)"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Symbols c) and d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "1199. Refer to the TAF for Amsterdam airport. FCNL31 281500 EHAM 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020 = Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. What lowest cloud base is forecast for arrival at Amsterdam?",
    "options": [
      "a. 500 m",
      "b. 250 FT",
      "c. 500 FT",
      "d. 800 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 500 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "1200. In the TAF for Dehli, during the summer, for the time of your landing you note: TEMPO TS. What is the maximum time this deterioration in weather can last in anyone instance ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 120 minutes.",
      "b. 60 minutes.",
      "c. 10 minutes.",
      "d. 20 minutes."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 60 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "1201. In the weather briefing room during the pre-flight phase of a passenger flight from Zurich to Rome, you examine the following weather reports of pressing importance at the time: EINN SHANNON 2808 sigmet 2 valid 0800/1100 loc sev turb fcst einn fir blw fl 050 south of 53n wkn = LIMM MILANO 2809 sigmet 2 valid 0900/1500 mod sev cat btn fl 250 and fl 430 fcst limm fir stnr nc = EGL",
    "options": [
      "a. You show no further interest in these reports, since they do not concern the route to be flown.",
      "b. Because of the expected turbulence you select a flight level below FL 250.",
      "c. Owing to these reports and taking into account the presence of heavy thunderstorms at planned FL 310 you select a higher flight level (FL 370).",
      "d. You cancel the flight since the expected dangerous weather conditions along the route would demand too much of the passengers."
    ],
    "answer": "b. Because of the expected turbulence you select a flight level below FL 250."
  },
  {
    "question": "1202. What is a trend forecast?",
    "options": [
      "a. An aerodrome forecast valid for 9 hours",
      "b. A landing forecast appended to METAR/SPECI, valid for 2 hours",
      "c. A route forecast valid for 24 hours",
      "d. A routine report"
    ],
    "answer": "b. A landing forecast appended to METAR/SPECI, valid for 2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "1203. What does the expression \"Broken (BKN)\" mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. 5-7 Eights of the sky is cloud covered",
      "b. 3-4 Eights of the sky is cloud covered",
      "c. 3-5 Eights of the sky is cloud covered",
      "d. Nil significant cloud cover"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 5-7 Eights of the sky is cloud covered"
  },
  {
    "question": "1204. What does the abbreviation \"nosig\" mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. No significant changes",
      "b. No report received",
      "c. No weather related problems",
      "d. Not signed by the meteorologist"
    ],
    "answer": "a. No significant changes"
  },
  {
    "question": "1205. In which weather report would you expect to find information about icing conditions on the runway?",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF",
      "b. SIGMET",
      "c. GAFOR",
      "d. METAR"
    ],
    "answer": "d. METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "1206. In which of the following 1850 UTC METAR reports, is the probability of fog formation, in the coming night, the highest?",
    "options": [
      "a. VRB02KT 2500 SCT120 14/M08 Q1035 NOSIG =",
      "b. 22004KT 6000 -RA SCT012 OVC030 17/14 Q1009 NOSIG =",
      "c. VRB01KT 8000 SCT250 11/10 Q1028 BECMG 3000 =",
      "d. 00000KT 9999 SCT300 21/01 Q1032 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. VRB01KT 8000 SCT250 11/10 Q1028 BECMG 3000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1207. Which of the following weather reports could be, in accordance with the regulations, abbreviated to \"CAVOK\"? (MSA above ground: LSZB 10000 FT, LSZH 8000 FT, LSGG 12000 FT, LFSB 6000 FT)",
    "options": [
      "a. LSZH 26024G52KT 9999 BKN060 17/14 Q1012 RETS TEMPO 5000 TSRA =",
      "b. LSGG 22003KT 9999 SCT120 BKN280 09/08 Q1026 BECMG 5000 =",
      "c. LSZB 30004KT 9999 SCT090 10/09 Q1006 NOSIG =",
      "d. LFSB 00000KT 9000 SCT080 22/15 Q1022 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "b. LSGG 22003KT 9999 SCT120 BKN280 09/08 Q1026 BECMG 5000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1208. Which of the following weather reports could be, in accordance with the regulations, abbreviated to \"CAVOK\"? (MSA above ground : LSZB 10000 FT, LSZH 8000 FT, LSGG 12000 FT, LFSB 6000 FT)",
    "options": [
      "a. LFSB 24008KT 9999 SCT050 18/11 Q1017 RERA NOSIG =",
      "b. LSZB 28012KT 9999 OVC100 16/12 Q1012 BECMG 5000 =",
      "c. LSZH VRB02KT 9000 BKN080 21/14 Q1022 NOSIG =",
      "d. LSGG 22006KT 9999 BKN090 17/15 Q1008 RERA NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "a. LFSB 24008KT 9999 SCT050 18/11 Q1017 RERA NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1209. Within a short interval, several flight crews report that they have experienced strong clear air turbulence in a certain airspace. What is the consequence of these reports?",
    "options": [
      "a. The competent aviation weather office will issue a SPECI",
      "b. The airspace in question, will be temporarily closed",
      "c. The competent aviation weather office will issue a SIGMET",
      "d. The competent aviation weather office will issue a storm warning"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The competent aviation weather office will issue a SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "1210. Refer to the TAF for Bordeaux airport. FCFR31 281400 LFBD 1524 26015KT 9999 SHRA BKN020 TEMPO 1620 26020G30KT 8000 +SHRA BKN015CB PROB30 TSRA = Flight Lisbon to Bordeaux, ETA 1800 UTC. What type of precipitation is forecast on the approach to Bordeaux ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Light drizzle and fog",
      "b. Continuous moderate rain",
      "c. Heavy rain showers",
      "d. Moderate snow showers"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Heavy rain showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "1211. Refer to the TAF for Bordeaux airport. FCFR31 281400 LFBD 1524 26015KT 9999 SHRA BKN020 TEMPO 1620 26020G30KT 8000 +SHRA BKN015CB PROB30 TSRA = Flight Lisbon to Bordeaux, ETA 1800 UTC. At ETA Bordeaux what is the lowest quoted visibility forecast ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 10 or more km",
      "b. 8 NM",
      "c. 10 NM",
      "d. 8 km"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 8 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "1212. Refer to the TAF for Amsterdam airport. FCNL31 281500 EHAM 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020 = Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. At ETA Amsterdam what surface wind is forecast ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 120\u00b0 / 15 kt gusts 25 kt",
      "b. 140\u00b0 / 10 kt",
      "c. 300\u00b0 / 15 kt maximum wind 25 kt",
      "d. 250\u00b0 / 20 kt"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 120\u00b0 / 15 kt gusts 25 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1213. Refer to the TAF for Amsterdam airport. FCNL31 281500 EHAM 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020 = Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. What is the minimum visibility forecast for ETA Amsterdam ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 5 km",
      "b. 3 km",
      "c. 5 NM",
      "d. 6 km"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 3 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "1214. Does the following report make sense? LSZH VRB02KT 5000 MIFG 02/02 Q1015 NOSIG",
    "options": [
      "a. The report is nonsense, because it is impossible to observe a meteorological visibility of 5 km if shallow fog is reported.",
      "b. The report would never be seen, because shallow fog is not reported when the meteorological visibility is more than 2 km.",
      "c. The report is possible, because shallow fog is defined as a thin layer of fog below eye level.",
      "d. The report is not possible, because, with a temperature of 2\u00b0C and a dew point of 2\u00b0C there must be uniform fog."
    ],
    "answer": "c. The report is possible, because shallow fog is defined as a thin layer of fog below eye level."
  },
  {
    "question": "1215. You receive the following METAR : LSGG 0750Z 00000KT 0300 R05/0700N FG VV001 M02/M02 Q1014 NOSIG = What will be the RVR at 0900 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. 300 m.",
      "b. The RVR is unknown, because the \"NOSIG\" does not refer to RVR.",
      "c. 700 m.",
      "d. 900 m."
    ],
    "answer": "b. The RVR is unknown, because the \"NOSIG\" does not refer to RVR."
  },
  {
    "question": "1216. Which of the four answers is a correct interpretation of data from the following METAR ? 16003KT 0400 R14/P1500 R16/1000N FZFG VV003 M02/M02 Q1026 BECMG 2000 =",
    "options": [
      "a. Meteorological visibility 1000 m, RVR 400 m, freezing level at 300 m, variable winds, temperature 2\u00b0C.",
      "b. RVR for runway 16 1000 m, meteorological visibility increasing in the next 2 hours to 2000 m, vertical visibility 300 m, temperature -2\u00b0C.",
      "c. RVR for runway 14 1500 m, meteorological visibility 400 m, QNH 1026 hPa, wind 160\u00b0 at 3 kt.",
      "d. Meteorological visibility 400m, RVR for runway 16 1000 m, dew point -2\u00b0C, freezing fog."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Meteorological visibility 400m, RVR for runway 16 1000 m, dew point -2\u00b0C, freezing fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "1217. Refer to the following TAF extract: BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What visibility is forecast for 2400 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. Between 500 m and 2000 m.",
      "b. 2000 m.",
      "c. 500 m.",
      "d. Between 0 m and 1000 m."
    ],
    "answer": "c. 500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "1218. Refer to the following TAF extract: BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What does the abbreviation \"VV001\" mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. RVR greater than 100 m.",
      "b. RVR less than 100 m.",
      "c. Vertical visibility 100 FT.",
      "d. Vertical visibility 100 m."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Vertical visibility 100 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "1219. What does the term METAR signify?",
    "options": [
      "a. A METAR is a flight forecast, issued by the meteorological station several times daily.",
      "b. A METAR is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions within a FIR.",
      "c. A METAR signifies the actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued in half-hourly intervals.",
      "d. A METAR is a landing forecast added to the actual weather report as a brief prognostic report."
    ],
    "answer": "c. A METAR signifies the actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued in half-hourly intervals."
  },
  {
    "question": "1220. How long from the time of observation is a TREND in a METAR valid?",
    "options": [
      "a. 9 hours.",
      "b. 2 hours.",
      "c. 1 hour.",
      "d. 30 minutes."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 2 hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "1221. What is a SPECI?",
    "options": [
      "a. A routine aerodrome weather report issued every 3 hours.",
      "b. A selected special aerodrome weather report, issued when a significant change of the weather conditions have been observed.",
      "c. A warning of meteorological dangers at an aerodrome, issued only when required.",
      "d. An aerodrome forecast issued every 9 hours."
    ],
    "answer": "b. A selected special aerodrome weather report, issued when a significant change of the weather conditions have been observed."
  },
  {
    "question": "1222. Appended to a METAR you get the following runway report: 01650428 What must you consider when making performance calculations?",
    "options": [
      "a. Aquaplaning conditions.",
      "b. The braking action will be medium to good.",
      "c. The runway will be wet.",
      "d. The friction coefficient is 0.28."
    ],
    "answer": "d. The friction coefficient is 0.28."
  },
  {
    "question": "1223. Refer to the following TAF extract: BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What does the \"BECMG\" data indicate for the 18 to 21 hour time frame?",
    "options": [
      "a. The new conditions are achieved between 1800 and 2100 UTC",
      "b. A quick change to new conditions between 1800 UTC and 1900 UTC.",
      "c. Many short term changes in the original weather.",
      "d. Many long term changes in the original weather."
    ],
    "answer": "a. The new conditions are achieved between 1800 and 2100 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "1224. Refer to the following TAF extract: BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What does the abbreviation \"BKN004\" mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1 - 4 oktas, ceiling 400 m.",
      "b. 1 - 4 oktas, ceiling 400 FT.",
      "c. 4 - 8 oktas, ceiling 400 m.",
      "d. 5 - 7 oktas, ceiling 400 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 5 - 7 oktas, ceiling 400 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "1225. Refer to the following TAF extract; BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What does the abbreviation \"PROB30\" mean?",
    "options": [
      "a. Probability of 30%.",
      "b. Conditions will last for at least 30 minutes.",
      "c. The cloud ceiling should lift to 3000 FT.",
      "d. Change expected in less than 30 minutes."
    ],
    "answer": "a. Probability of 30%."
  },
  {
    "question": "1226. Refer to TAF below. EGBB 261812 28015G25KT 9999 SCT025 TEMPO 1822 29018G35KT 5000 SHRASN BKN010CB PROB30 TEMPO 1821 1500 TSGR BKN008CB BECMG 2124 26010 KT From the TAF above you can assume that visibility at 2055Z in Birmingham (EGBB) will be :",
    "options": [
      "a. not less than 1,5 km but could be in excess of 10 km.",
      "b. a maximum 5 km.",
      "c. a minimum of 1,5 km and a maximum of 5 km.",
      "d. more than 10 km"
    ],
    "answer": "a. not less than 1,5 km but could be in excess of 10 km."
  },
  {
    "question": "1227. What is the wind speed given in a METAR report based on?",
    "options": [
      "a. The average speed of the previous 30 minutes",
      "b. The average speed of the previous 10 minutes",
      "c. The strongest gust in the previous hour",
      "d. The actual speed at the time of recording"
    ],
    "answer": "b. The average speed of the previous 10 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "1228. What does the term SIGMET signify?",
    "options": [
      "a. A SIGMET is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions",
      "b. A SIGMET is a flight forecast, issued by the meteorological station several times daily",
      "c. A SIGMET is a brief landing forecast added to the actual weather report",
      "d. A SIGMET is an actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued at half-hourly intervals"
    ],
    "answer": "a. A SIGMET is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "1229. What does the term TREND signify?",
    "options": [
      "a. It is a flight forecast, issued by the meteorological station several times daily",
      "b. It is the actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued at half-hourly intervals",
      "c. It is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions",
      "d. It is a brief landing forecast added to the actual weather report"
    ],
    "answer": "d. It is a brief landing forecast added to the actual weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "1230. Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "options": [
      "a. FZFG",
      "b. BCFG",
      "c. SN",
      "d. HZ"
    ],
    "answer": "c. SN"
  },
  {
    "question": "1231. Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "options": [
      "a. +SHSN",
      "b. VA",
      "c. BR",
      "d. MIFG"
    ],
    "answer": "a. +SHSN"
  },
  {
    "question": "1232. Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "options": [
      "a. TS",
      "b. SA",
      "c. DZ",
      "d. SQ"
    ],
    "answer": "c. DZ"
  },
  {
    "question": "1233. Which of the following meteorological phenomena can rapidly change the braking action of a runway?",
    "options": [
      "a. HZ",
      "b. MIFG",
      "c. FG",
      "d. +FZRA"
    ],
    "answer": "d. +FZRA"
  },
  {
    "question": "1234. Which of the following phenomena can produce a risk of aquaplaning?",
    "options": [
      "a. SA",
      "b. FG",
      "c. BCFG",
      "d. +RA"
    ],
    "answer": "d. +RA"
  },
  {
    "question": "1235. Which of these four METAR reports suggests that rain is most likely in the next few hours?",
    "options": [
      "a. 23015KT 8000 BKN030 OVC070 17/14 Q1009 BECMG 4000 =",
      "b. 34004KT 9999 SCT040 SCT100 m05/m08 Q1014 NOSIG =",
      "c. 16002KT 0100 FG SCT300 06/06 Q1022 BECMG 1000 =",
      "d. 05016G33KT 8000 OVC015 08/06 Q1028 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "a. 23015KT 8000 BKN030 OVC070 17/14 Q1009 BECMG 4000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1236. Which of these four METAR reports suggests that a thunderstorm is likely in the next few hours?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1350Z 21005KT 9999 SCT040CB SCT100 26/18 Q1016 TEMPO 24018G30 TS =",
      "b. 1350Z 16004KT 8000 SCT110 OVC220 02/m02 Q1008 NOSIG =",
      "c. 1350Z 34003KT 0800 SN VV002 m02/m04 Q1014 NOSIG =",
      "d. 1350Z 04012KT 3000 OVC012 04/03 Q1022 BECMG 5000 ="
    ],
    "answer": "a. 1350Z 21005KT 9999 SCT040CB SCT100 26/18 Q1016 TEMPO 24018G30 TS ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1237. In which of the following METAR reports, is the probability of fog formation in the coming night the highest?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1850Z 15003KT 6000 SCT120 05/04 Q1032 BECMG 1600 =",
      "b. 1850Z 21003KT 8000 SCT250 12/m08 Q1028 NOSIG =",
      "c. 1850Z 06018G30KT 5000 OVC010 04/01 Q1024 NOSIG =",
      "d. 1850Z 25010KT 4000 RA BKN012 OVC030 12/10 Q1006 TEMPO 1500 ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. 1850Z 06018G30KT 5000 OVC010 04/01 Q1024 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1238. Look at this TAF for Zurich Airport TAF LSZH 211322 22018G35KT 9999 SCT012 BKN030 BECMG 1315 25025G45KT TEMPO 1720 4000 +SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 2022 25015KT T1815Z T1618Z = Which of these statements best describes the weather most likely to be experienced at 1500 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. Meteorological visibility 10 kilometres or more, main cloudbase 1200 feet, gusts up to 45 knots.",
      "b. Meteorological visibility 4000 metres, gusts up to 25 knots, temperature 18\u00b0C.",
      "c. Meteorological visibility 10 kilometres or more, main cloudbase 3000 feet, wind 250\u00b0, temperature 18\u00b0C.",
      "d. Severe rainshowers, meteorological visibility 4000 metres, temperature 15\u00b0C, gusts up to 35 knots."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Meteorological visibility 10 kilometres or more, main cloudbase 3000 feet, wind 250\u00b0, temperature 18\u00b0C."
  },
  {
    "question": "1239. Refer to the TAF for Zurich Airport TAF LSZH 250716 00000KT 0100 FG VV001 BECMG 0810 0800 VV002 BECMG 1012 23005KT 2500 BKN005 TEMPO 1316 6000 SCT007 = Which of these statements best describes the weather that can be expected at 1200 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. Meteorological visibility 6 kilometres, cloudbase 500 feet, windspeed 5 knots",
      "b. Meteorological visibility 800 metres, wind from 230\u00b0, cloudbase 500 feet",
      "c. Meteorological visibility 800 metres, vertical visibility 200 feet, calm",
      "d. Meteorological visibility 2,5 kilometres, cloudbase 500 feet, windspeed 5 knots"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Meteorological visibility 2,5 kilometres, cloudbase 500 feet, windspeed 5 knots"
  },
  {
    "question": "1240. Which of the following weather reports could be, in accordance with the regulations, abbreviated to \"CAVOK\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. 29010KT 9999 SCT045TCU 16/12 Q1015 RESHRA NOSIG =",
      "b. 24009KT 6000 RA SCT010 OVC030 12/11 Q1007 TEMPO 4000 =",
      "c. 15003KT 9999 BKN100 17/11 Q1024 NOSIG =",
      "d. 04012G26KT 9999 BKN030 11/07 Q1024 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. 15003KT 9999 BKN100 17/11 Q1024 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1241. Which of the following weather reports could be, in accordance with the regulations, abbreviated to \"CAVOK\"?",
    "options": [
      "a. 34004KT 7000 MIFG SCT260 09/08 Q1029 BECMG 1600 =",
      "b. 27019G37KT 9999 BKN050 18/14 Q1016 NOSIG =",
      "c. 00000KT 0100 FG VV001 11/11 Q1025 BECMG 0500 =",
      "d. 26012KT 8000 SHRA BKN025 16/12 Q1018 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "b. 27019G37KT 9999 BKN050 18/14 Q1016 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1242. Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the METAR ? 25020G38KT 1200 +TSGR BKN006 BKN015CB 23/18 Q1016 BECMG NSW =",
    "options": [
      "a. Gusts of 38 knots, thunderstorm with heavy hail, dew point 18\u00b0C",
      "b. Mean wind speed 20-38 knots, meteorological visibility 1200 metres, temperature 23\u00b0C",
      "c. Broken, cloudbase 600 feet and 1500 feet, temperature 18\u00b0C",
      "d. Wind 250\u00b0, thunderstorm with moderate hail, QNH 1016 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Wind 250\u00b0, thunderstorm with moderate hail, QNH 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1243. Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the METAR ? 00000KT 0200 R14/0800U R16/P1500U FZFG VV001 m03/m03 Q1022 BECMG 0800 =",
    "options": [
      "a. Meteorological visibility for runway 14 800 metres, fog with hoar frost, RVR for runway 16 more than 1500 metres",
      "b. Meteorological visibility 200 metres, RVR for runway 16 1500 metres, temperature -3\u00b0C, vertical visibility 100 metres",
      "c. Meteorological visibility 200 feet, RVR for runway 16 more than 1500 metres, vertical visibility 100 feet, fog with hoar frost",
      "d. RVR for runway 14 800 metres, vertical visibility 100 feet, calm, meteorological visibility improving to 800 metres in the next 2 hours"
    ],
    "answer": "d. RVR for runway 14 800 metres, vertical visibility 100 feet, calm, meteorological visibility improving to 800 metres in the next 2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "1244. Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the SIGMET ? LSAW SWITZERLAND 0307 SIGMET 2 VALID 030700/031100 LSSW mod to sev cat fcst north of alps btn fl 260 and fl 380 / stnr / intsf =",
    "options": [
      "a. Zone of moderate-to-severe turbulence moving towards the area north of the Alps. Intensity increasing. Pilots advised to cross this area above FL 260",
      "b. Moderate-to-severe clear air turbulence to be expected north of the Alps. Intensity increasing. Danger zone between FL 260 and FL 380",
      "c. Severe turbulence observed below FL 260 north of the Alps. Pilots advised to cross this area above FL 380",
      "d. Moderate to strong clear air turbulence of constant intensity to be expected north of the Alps"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Moderate-to-severe clear air turbulence to be expected north of the Alps. Intensity increasing. Danger zone between FL 260 and FL 380"
  },
  {
    "question": "1245. Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the SIGMET ? SIGMET VALID 121420/121820 embd ts obs and fcst in w part of athinai fir / mov e / intst nc =",
    "options": [
      "a. Athens Airport is closed due to thunderstorms. The thunderstorm zone should be east of Athens by 1820 UTC",
      "b. Thunderstorms have formed in the eastern part of the Athens FIR and are slowly moving west",
      "c. Thunderstorms must be expected in the western part of the Athens FIR. The thunderstorm zone is moving east. Intensity is constant",
      "d. The thunderstorms in the Athens FIR are increasing in intensity, but are stationary above the western part of the Athens FIR"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Thunderstorms must be expected in the western part of the Athens FIR. The thunderstorm zone is moving east. Intensity is constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "1246. Refer to the following TAF for Zurich. LSZH 261019 20018G30KT 9999 -RA SCT050 BKN080 TEMPO 23012KT 6000 -DZ BKN015 BKN030 BECMG 1518 23020G35KT 4000 RA OVC010= The lowest visibility forecast at ETA Zurich 1430 UTC is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 6 NM.",
      "b. 6 km.",
      "c. 4 km.",
      "d. 10 km."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 6 km."
  },
  {
    "question": "1247. Refer to the following TAF for Zurich. LSZH 061019 20018G30KT 9999 -RA SCT050 BKN080 TEMPO 23012KT 6000 -DZ BKN015 BKN030 BECMG 1518 23020G35KT 4000 RA OVC010= The lowest cloud base forecast at ETA Zurich (1200 UTC) is:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1000 FT.",
      "b. 1500 FT.",
      "c. 1500 m.",
      "d. 5000 FT."
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1500 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "1248. The following weather report EDDM 241322 VRB03KT 1500 HZ OVC004 BECMG 1517 00000KT 0500 FG VV002 TEMPO 2022 0400 FG VV001 is a :",
    "options": [
      "a. METAR.",
      "b. 24 hour TAF.",
      "c. SPECI.",
      "d. 9 hour TAF."
    ],
    "answer": "d. 9 hour TAF."
  },
  {
    "question": "1249. In METAR messages, the pressure group represents the",
    "options": [
      "a. QNH rounded up to the nearest hPa.",
      "b. QFE rounded to the nearest hPa.",
      "c. QNH rounded down to the nearest hPa.",
      "d. QFE rounded down to the nearest hPa."
    ],
    "answer": "c. QNH rounded down to the nearest hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "1250. What is the meaning of the abbreviation \"SCT\" ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 1 - 2 oktas",
      "b. 3 - 4 oktas",
      "c. 5 - 7 oktas",
      "d. 1 - 4 oktas"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 3 - 4 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "1251. Which of the statements is true concerning squall lines ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Severe squall lines always move from northwest to southeast",
      "b. Severe squall lines only occur in the tropics",
      "c. For severe squall lines a TAF is issued",
      "d. For severe squall lines a SIGMET is issued"
    ],
    "answer": "d. For severe squall lines a SIGMET is issued"
  },
  {
    "question": "1252. The validity of a TAF is",
    "options": [
      "a. between 6 and 9 hours",
      "b. 2 hours",
      "c. stated in the TAF",
      "d. 9 hours from the time of issue"
    ],
    "answer": "c. stated in the TAF"
  },
  {
    "question": "1253. If CAVOK is reported then",
    "options": [
      "a. no low drifting snow is present",
      "b. no clouds are present",
      "c. low level windshear has not been reported",
      "d. any CB's have a base above 5000 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. no low drifting snow is present"
  },
  {
    "question": "1254. Runway visual range can be reported in",
    "options": [
      "a. a TAF",
      "b. a METAR",
      "c. a SIGMET",
      "d. both a TAF and a METAR"
    ],
    "answer": "b. a METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "1255. SIGMET information is issued as a warning for significant weather to",
    "options": [
      "a. heavy aircraft only",
      "b. light aircraft only",
      "c. VFR operations only",
      "d. all aircraft"
    ],
    "answer": "d. all aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "1256. A SPECI is",
    "options": [
      "a. an aviation routine weather report",
      "b. an aviation selected special weather report",
      "c. a warning for special weather phenomena",
      "d. a forecast for special weather phenomena"
    ],
    "answer": "b. an aviation selected special weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "1257. On the European continent METARs of main airports are compiled and distributed with intervals of",
    "options": [
      "a. 2 hours",
      "b. 1 hour",
      "c. 0.5 hour",
      "d. 3 hours"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 0.5 hour"
  },
  {
    "question": "1258. The RVR, as reported in a METAR, is always the",
    "options": [
      "a. highest value of the A-, B- and C-position",
      "b. average value of the A-, B- and C-position",
      "c. value representative of the touchdown zone",
      "d. lowest value of the A-, B- and C-position"
    ],
    "answer": "c. value representative of the touchdown zone"
  },
  {
    "question": "1259. Given the following METAR: EDDM 250850Z 33005KT 2000 R26R/P1500N R26L/1500N BR SCT002 OVC003 05/05 Q1025 NOSIG",
    "options": [
      "a. Visibility is reduced by water droplets",
      "b. There is a distinct change in RVR observed",
      "c. Runway 26R and runway 26L have the same RVR",
      "d. RVR on runway 26R is increasing"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Visibility is reduced by water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "1260. At a weather station, at 0600 UTC, the air temperature and dew point are respectively: T = - 0,5\u00b0C,Td = -1,5\u00b0C. In the METAR message transmitted by this station, the \"temperature group\" will be:",
    "options": [
      "a. M00/M01",
      "b. M01/M02",
      "c. 00/M01",
      "d. M01/M01"
    ],
    "answer": "a. M00/M01"
  },
  {
    "question": "1261. The TAF validity in terms of time is usually:",
    "options": [
      "a. 3 hours",
      "b. 6 hours",
      "c. 9 hours",
      "d. 12 hours"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 9 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "1262. A \"SIGMET\" is:",
    "options": [
      "a. A significant weather chart",
      "b. A special \"METAR\"",
      "c. A message about observed or forecasted weather phenomena of special importance to aviation",
      "d. The same as a \"TAF\"-forecast"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A message about observed or forecasted weather phenomena of special importance to aviation"
  },
  {
    "question": "1263. Which of the following is a landing forecast ?",
    "options": [
      "a. METAR.",
      "b. TAF.",
      "c. SPECI.",
      "d. METAR with TREND."
    ],
    "answer": "d. METAR with TREND."
  },
  {
    "question": "1264. SIGMETs are issued as a warning of weather conditions hazardous:",
    "options": [
      "a. Particularly to light aircraft",
      "b. To all aircraft",
      "c. Only to light aircraft operations",
      "d. Particularly to heavy aircraft"
    ],
    "answer": "b. To all aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "1265. The function of a TAF is to be a/an :",
    "options": [
      "a. Area forecast.",
      "b. Local forecast.",
      "c. Forecast for an airfield.",
      "d. Wind forecast."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Forecast for an airfield."
  },
  {
    "question": "1266. A METAR from an airfield reporting visibility 8 km. Added to the report is a \"BECMG 4000\". From this you will expect the visibility to",
    "options": [
      "a. Decrease to 4 km within 1 hour.",
      "b. Improve from 4 km to 8 km in the next 2 hours.",
      "c. Be variable between 4 and 8 km.",
      "d. Decrease to 4 km within the next 2 hours."
    ],
    "answer": "d. Decrease to 4 km within the next 2 hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "1267. Cloud bases in TAFs and METARs are given in:",
    "options": [
      "a. Heights above mean sea level",
      "b. Heights above the 1013 hPa pressure level",
      "c. Heights above airfield elevation"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Heights above airfield elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "1268. The abbreviation BKN means:",
    "options": [
      "a. 1-4 oktas cloud cover",
      "b. 3-7 oktas cloud cover",
      "c. 5-7 oktas cloud cover"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 5-7 oktas cloud cover"
  },
  {
    "question": "1269. The abbreviation SCT means:",
    "options": [
      "a. 2-4 oktas cloud cover",
      "b. 3-7 oktas cloud cover",
      "c. 5-7 oktas cloud cover"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 2-4 oktas cloud cover"
  },
  {
    "question": "1270. The abbreviation FEW means:",
    "options": [
      "a. 2-4 oktas cloud cover",
      "b. 1-2 oktas cloud cover",
      "c. 5-7 oktas cloud cover"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1-2 oktas cloud cover"
  },
  {
    "question": "1271. EHAM 120600Z 02025KT 3000 RA BKN005 OVC015 11/10 Q1012= Which of the following is the correct decode for the Amsterdam METAR?",
    "options": [
      "a. Observation at 0600Z, wind 020\u00b0 at 25 knots, visibility 3000 metres in rain, clouds: broken ST with base 500ft AGL and 8 oktas NS with base 1500ft AGL, temperature +11\u00b0C, dew point +10\u00b0C, QNH 1012 hPa",
      "b. Observation at 0600 UTC, wind 020\u00b0 at 25 knots, visibility 3000m, rain, broken ST with base 500ft AGL and 8 oktas NS with base 1500ft MSL, temperature +11\u00b0C, dew point +10\u00b0C, QNH 1012 hPa",
      "c. Period valid between 0600 UTC and 0000 UTC, wind 020\u00b0 at 25 knots, visibility 3000 metres in rain, clouds: broken ST with base 500ft AGL and 8 oktas NS with base 1500ft AGL, temperature +11\u00b0C, dew point +10\u00b0C, QNH 1012 hPa"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Observation at 0600Z, wind 020\u00b0 at 25 knots, visibility 3000 metres in rain, clouds: broken ST with base 500ft AGL and 8 oktas NS with base 1500ft AGL, temperature +11\u00b0C, dew point +10\u00b0C, QNH 1012 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "1272. If weather conditions are reported as CAVOK, which of the following could not be present:",
    "options": [
      "a. Winds 25 KT, gusting to 40 KT",
      "b. 1 okta of CB at 9000ft",
      "c. Overcast cloud at 5100ft"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1 okta of CB at 9000ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "1273. A SIGMET message is:",
    "options": [
      "a. A routine weather report to an aircraft in flight",
      "b. A routine weather report from an aircraft in flight",
      "c. A warning of reported or forecast hazardous in-flight conditions"
    ],
    "answer": "c. A warning of reported or forecast hazardous in-flight conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "1274. It is October, and an aerea of high pressure has been established for several days. Which of the following is most likely to represent the TAF for an inland airport?",
    "options": [
      "a. 0716 04025KT 7000 BKN013 OVC090=",
      "b. 0716 05002KT 0800 FG OVC001 TEMPO 0709 0200 VV/// BECMG 0811 3000 BR OVC005 TEMPO 1116 6000 SCT008=",
      "c. 0716 30005KT 9999 SCT035 PROB30 TEMPO 0710 5000 +TSRA BKN050CB="
    ],
    "answer": "b. 0716 05002KT 0800 FG OVC001 TEMPO 0709 0200 VV/// BECMG 0811 3000 BR OVC005 TEMPO 1116 6000 SCT008="
  },
  {
    "question": "1275. What conditions have to be met amongst others, that the weather is reported to be CAVOK?",
    "options": [
      "a. No low drifting snow is present",
      "b. Wind of less than 25KT",
      "c. No clouds are present below 8000 ft AGL",
      "d. No clouds are present below 5000 ft AMSL"
    ],
    "answer": "a. No low drifting snow is present"
  },
  {
    "question": "1276. A pilot observes thunderstorm activity and severe icing along his flight path. Therefore, he files a pilot report. What does it lead to?",
    "options": [
      "a. It leads to a SIGMET",
      "b. It leads to a METAR",
      "c. An amended General Aviation Forecast will be issued",
      "d. No action will be taken"
    ],
    "answer": "a. It leads to a SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "1277. A SIGMET....",
    "options": [
      "a. is a warning of meteorological hazards in the FIR for all aircraft",
      "b. is a route forecast, issued several times during the day by the Met Offices",
      "c. is added as a short-term forecast to the actual weather report of an airport",
      "d. reports the actual weather of an airport every 30 minutes"
    ],
    "answer": "a. is a warning of meteorological hazards in the FIR for all aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "1278. TAF LSZH 1322 22018G35KT 9999 SCT012 BKN030 BECMG 1315 25025G45KT BECMG 1820 4000 RA BKN025 BECMG 2022 25015KT T1815Z T1618Z = Which statement is true at 15 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. met. vis. 4000 metres, gusts of 25 KT, temperature 18\u00b0C",
      "b. met. vis. 10 km or more, ceiling 3000 ft, wind from 250 degrees, temperature 18\u00b0C",
      "c. met. vis. 10 km or more, ceiling 1200 ft, gusts of 45 KT",
      "d. strong rain showers, met. vis. 4000 metres, temperature 15\u00b0C, gusts of 35 KT"
    ],
    "answer": "c. met. vis. 10 km or more, ceiling 1200 ft, gusts of 45 KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "1279. Refer to the TAF below: What are the weather conditions you have to expect at 1200UTC on Zurich airport? TAF LSZH 0716 00000KT 0100FG VV001 BECMG 0810 0800 VV002 BECMG 1012 23005KT 2500 BKN005 TEMPO 1316 6000 SCT007 =",
    "options": [
      "a. met. vis. 800 metres, vertical vis. 200ft, calm",
      "b. met. vis. 6 km, ceiling 500 ft, wind from 230 degrees",
      "c. met. vis. 2,5 km, ceiling 500 ft, wind speed 5 KT",
      "d. met. vis. 800 m, wind direction 230 degrees, ceiling 500 ft"
    ],
    "answer": "c. met. vis. 2,5 km, ceiling 500 ft, wind speed 5 KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "1280. For your flight from Zurich to Rome you consult, amongst other information, the following SIGMET: SIGMET VALID121420/121820 MOD TO SEV CAT OBS AND FCST S OF ALPS BTN FL 260 AND FL 380 / STNR / INTSF =",
    "options": [
      "a. You select a flight level below FL 260 due to turbulence",
      "b. You select a flight level between FL 260 and FL 380 due to turbulence",
      "c. You delay your departure until 18.20 LT to avoid the icing conditions between FL 260 and FL 380",
      "d. You disregard this SIGMET, because it does not affect your flight"
    ],
    "answer": "a. You select a flight level below FL 260 due to turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "1281. Compare the following TAF and VOLMET reports for Nice: TAF 240716 VRB02KT CAVOK = 0920Z 13012KT 8000 SCT040CB BKN100 20/18 Q1015 TEMPO TS = What can be concluded from the differences between the two reports ?",
    "options": [
      "a. That the weather in Nice after 0920 is also likely to be as predicted in the TAF",
      "b. That the weather conditions at 0920 were actually predicted in the TAF",
      "c. That the weather at Nice is clearly more volatile than the TAF could have predicted earlier in the morning",
      "d. That the VOLMET speaker has got his locations mixed up, because there is no way the latest VOLMET report could be so different from the TAF"
    ],
    "answer": "c. That the weather at Nice is clearly more volatile than the TAF could have predicted earlier in the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "1282. Marseille Information gives you the following meteorological information for Ajaccio and Calvi for 16:00 UTC : Ajaccio: wind 360\u00b0/2 kt, visibility 2000 m, rain, BKN stratocumulus at 1000 FT, OVC altostratus at 8000 FT, QNH 1023 hPa. Calvi: wind 040\u00b0/2 kt, visibility 3000 m, mist, FEW stratus at 500 FT, SCT stratocumulus at 2000 FT, OVC altostratus at 9000 FT, QNH 1023 hPa. The",
    "options": [
      "a. 1000 FT at Ajaccio and 2000 FT at Calvi",
      "b. 1000 FT at Ajaccio and 500 FT at Calvi",
      "c. 8000 FT at Ajaccio and 9000 FT at Calvi",
      "d. 1000 FT at Ajaccio and 9000 FT at Calvi"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 1000 FT at Ajaccio and 500 FT at Calvi"
  },
  {
    "question": "1283. ATIS information contains",
    "options": [
      "a. operational information and if necessary meteorological information",
      "b. only meteorological information",
      "c. meteorological and operational information",
      "d. only operational information"
    ],
    "answer": "c. meteorological and operational information"
  },
  {
    "question": "1284. Which airport, at 1200 UTC, has the lowest probability of precipitation?",
    "options": [
      "a. ESSA",
      "b. LSZH",
      "c. ENFB",
      "d. EFHK"
    ],
    "answer": "b. LSZH"
  },
  {
    "question": "1285. Over Paris at what height would you expect to find the tropopause according to the map?",
    "options": [
      "a. approx.30000 FT",
      "b. approx. 36000 FT",
      "c. approx. 15000 FT",
      "d. approx. 28000 FT"
    ],
    "answer": "a. approx.30000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "1286. What is the optimum flight level between Rome and Paris according to the significant weather chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 340",
      "b. FL 200",
      "c. FL 160",
      "d. FL 180"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 200"
  },
  {
    "question": "1287. Flight Zurich to Rome, ETD 1600 UTC, ETA 1800 UTC. At what flight level would you first expect to encounter clear air turbulence on the climb out from Zurich?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 140",
      "b. FL 160",
      "c. FL 320",
      "d. FL 220"
    ],
    "answer": "d. FL 220"
  },
  {
    "question": "1288. What is the approximate height of the tropopause between Munich and Helsinki?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 340",
      "b. FL 280",
      "c. FL 300",
      "d. FL 390"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 340"
  },
  {
    "question": "1289. You are flying from Munich to Amsterdam. Which of the following flight levels would you choose in order to avoid turbulence and icing?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 140",
      "b. FL 320",
      "c. FL 180",
      "d. FL 260"
    ],
    "answer": "d. FL 260"
  },
  {
    "question": "1290. In what height range and at what intensity could you encounter turbulence in CAT area n\u00b02?",
    "options": [
      "a. From FL 220 to FL 400, moderate",
      "b. From FL 220 to FL 350, moderate",
      "c. From below FL 220 to FL 400, moderate, occasionally severe",
      "d. From FL 240 to FL 370, light, occasionally moderate"
    ],
    "answer": "a. From FL 220 to FL 400, moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "1291. At what flight level is the jet stream core that is situated over Germany?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 280",
      "b. FL 330",
      "c. FL 360",
      "d. FL 300"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 330"
  },
  {
    "question": "1292. How may the correct wind speed be found, for a level, which is between two upper air chart levels? (e.g. wind at FL 250, when the 500 hPa and the 300 hPa chart are available).",
    "options": [
      "a. By interpolation of the wind information available from the two charts, while also considering the maximum wind information found on the Significant Weather Chart.",
      "b. By simple interpolation of wind information available from the two charts.",
      "c. By reading wind direction and speed from the next higher chart.",
      "d. By reading wind direction and speed from the 300 hPa chart."
    ],
    "answer": "a. By interpolation of the wind information available from the two charts, while also considering the maximum wind information found on the Significant Weather Chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "1293. Why are indications about the height of the tropopause not essential for flight documentation in the tropics?",
    "options": [
      "a. The meteorological services are unable to provide such a chart.",
      "b. The tropopause is generally well above the flight level actually flown.",
      "c. The temperatures of the tropical tropopause are always very cold and therefore not important.",
      "d. Tropopause informations are of no value."
    ],
    "answer": "b. The tropopause is generally well above the flight level actually flown."
  },
  {
    "question": "1294. If you are flying from Zurich to Shannon at FL 340, where will your cruising altitude be?",
    "options": [
      "a. Constantly in the troposphere",
      "b. Constantly in the stratosphere",
      "c. First in the troposphere and later in the stratosphere",
      "d. In the stratosphere for part of time"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Constantly in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "1295. Which of these statements is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. Turbulence is likely to be encountered at FL 410 over Madrid",
      "b. Freezing level above Madrid is higher than FL 120",
      "c. The front to the north of London is moving south",
      "d. Scattered thunderstorms can be expected over France"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Scattered thunderstorms can be expected over France"
  },
  {
    "question": "1296. On which of these routes would you not need to worry about icing at FL 220?",
    "options": [
      "a. Zurich - Hamburg",
      "b. Zurich - Madrid",
      "c. Hamburg - Stockholm",
      "d. Shannon - Zurich"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Hamburg - Stockholm"
  },
  {
    "question": "1297. What is the wind direction and speed at 3 000 FT overhead position \"Q\" at 0600 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. 270\u00b0 30 kt.",
      "b. 270\u00b0 15 kt.",
      "c. 240\u00b0 25 kt.",
      "d. 240\u00b0 20 kt."
    ],
    "answer": "a. 270\u00b0 30 kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "1298. At which airport, is the following weather development taking place? (Chart 0600 UTC) TAF 060716 25006KT 8000 BKN240 BECMG 0710 OVC200 BECMG 1013 23010KT 8000 OVC100 BECMG 1316 23014KT 6000 RA SCT030 OVC050 =",
    "options": [
      "a. EGLL",
      "b. LFPO",
      "c. EDDF",
      "d. LEMD"
    ],
    "answer": "c. EDDF"
  },
  {
    "question": "1299. What weather conditions are expected at Paris airport (LFPO) around 1300 UTC?",
    "options": [
      "a. 23014KT 3000 +RA SCT008 OVC025 15/13 Q1004 NOSIG =",
      "b. 26012KT 9999 SCT025 SCT040 14/09 Q1018 TEMPO 5000 SHRA =",
      "c. 22020G36KT 1500 TSGR SCT004 BKN007 BKN025CB 18/13 Q1009 BECMG NSW =",
      "d. 20004KT 8000 SCT110 SCT250 22/08 Q1016 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "a. 23014KT 3000 +RA SCT008 OVC025 15/13 Q1004 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1300. Over Madrid, what intensity of turbulence and icing is forecast at FL 200 ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Moderate turbulence and icing",
      "b. Moderate turbulence, light icing",
      "c. Severe turbulence, moderate icing",
      "d. Severe turbulence, severe icing"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Moderate turbulence and icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "1301. At what approximate flight level is the tropopause over Frankfurt?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 300",
      "b. FL 330",
      "c. FL 350",
      "d. FL 240"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 330"
  },
  {
    "question": "1302. Select from the map the wind for the route Zurich - London at FL 280.",
    "options": [
      "a. 040 / 60",
      "b. 250 / 80",
      "c. 220 / 50",
      "d. 160 / 90"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 220 / 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "1303. What is the average wind at FL 160 between Zurich and Rome ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 050/40",
      "b. 020/50",
      "c. 200/45",
      "d. 200/40"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 020/50"
  },
  {
    "question": "1304. The temperature at FL 330 overhead London will be",
    "options": [
      "a. -42\u00b0C",
      "b. -30\u00b0C",
      "c. -33\u00b0C",
      "d. -57\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "d. -57\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1305. What wind is forecast at FL 390 over Paris ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 030/40",
      "b. 230/20",
      "c. 210/40",
      "d. 190/40"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 210/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "1306. What is the average temperature at FL 160 between Oslo and Paris ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -11\u00b0C",
      "b. -23\u00b0C",
      "c. -19\u00b0C",
      "d. -25\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -19\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1307. What is the temperature deviation in degrees Celsius, from the International Standard Atmosphere overhead Frankfurt ?",
    "options": [
      "a. ISA + 2\u00b0C",
      "b. ISA -13\u00b0C",
      "c. ISA +13\u00b0C",
      "d. ISA +8\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. ISA -13\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1308. What is the speed of the front located over France?",
    "options": [
      "a. 30 kt",
      "b. 25 kt",
      "c. 10 kt",
      "d. 15 kt"
    ],
    "answer": "d. 15 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1309. Flight Munich to London. What is the direction and maximum speed of the jet stream affecting the route between Munich and London ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 230\u00b0 / 120 kt",
      "b. 220\u00b0 / 120 km/h",
      "c. 050\u00b0 / 120 kt",
      "d. 230\u00b0 / 120 m/sec"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 230\u00b0 / 120 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1310. Flight Shannon to London. What is forecast for the eastern sector of the route between Shannon and London at FL 220 ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Scattered towering cumulus",
      "b. Overcast nimbo layered cumulonimbus",
      "c. Moderate or severe turbulence and icing",
      "d. Scattered castellanus"
    ],
    "answer": "c. Moderate or severe turbulence and icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "1311. Over Amsterdam, what amount and general type of cloud would you expect at FL 160 ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Mainly 5 to 8 oktas",
      "b. 4 oktas broken cumulus",
      "c. Isolated cumulonimbus only",
      "d. 5 to 7 oktas towering cumuliform cloud and with moderate turbulence"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Mainly 5 to 8 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "1312. To what extent is Munich covered by clouds ?",
    "options": [
      "a. 5 to 8 oktas",
      "b. 1 to 4 oktas",
      "c. 5 to 7 oktas",
      "d. 3 to 5 oktas"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 5 to 8 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "1313. What OAT would you expect at FL 200 over Geneva ?",
    "options": [
      "a. -24\u00b0C",
      "b. -20\u00b0C",
      "c. -16\u00b0C",
      "d. -28\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -24\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1314. Assuming a normal vertical temperature gradient, at what altitude will the freezing level above Tunis be found?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 100",
      "b. FL 20",
      "c. FL 180",
      "d. FL 240"
    ],
    "answer": "a. FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "1315. What is the mean temperature deviation from ISA for the Frankfurt - Roma route?",
    "options": [
      "a. 9\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "b. 4\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "c. 4\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "d. 9\u00b0C warmer than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "c. 4\u00b0C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "1316. Select from the map the average wind for the route Athens - Geneva at FL 160.",
    "options": [
      "a. 240/40",
      "b. 210/25",
      "c. 260/40",
      "d. 050/35"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 240/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "1317. Select from the map the average temperature for the route Athens - Geneva at FL 150.",
    "options": [
      "a. -21\u00b0C",
      "b. -14\u00b0C",
      "c. -11\u00b0C",
      "d. -27\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "b. -14\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1318. What is the deviation of the temperature at FL 140 above Copenhagen compared to ISA?",
    "options": [
      "a. 4\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "b. 9\u00b0C colder than ISA",
      "c. 9\u00b0C warmer than ISA",
      "d. 12\u00b0C colder than ISA"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 9\u00b0C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "1319. Select from the map the average wind for the route Zurich - Hamburg at FL 240.",
    "options": [
      "a. 230/15",
      "b. 020/20",
      "c. 200/15",
      "d. 260/25"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 230/15"
  },
  {
    "question": "1320. Select from the map the average temperature for the route Zurich - Lisboa at FL 200.",
    "options": [
      "a. -33\u00b0C",
      "b. -30\u00b0C",
      "c. -41\u00b0C",
      "d. -49\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "a. -33\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1321. Select from the map the average wind for the route Shannon - Lisboa at FL 290.",
    "options": [
      "a. 030/70",
      "b. 360/80",
      "c. 190/75",
      "d. 340/90"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 360/80"
  },
  {
    "question": "1322. Select from the map the average temperature for the route Geneva -Stockholm at FL 260.",
    "options": [
      "a. -55\u00b0C",
      "b. -51\u00b0C",
      "c. -47\u00b0C",
      "d. -63\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -47\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1323. On which of the following routes can you expect icing to occur, on the basis of the chart?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rome - Frankfurt",
      "b. Hamburg - Oslo",
      "c. Tunis - Rome",
      "d. Copenhagen - Helsinki"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Rome - Frankfurt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1324. Looking at the chart, at what altitude above Frankfurt would you expect the tropopause to be located?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 310",
      "b. FL 350",
      "c. FL 250",
      "d. FL 280"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 350"
  },
  {
    "question": "1325. If you are flying from Zurich to London at FL 220, what conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. Flight largely in cloud; no turbulence",
      "b. Scattered thunderstorms",
      "c. Prolonged severe turbulence and icing throughout the flight",
      "d. CAT for the first half of the flight"
    ],
    "answer": "b. Scattered thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "1326. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "options": [
      "a. Thunderclouds have formed over the Iberian peninsula extending to some 25000 meters",
      "b. The jet stream above Italy has a maximum speed of 120 km/h",
      "c. The front to the north of Frankfurt is moving north-east at about 5 kt",
      "d. There is no significant cloud above Rome"
    ],
    "answer": "c. The front to the north of Frankfurt is moving north-east at about 5 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1327. On which of these routes would you not have to worry about turbulence at FL 340?",
    "options": [
      "a. Rome - Berlin",
      "b. Zurich - Rome",
      "c. Zurich - Athens",
      "d. Shannon - Hamburg"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Shannon - Hamburg"
  },
  {
    "question": "1328. If you are flying from Zurich to Stockholm at FL 240, what conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "options": [
      "a. Out of cloud throughout the flight",
      "b. Cloud most of the way; little chance of CAT",
      "c. Scattered thunderstorms",
      "d. Largely free of cloud; moderate icing half way along the route"
    ],
    "answer": "d. Largely free of cloud; moderate icing half way along the route"
  },
  {
    "question": "1329. Judging by the chart, what windspeeds can you expect at FL 340 above Rome?",
    "options": [
      "a. 340 kt",
      "b. 145 kt",
      "c. 95 kt",
      "d. 140 km/h"
    ],
    "answer": "b. 145 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "1330. Judging by the chart, on which of these routes can you expect to encounter moderate and locally severe CAT at FL 300?",
    "options": [
      "a. Zurich - Rome",
      "b. London - Zurich",
      "c. Zurich - Copenhagen",
      "d. Paris - Bordeaux"
    ],
    "answer": "a. Zurich - Rome"
  },
  {
    "question": "1331. To which aerodrome is the following TAF most applicable ? TAF 231019 24014KT 6000 SCT030 BKN100 TEMPO 1113 25020G38KT 2500 +TSRA SCT008 BKN025CB BECMG 1315 28012KT 9999 SCT025 TEMPO 5000 SHRA BKN020 BECMG 1719 27008KT 9999 SCT030",
    "options": [
      "a. LFPG",
      "b. LEMD",
      "c. LOWW",
      "d. EKCH"
    ],
    "answer": "c. LOWW"
  },
  {
    "question": "1332. At which airport is the following weather development taking place? TAF 231322 24014G32KT 4000 +TSRA SCT005 BKN015 BKN020CB BECMG 1416 29012KT 9999 BKN030TCU SCT100 TEMPO 8000 SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 1922 27012KT 9999 SCT030 OVC220 = (chart 1200 UTC)",
    "options": [
      "a. EINN",
      "b. ESSA",
      "c. ENFB",
      "d. EKCH"
    ],
    "answer": "a. EINN"
  },
  {
    "question": "1333. Which of the following weather conditions would be expected at Athens Airport (LGAT) at around 1450 UTC? (chart 1200 UTC)",
    "options": [
      "a. 26014KT 8000 BKN090 17/12 Q1009 BECMG 4000 =",
      "b. 16002KT 0200 R33L/0600N FG VV001 12/12 Q1031 BECMG 0800 =",
      "c. 21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 Q1026 NOSIG =",
      "d. 23018G35KT 9999 SCT035 10/04 Q0988 NOSIG ="
    ],
    "answer": "c. 21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 Q1026 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "1334. Which airport is most likely to have fog in the coming night?",
    "options": [
      "a. ENFB",
      "b. LSZH",
      "c. EKCH",
      "d. ESSA"
    ],
    "answer": "b. LSZH"
  },
  {
    "question": "1335. Select from the map the average wind for the route Zurich - Rome at FL110.",
    "options": [
      "a. 230/10",
      "b. 200/30",
      "c. 040/10",
      "d. 250/20"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 230/10"
  },
  {
    "question": "1336. Select from the map the average temperature for the route Zurich - Rome at FL 110.",
    "options": [
      "a. -6\u00b0C",
      "b. -12\u00b0C",
      "c. -9\u00b0C",
      "d. +5\u00b0C"
    ],
    "answer": "c. -9\u00b0C"
  },
  {
    "question": "1337. Look at the chart. Assuming a normal vertical temperature gradient, at what altitude will the freezing level above Shannon be found?",
    "options": [
      "a. FL 20",
      "b. FL 60",
      "c. FL 140",
      "d. FL 120"
    ],
    "answer": "b. FL 60"
  },
  {
    "question": "1338. Select from the map the average wind for the route Frankfurt - Roma at FL 170.",
    "options": [
      "a. 230/40",
      "b. 200/50",
      "c. 050/40",
      "d. 030/35"
    ],
    "answer": "a. 230/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "1339. 8/8 stratus base 200 FT/AGL is observed at sunrise at an aerodrome in the north of France; the QNH is 1028 hPa and there is a variable wind of 3 kt. What change in these clouds is likely at 12:00 UTC in summer and winter?",
    "options": [
      "a. Winter: BKN base 2500 FT/AGL; summer BKN base 3500 FT/AGL.",
      "b. Winter: clear sky; summer BKN CB base 1500 FT/AGL.",
      "c. Winter: OVC base 500 FT/AGL; summer SCT base 3000 FT/AGL.",
      "d. Winter: SCT base 3000 FT/AGL; summer OVC base 500 FT/AGL."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Winter: OVC base 500 FT/AGL; summer SCT base 3000 FT/AGL."
  },
  {
    "question": "1340. A pilot is warned of severe icing at certain flight levels by information supplied in",
    "options": [
      "a. TAF and SIGMET",
      "b. TAF and METAR",
      "c. METAR and SIGMET",
      "d. SWC and SIGMET"
    ],
    "answer": "d. SWC and SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "1341. What units are used to report vertical wind shear?",
    "options": [
      "a. kt.",
      "b. kt/100 FT.",
      "c. m/100 FT.",
      "d. m/sec."
    ],
    "answer": "b. kt/100 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "1342. Which of the following weather reports is a warning of conditions that could be potentially hazardous to aircraft in flight ?",
    "options": [
      "a. SPECI.",
      "b. ATIS.",
      "c. SIGMET.",
      "d. TAF."
    ],
    "answer": "c. SIGMET."
  },
  {
    "question": "1343. In which of the following circumstances is a SIGMET issued ?",
    "options": [
      "a. Clear ice on the runways of an aerodrome.",
      "b. Fog or a thunderstorm at an aerodrome.",
      "c. Marked mountain waves.",
      "d. A sudden change in the weather conditions contained in the METAR."
    ],
    "answer": "c. Marked mountain waves."
  }
]